<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 6</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 6</title>
          <date when="2025-08-04">August 04, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-08-04" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="15-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Hd1e97">Section 6</head>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e99">
          § 6
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e106">
          Nevertheless for a greater declaration and solution of this object 
          some considerations should be put forward.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e115">
          The first consideration is that 
          since the domnions and jurisdictions, 
          status and royal dignities are 
          belong to infidels by the 
          law of nations (ius gentium) and natural law, 
          and have been confirmed by both 
          divine law and especially evangelical law,
          it is manifest that the catholic faith or the Christian religion 
          do not deprive infidel kings or lords from their status, 
          dignities, and goods or other rights and dominion 
          which they have over their subjects by natural law and the law of the people,
          but on the contrary the faith justifies these rights.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e138">
          And that they have been approved by divine law is clear 
          from the old law in which it is mentioned a thousand times 
          about infidel and idolatrous kings. 
          Of the first king Nimrod, in Genesis 10: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e155">the beginning of his kingdom was Babylon</quote>. 
          And also the four kings of Sodom and Gomorrah in Genesis 14.
          And the thirty kings of Canaan, in the book of Numbers. 
          And throughout nearly all books of divine scripture 
          there is frequent memory of idolatrous kings. 
          And, while not mentioning many other things, 
          Nebuchadnezzar is called king by the divine mouth itself: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e169">Behold, he says, I will bring against Tyre
          Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon from the north, king of kings, with horses</quote> etc.
          And to this Daniel said, not for the sake of flattery
          but in order to reveal the truth,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e183">
            you are the king of kings
            and the God of heaven gave to the kingdom and fortitude and empyreum and glory
          </quote>
          etc
          <ref>Daniel 2</ref>.
          From this therefore God 
          his own scriptures calls kings those who are infidels and even idolatrous kings. 
          They are kings 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e195">
            because he himself said it and it was done
          </quote>. 
          <ref>Psalm 148</ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e179">
          And the patriarchs and prophets also showed reverence and obedience 
          to the infidel, idolatrous, and wicked kings 
          under whose rule they lived, as saint Joseph did to Pharaoh, 
          Daniel to Nebuchadnezzar, Mordecai and Esther to Ahasuerus,
          and in Baruch chapter 1, it is said, 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e220">
            Pray for the life of Nebuchadnezzar, 
            king of Babylon, 
            and for the life of Belshazzar, 
            his son, that their days may be like the days of heaven on earth, 
            so that we may live under the shadow of Nebuchadnezzar 
            and the shadow of Belshazzar, his son,
            and serve them for many days
          </quote> etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e203">
          The Prophetic King David also honored Saul 
          after God had withdrawn from him because he was still the king 
          and was so as long as he lived.
          Thus Augustine says in his questions on the old and new testament, question 35,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e247">
            For what reason did David call Saul the anointed of the Lord 
            and give honor to him after God had left him. 
            David was not unaware that the divine tradition 
            is in the office of the royal order. 
            Therefore he honored Saul in this same tradition, 
            lest he would seem to do injury to God, 
            who had decreed that there should be honor for these orders.
            For the king has the image of God, just as the bishop bears the image of Christ, 
            therefore as long as he is in this tradition 
            the king should be honored, 
            even if not for his own sake or on account of the order.
            Thus the apostle says in Romans 13. 
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e270">
              Be subject to the higher authorities, 
              for there is no power unless it is from God. 
              For those powers that exist are from God
            </quote>.
            this is the reason why when a gentile is in power 
            we still honor them, even though they are unworthy
            and, while holding God's office, are actually serving the devil. 
            For power demands honor because it deserves honor. 
            For thus a future famine was revealed in a dream to the pharoah, 
            and Nabechadnezzar along among those assisting him 
            saw the son of God in the furnace, 
            not because he had his own merit, 
            for he wanted to be worshipped in his own idol, 
            but through the merit of the royal order</quote>.
            This is what Augustine says in the text.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e258">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Behold how infidel,
          idolatrous,
          and most wicked kings have kingdom,
          empire,
          strength and glory,
          that is,
          the excellence of dignity and the royal order from the God of heaven,
          and are in the tradition,
          that is,
          in the royal office constituted by God,
          although infidels,
          and therefore merit honor and reverence,
          bearing the image of God.
          Hence it appears that the aforesaid dignities and royal states,
          domains and jurisdictions,
          were introduced by natural and common law,
          confirmed by the divine law of the Old Testament.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e284">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          That they are approved and confirmed by the evangelical law,
          there are innumerable authorities.
          And the first is thus,
          this of the very author of justice,
          Christ:
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Rd1e294">
            Matthew 22
          </ref>
          ,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e296" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt22_21@7-11">
            Render to Caesar the things that are Caesar's
          </quote>
          , etc.
          By which words he taught that tribute and royal rights should be rendered to Caesar,
          an ethnic infidel,
          and in him to all other ethnic idolaters and infidels.
          Render,
          he says,
          not give,
          because to render signifies payment;
          but payment presupposes a debt.
          For tribute is owed even to infidel kings by the obligation of natural justice,
          as is clear in Romans where above:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e310" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_7@1-15">
            Render to all their dues:
            tribute to whom tribute is due,
            custom to whom custom,
            honor to whom honor
          </quote>
          , etc.
          For the Apostle was speaking of infidel princes,
          with whom the world was then full,
          <pb ed="#B" n="16-r"/>
          whom nevertheless he calls ministers of God serving in this very thing.
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e325" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_5@1-4">
            Therefore by necessity be subject
          </quote>
          .
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e329">
          The solicitous apostles strove to promulgate this same thing to all the faithful 
          and first Christians,
          commanding that they observe obedience and honor and rights to infidel princes 
          as one of the divine precepts of the evangelical law.
          1 Timothy 6:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e339" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_1@1-17 http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_2@1-16">
            Whosoever are under the yoke 
            (interlinear gloss:
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e343" source="http://scta.info/resource/go-Itim6-d1e99@1-1">
              of infidels
            </quote>
            , servants),
            let us deem their masters worthy of all honor,
            lest the name of the Lord be blasphemed.
            But those who have faithful masters,
            let them not despise them,
            but rather serve them,
            because they are faithful
          </quote>
          . And to Titus 3:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e357" source="http://scta.info/resource/tit3_1@1-13">
            Admonish them to be subject to princes and powers,
            to obey commands,
            to be ready for every good work
          </quote>
          , etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e365">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Having your conversation,
          that is,
          exterior acts and works,
          good among the gentiles (that is,
          living among gentiles and infidels,
          so that you may provoke them to faith according to Saint Thomas),
          so that in that which they speak against you as evildoers—
          because through the indiscretion and pride of some of those already converted to the faith,
          after receiving the faith they said that the faithful were not bound to obey infidel princes—
          therefore infidel lords complained and blasphemed the faith as unjust,
          because it removed the rights of nature and the condition or order of human condition 
          as if unjust and evildoers.
          And it follows: from good works,
          that is,
          from the due obedience and showing of subjection 
          (by which you were bound to your lords before your conversion),
          considering you,
          they may glorify God in the day of visitation,
          that is,
          of calling or of your conversion or theirs.
          And blessed Peter immediately infers the conclusion which he intended:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e400">
            Be subject therefore to every human creature
          </quote>
          (the gloss and Saint Thomas there:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e405">
            to faithful and unbelievers
          </quote>
          ).
          These things that one and the other.
          And it is an accommodated distribution for those under whose power they were,
          for God's sake,
          that is,
          with God so ordaining:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e411">
            whether to the king as supreme,
            or to governors
          </quote>
          , because this is the will of God,
          that by doing well,
          that is,
          by thus obeying,
          you may make silent,
          withdrawing from them the material of complaining and blaspheming,
          the ignorance of imprudent men,
          that is,
          of infidels.
          And shortly after:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e426">
            Fear God,
            honor the king.
            Servants be subject in all fear,
            not only to the good and modest,
            but to the harsh,
            that is,
            to infidels
          </quote>
          .
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e437">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Rd1e442">
            Paul in 1 Timothy 6
          </ref>
          commanded that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e447" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim2_1@6-13 http://scta.info/resource/Itim2_2@1-14">
            supplications,
            prayers,
            thanksgivings be made for kings and all who are,
            or were,
            constituted in high position,
            that we may lead a quiet and tranquil life
          </quote>
          .
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e460">
          For it is manifest that at the time when the Apostles promulgated these precepts 
          to the faithful and first Christians,
          the whole world (as we said)
          <pb ed="#B" n="16-v"/>
          was full of infidel princes or kings,
          and no king or prince was faithful.
          Therefore the dignities and royal states,
          domains and jurisdictions,
          and royal rights which are among infidels were and are approved and confirmed 
          by the divine law of the New Testament,
          or by the evangelical law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e482">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But that the faith of Christ and the Christian religion do not deprive 
          infidel kings or princes of their domains,
          states and dignities,
          jurisdictions and rights,
          etc.,
          which pertain to kings and the authority and excellence of kings,
          is already clear from what has been adduced.
          Because if God through the divine law of the Old Testament,
          and again through the new evangelical law,
          confirmed and established all the aforesaid,
          therefore it would be blasphemous to think that he would have revoked them through the faith,
          and much less the infidels themselves by receiving the faith.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e505">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But let us add other particular reasons and authorities.
          And the first is this:
          The order of superiority by which men are subject to their princes 
          is an order of natural justice instituted by God,
          according to Romans 13:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e516" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_1@7-20 http://scta.info/resource/rom13_2@1-7">
            There is no power except from God;
            but those things which are from God,
            he resists the ordination
          </quote>
          . And he speaks of the order by which inferiors are subdued to their superiors.
          But the faith of Christ is the principle and cause of justice,
          according to Romans 3:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e528" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom3_22@1-11">
            The justice of God through faith in Jesus Christ,
            unto all and upon all who believe in him
          </quote>
          . Therefore through the faith of Christ the order of justice is not removed,
          but rather confirmed.
          But the order of justice requires that inferiors obey their superiors,
          whether they be faithful or infidels,
          because justice extends not only to the faithful but also to all men universally.
          Therefore infidel princes,
          or even their subjects,
          especially by receiving the faith,
          do not lose their domains,
          jurisdictions,
          dignities,
          and rights owed.
          For this would be to be of better condition in their infidelity than existing 
          in Christianity and in the holy Church,
          contrary to what is held in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Rd1e559">
            c. iudei. el. 2o, extra, de iudeis et sarracenis
          </ref>
          , where it is commanded under penalty of excommunication 
          that for Jews coming to the faith,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e563" source="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t6-d1e180@55-71">
            their possessions should not be taken away,
            since those converted to the faith ought to be of better condition 
            than they were held before they received the faith
          </quote>
          . These things there.
          <pb ed="#B" n="17-r"/>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e575">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The same and more is contained in a certain extravagant of John 22,
          subtitle concerning Jews in the community.
          Judging it worthy,
          he says,
          and consonant with law that those reborn from the font of baptism,
          with Jewish blindness dismissed,
          should abound in more ample favors or graces than before,
          it is indecent and absurd that those who abounded in perfidy 
          should be compelled to beg as faithful.
          And below:
          We strictly command and mandate that to such converted ones 
          and those who will be converted in the future,
          in their possessions and other goods,
          by whatever name they may be called,
          which they held at the time of conversion or even will hold,
          no molestation should be inflicted on account of the aforesaid occasion,
          nor should they permit it to be inflicted by others,
          but showing themselves favorable to them in these and other things,
          they should protect and defend them from injuries and molestations,
          so that thus they may perceive that they have passed from servitude to freedom,
          nor should they be compelled by the pretext of hateful mendicity 
          to return to the dismissed perfidy.
          These things there.
          For indeed,
          in truth,
          a great disgrace would be done to the Catholic faith,
          since the Christian religion would be esteemed as unjust and tyrannical 
          and would be held in hatred,
          and consequently we would provide material for blaspheming Christ the Lord,
          the bearer of the evangelical law,
          if we should attempt the contrary of the aforesaid,
          as is manifest.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e624">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second reason:
          If through this faith the grace of the Holy Spirit is given,
          which is principally called the evangelical law itself,
          but grace does not remove nature but perfects and supplies the defect of nature,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Rd1e638">
            Saint Thomas 1st part q. 2 article 6 ad 1
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Rd1e640">
            2-2 q. 188 article 8
          </ref>
          , but principalities and powers,
          domains and jurisdictions which are among infidels of whatever nation,
          sect,
          or religion they exist (except however the Jews after the death of Christ),
          pertain to those by natural and common law,
          which laws the evangelical divine law and the grace of the Holy Spirit has restored,
          augmented,
          confirmed according to Augustine,
          perfected and supplied according to Saint Thomas.
          Therefore infidels,
          especially by receiving the faith,
          do not lose their principalities,
          dignities,
          powers,
          etc.,
          but rather are confirmed and participate in them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e674">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Third,
          it is proven by authorities.
          <pb ed="#B" n="17-v"/>
          And first Augustine on John 18,
          expounding that word 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e683" source="http://scta.info/resource/io18_36@3-9">
            My kingdom is not of this world
          </quote>
          :
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e688" source="http://scta.info/resource/iuy75t-d1e982-d1e257@2-73">
            Hear,
            he says,
            therefore,
            Jews and gentiles;
            hear,
            circumcision;
            hear,
            foreskin;
            hear,
            all kingdoms of the earth:
            I do not impede your dominion in this world;
            my kingdom is not of this world.
            Do not fear with most vain fear by which that greater Herod,
            when it was announced that Christ was born,
            was frightened and killed so many infants that death might reach him,
            fearing and becoming more cruel by anger.
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e698" source="http://scta.info/resource/io18_36@3-9">
              My kingdom,
              he says,
              is not of this world
            </quote>
            . What more do you want?
            Come to the kingdom which is not of this world;
            come by believing and do not rage by fearing
          </quote>
          , etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e710">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And on that Psalm 118:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e717" source="http://scta.info/resource/ps118_161@2-6">
            Princes have persecuted me without cause
          </quote>
          , sermon 31,
          the same Augustine:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e725">
            For what harm had Christians done to earthly kingdoms,
            <add place="margin-left">
              although their king promised them the kingdoms of heaven?
              What harm,
              I say,
              had they done to earthly kingdoms?
            </add>
            Never did their king prohibit his soldiers from paying and showing what is owed to kings of the earth.
            Did he not say to the Jews who were contriving calumny against him:
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e735" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt22_21@7-17">
              Render to Caesar the things that are Caesar's and to God the things that are God's
            </quote>
            ? Did he not himself even pay tribute from the mouth of a fish?
            Did not his precursor,
            to soldiers of this kingdom asking what they should do for eternal salvation,
            say:
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e745">
              Loose your belt,
              throw down your arms,
              desert your king,
              that you may be able to serve God
            </quote>
            ? But he said:
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e750">
              Shake down no one,
              make false accusation to no one,
              let your wages suffice you
            </quote>
            . Did not one of his soldiers and his most beloved comrade say to his fellow soldiers 
            and in the manner of Christ to his provincials:
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e760">
              Let every soul be subject to the higher powers
            </quote>
            ? And a little after he says:
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e765">
              Render to all their dues:
              tribute to whom tribute,
              custom to whom custom,
              fear to whom fear,
              honor to whom honor.
              Owe no one anything except to love one another
            </quote>
            . Did he not command that the church should pray even for those kings?
            What therefore did Christians offend them?
            That they did not render what was due?
            In what did Christians not obey earthly kings?
            Therefore earthly kings persecuted Christians without cause
          </quote>
          , etc.
          These things Augustine.
          Behold how Augustine passes sentence against those things which in our times 
          have been perpetrated by Christians concerning infidels,
          especially the Indian nations,
          concerning which ours will by no means boast,
          <pb ed="#B" n="18-r"/>
          because not without cause but most deservedly,
          if strength should supply them,
          they would persecute them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e798">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Chrysostom also on the aforesaid word:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e804">
            Every soul
          </quote>
          , etc., homily 23:
          Of this thing,
          he says,
          he makes mention very much also in other epistles,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e808">
            just as he subjects servants to their masters,
            so also subjects to their princes.
            But he does this therefore that he may show that Christ introduced his laws 
            not to overturn polities,
            but to institute them for the better,
            and at the same time to teach that superfluous and useless wars are not to be undertaken
          </quote>
          . And below:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e819">
            And he does not simply say:
            <mentioned>obey</mentioned>,
            but <mentioned>be subject</mentioned>.
            But there is the first justice of this constitution which is both sufficient 
            and decorous and honest to faithful thoughts and members,
            namely that these things are ordained by God
          </quote>
          . And far below the same Chrysostom says:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e839">
            For if Paul commanded these things when the princes were still gentiles,
            much more ought they to be shown to the faithful
          </quote>
          , etc.
          These things Chrysostom.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e850">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The authority of the universal Church confirms the aforeshown,
          which on the feast of Epiphany sings,
          reproving King Herod,
          saying:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e859">
            O impious enemy Herod,
            why do you fear that Christ is coming?
            He does not take away mortal kingdoms,
            who gives celestial kingdoms
          </quote>
          .
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e865">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Behold how manifestly it is shown by authorities and reasons,
          beyond very many others which we have more fully adduced elsewhere,
          that the law of Christ not only does not remove from infidel princes 
          their dignities and kingdoms or their royal rights,
          but rather confirms and establishes them,
          since the contrary would be to overturn the republics and the order 
          which he himself established with the Father and the Holy Spirit,
          which Saint Thomas on 1 Corinthians chapter 6 did not pass over in silence,
          saying that it is 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e883">
            against divine law to impede subjects,
            even Christians,
            from appearing whenever they have been called before infidel princes or judges
          </quote>
          . These things from him.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e891">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But if the aforealleged things do not suffice,
          let the decree and declaration of the Apostolic See itself finally suffice,
          through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Rd1e900">
            Pope Paul III,
            who in his bull beginning 
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e904">
              Sublimis Deus so loved the human race
            </quote>
          </ref>
          , where he concludes by decreeing and declaring:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-Qd1e909">
            that our Indians and all other peoples who may come to the knowledge of Christians 
            in the future,
            although they exist outside the faith of Christ,
            are nevertheless not deprived or to be deprived of their liberty 
            or of the dominion of their things;
            indeed they can use,
            possess,
            and enjoy freely and licitly this kind of liberty and dominion,
            nor ought they to be reduced into servitude,
            and that whatever may happen to be done otherwise is irritated and void,
            of no strength or moment,
            <pb ed="#B" n="18-v"/>
            and that the same Indians and other peoples are to be invited to the said faith of Christ 
            by the preaching of the word and the example of good life,
            we decree and declare by apostolic authority through the present letters
          </quote>
          , etc.
          These things there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e137-d1e938">
          Therefore it is clear that infidels justly possess kingdoms and principalities 
          and domains and jurisdictions,
          not only over infidel subjects but even over the faithful,
          if it happens that by some right or some reason they are subject to them,
          and consequently infidel kings or princes,
          especially those receiving the Catholic faith,
          do not lose their kingdoms,
          principalities,
          and other royal rights.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>