<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 10</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 10</title>
          <date when="2025-11-13">November 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="26-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Hd1e97">Section 10</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e99">
          § 10
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e104">
          The fifth consideration:
          Our kings of the Spains are bound by necessity of precept and therefore by necessity of salvation 
          both as to their first entry or that of their messengers into those Indian parts and world,
          and as to all other things which would have to be done by them concerning the aforesaid peoples,
          to order,
          moderate,
          and dispose them in such a way that they may conduce or be suitable to the aforesaid end 
          which God and his vicar intend,
          namely the preaching of the gospel and the expansion of the faith 
          and the planting of divine worship and the conversion and salvation of souls.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e132">
          And consequently they are obligated by natural and divine law to avoid and guard against 
          all those things which could totally impede the prenoted end or in any way retard it,
          or make its attainment difficult.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e141">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The first part is proven thus:
          Whoever necessarily has the duty to perfect something which is ordered to another 
          as a means to an end,
          is bound first to attend to this,
          that his work,
          that is the means,
          be congruous to the end,
          just as the smith makes a sword so that it may be suitable for fighting,
          and the builder so arranges a house that it may be apt for dwelling.
          But the advent,
          application,
          and entry 
          <pb ed="#B" n="26-v"/>
          into those parts of our kings or their messengers,
          and also the regime or government which they are about to establish,
          and the total office or jurisdiction or power newly conferred on them,
          are assumed as means conducing and helping toward the attainment of the aforesaid end,
          as can be gathered from what has been said.
          Therefore they must be congruous or suitable and patronize the aforesaid end,
          and thus conduce and help so that the end may be obtained.
          The consequence is clear,
          because according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e179">the Philosopher in Physics 2</ref>,
          of all things to be ordered to the end,
          the reasons and rules of government and of the order of law must necessarily be taken from the end,
          just as the reason for the disposition of a saw is taken from the cutting which is its end.
          And in human laws it is held that an act ordered and determined to some end 
          ought to attain that end,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e198">ff. simul herciscus l. si filia</ref>
          § Item scribit 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e202">C. ad sclli l. penultima in fine.</ref>
          Concerning this Baldus,
          By which causes a feud is lost 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e210">c. 1. nu. 5.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e204">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For then any thing is best disposed when it is suitably ordered and led to its end.
          Hence everything which is for the sake of an end must be proportioned to the end,
          so that it may help toward the attainment of the end.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e218">
          Thus therefore our kings of the Spains will then well and suitably dispose 
          their advent,
          application,
          or entry,
          or that of their messengers,
          into and to those parts of the Western and Southern Indies,
          and also their regime or government,
          jurisdiction,
          and the whole royal office,
          when in exercising all these things they will inviolably preserve to the letter 
          the order of natural law.
          For order,
          which anyone is bound to preserve,
          is the mode of doing any thing,
          or according to Baldus in the proem of the Digests at the beginning:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Qd1e238">
            It is joining principles to means and means to their ends,
            which being omitted,
            nothing is done rightly
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e255">ff. de regulis iuris l. sicut nulla</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e257">C. de sententiis et interlocutionibus l. probatam</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e262">de rescriptis c. cum dilecta</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e264">de restitutione spoliatorum c. pisanis</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e250">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But there is a twofold order:
          one induced by civil or positive law,
          and its defect does not vitiate the act or process before a prince,
          because he is not bound by laws since he is above the law,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e285" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e204-Dd1e139">
            l. digna vox C. de legibus
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e287">l. princeps ff. eo c. proposuit de concessione prebende.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e268">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But there is another order founded upon natural law,
          such as that sentence be delivered with the party summoned,
          and if that order is omitted,
          the sentence is not valid,
          as in the Clementine pastoralis 
          <pb ed="#B" n="27-r"/>
          de re iudicata,
          concerning which see 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e312">Panormitanus in c. in causis de re iudicata</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e321">Angelus in d. l. princeps</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e326">all in d. clemen. pastoralis.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e290">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          When that order is omitted,
          the faculty of defending himself is given by law to anyone,
          even against the treasury and the messengers of the prince,
          without first making faith through letters by which the justice may be made known to all 
          whose interest it is.
          To those wishing to seize the goods of others,
          even those which are borne to the treasury,
          anyone whose interest it is can resist in fact,
          and as punishment for not observing the order of law,
          the loss of the cause is even inflicted on the treasury itself,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e337" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e6196-Dd1e150">
            l. prohibitum
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e339" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e6196-Dd1e166">
            l. iustas
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e341">
            l. defensionis facultas C. de iure fisci lib. 10
          </ref>.
          And this deservedly,
          because nothing inordinate pleases the law,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e363">Baldus notes in c. dilecti El. 3. de appel.</ref>
          and the thing is assumed by others in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e368">c. Romana eo titulo lib. 6</ref>.
          And for this it is further said that a commission made by the pope against the order of law,
          among non-subjects or among laymen,
          or perhaps against laymen in patrimonial matters,
          is not valid.
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e377">John of Imola notes this in d. cap. clementina pastoralis</ref>.
          Nor can he remove the judicial order as regards the forum of laymen,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e384">the gloss notes in clementina dispendiosam de iudiciis</ref>.
          And an excellent argument that he who enters by a bad order,
          having omitted something which he ought to have done—
          for instance,
          if a consul enters the consulship having omitted the oath,
          concerning which in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e393">
            c. consules de pace constantie in libro feudarum
          </ref>
          —he is to be removed from there and also punished,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e370">l. 1 § necessario ff. si mulier ventris nomine</ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e402">
            libro feudarum de milite vasalla qui contumax est c. 1 § si vero
          </ref>,
          where it is said that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Qd1e340">
            what is done by bad order ought to be reformed
          </quote>,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e343">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But there is an order founded in natural and divine law which must necessarily be observed 
          in this business,
          so that our first entry may be pacific and the progress just,
          as will be clear below.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e354">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore,
          our kings observing the aforesaid order founded upon natural law,
          to the observance of which they are obligated by precept of divine and natural law,
          it will necessarily follow that they will be understood to have applied congruous,
          proportioned,
          and due means to such an end,
          and consequently the peoples and nations inhabiting that world will be efficaciously provoked 
          to hear the promulgation of the gospel and to receive the faith 
          and to imitate Christian and religious morals,
          and thus deservedly they will then be said to be suitably led to their end.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e383">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second part of this fifth consideration,
          which is a consequence of the first,
          namely that our kings are bound by natural and divine law to avoid all things 
          which can in any way retard or make difficult the attainment of the aforesaid end,
          <pb ed="#B" n="27-v"/>
          is proven.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e406">
          First,
          because all that which renders an action inconvenient to the end which God or nature intends 
          from some work is said to be against natural or divine law.
          But if in the advent and application or in the first entry of our kings or their messengers 
          into those Indian regions and world,
          or in the progress,
          that is,
          in the regime or government,
          or in any other of those things which necessarily must be done by our illustrious kings 
          concerning those Indian nations,
          there should happen to be some disorder,
          injustice,
          scandal,
          or some other undue work and not according to reason,
          or done against the order of law,
          which is of itself apt to generate in such infidels a sinister or perverse opinion 
          concerning the faith or Christian religion,
          and to be a cause that they may be reasonably moved with capital hatred 
          against the Christian people professing the name of Christ,
          they would render the actions of our kings,
          and those things which necessarily must be done by them concerning those peoples,
          inconvenient to and disproportioned to the end which God intends 
          and also natural reason dictates,
          namely the preaching of the gospel and the conversion of those peoples themselves,
          and also temporal peace and quiet and complete utility,
          indeed their salvation.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e452">
          Therefore our kings are bound by natural and divine law to avoid and guard against 
          all injustice,
          scandal,
          disorder,
          burdens,
          and all other things which will be of themselves apt to disturb those peoples 
          and to generate scandal among them,
          and moreover to think badly concerning faith and Christian religion or also Christian morals,
          all of which will yield to the offense of the gospel and will without doubt redound 
          to the ignominy of the name of Christ,
          and consequently,
          who,
          I pray,
          will ever doubt that it will not only retard or make difficult the attainment of the aforesaid end,
          but totally impede it?
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e474">
          The minor is clear of itself.
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But the major is from 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e481">
            Saint Thomas in 4 Sentences distinction 33 question 1 article 1 in the body 
            and article 3 in the body
          </ref>,
          where he says that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Qd1e469" source="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d33q1-d1e369@11-23">
            that action is said to be against the law of nature which is not suitable to the due end
          </quote>,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Qd1e475" source="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d33q1-d1e174@241-284" type="paraphrase">
            whether because it is of itself disproportioned to that end,
            or because it altogether impedes the end or makes difficult or less decent 
            <pb ed="#B" n="28-r"/>
            the arrival at the end.
          </quote>
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Qd1e486" source="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d33q1-d1e174@295-377">
            And if the action is inconvenient to the end as entirely prohibiting the principal end,
            it is directly prohibited by the law of nature by the first precepts of the law of nature,
            which are in operables as common conceptions are in speculative matters.
            But if making difficult or less congruous the arrival at the end itself,
            it is prohibited by the second precepts of the law of nature,
            which are derived from the first,
            just as conclusions in speculative matters have faith from self-evident principles.
            And thus the said action is said to be against the law of nature
          </quote>.
          These things Saint Thomas.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e510">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The consequence is proven because our kings are bound to observe the first and second,
          especially negative,
          precepts of the law of nature and divine law;
          otherwise they would sin mortally.
          For they are prohibited by negative precepts (as has been proven) from directly impeding the end 
          or rendering difficult the attainment of the end which God or nature intends to elicit 
          from the work of our kings,
          namely the preaching of the faith in the manner according to which it ought to be done 
          according to the form established by Christ,
          the conversion of those living in those lands and seas,
          and their complete utility,
          not only spiritual but temporal,
          since such concession or institution was introduced for their grace,
          advantage,
          and favor,
          as was proven in the third consideration.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e540">
          Therefore our kings are bound by natural and also divine law to avoid and guard against,
          both in the application and entry into those lands and in the progress,
          all disturbance,
          scandal,
          injustice,
          etc.,
          and everything by which such end can be impeded or retarded or made difficult to obtain,
          in which things indeed a negative precept is included,
          no one ought to doubt,
          namely not to make disturbance,
          not to give cause for scandal,
          not to place an offense to the gospel,
          not to impede the progress of the faith and the conversion of souls,
          not,
          finally,
          to omit applying those things which can prohibit prohibiting things,
          and many things of this kind which are contained under negative precepts 
          and are prohibited by their force.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e569">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second,
          the same second part is proven through the locus from contraries or opposites,
          because it belongs to the same to pursue one of contraries and to refute or exclude the other,
          as is clear.
          For medicine works health;
          consequently it strives to exclude illness with what force it can.
          It is of the same reason to be moved upward and downward.
          And therefore it is said that the matter,
          power,
          and discipline of contraries is the same,
          <pb ed="#B" n="28-v"/>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e671">2 De coelo et mundo</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e673">2 Rhetoricorum</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e676">1 and 6 Topicorum</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e678">4 and 8 Physicorum</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e682">11 Metaphysicae</ref>,
          and by the legists 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e646">l. et si contra in fine ff. de vulgari et pupillari</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e689">
            institut: de his qui sunt sui vel alieni iuris, in principio.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e616">
          Hence one tending toward any natural end is moved by two things,
          of which the first is the flight and removal of that which is an impediment to motion 
          toward the end and makes one deviate from the end.
          But the other is adhesion and tension of that which is leading to the end,
          and this according to the two integral parts of justice by which virtues are acquired,
          namely by declining from evil and doing good.
          Thus says 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e610">
            Henry of Ghent in his Summa of Theology article 24 question 4
          </ref>.
          And thus it is clear that avoiding the contrary of that which is intended as end 
          in mortal matters falls under the precept of natural justice.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e622">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Third,
          the same second part is proven because unless our kings guard against or avoid 
          the aforesaid contrary,
          inconvenient,
          and prohibiting things in their advent and entry,
          or that of their own,
          and similarly in the progress,
          without doubt they would be the privative cause of any good.
          For anyone is said to be,
          and is,
          the privative cause of any good,
          to whom by special law,
          as for instance from office or stipend,
          it falls to obtain something,
          and yet he omits through negligence or carelessness to remove the impediments 
          of the thing to be obtained.
          Just as a sailor is bound by his office not only to lead the ship to port,
          but truly also to guard against the ship perishing by shipwreck in the shallows while sailing.
          And soldiers who are hired are obligated not only to defend the city by fighting bravely in conflict,
          but also to keep watch and to be supremely careful lest it be captured by enemies 
          through ambushes and secretly.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e681">
          Thus also our princes of the Spains,
          who have been hired (so to speak) by the Apostolic See at great stipend,
          and by special law,
          that is,
          from the office incumbent on them,
          are bound to be supremely careful and to remove,
          not in any manner but efficaciously,
          whatever impediments by which the prementioned end can be removed or impeded or even retarded.
          Otherwise,
          if through negligence or carelessness they omit these things,
          they will without doubt be the privative cause of the aforesaid goods,
          and consequently guilty of all the evils which through such omission and carelessness 
          <pb ed="#B" n="29-r"/>
          will follow to the detriment of the faith and Christian religion and divine honor,
          and to the perdition of souls.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e684">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Fourth,
          both parts are proven at once:
          Each one is obligated by necessity of salvation to those things which are of his office,
          to the exercise of which he has obligated himself,
          and for whose exercise and expenditure he has received payment.
          But our kings have obligated themselves to exercising those things which pertain 
          to the office of kings in general,
          and beyond this by a certain peculiar law,
          that is,
          the office of apostles,
          to having care how,
          namely,
          the gospel of Christ may be preached and divine worship amplified 
          and the name of the redeemer made known to all those Indian peoples in that whole world of the Indies,
          of the peoples,
          and their salvation may be procured.
          And for the expenditure of this exercise they have received great,
          indeed maximum,
          payment,
          although without payment they could have been obligated by the Apostolic See through precept.
          Therefore they are bound by force of precept and necessity of salvation to the aforesaid two things 
          contained in this fifth consideration,
          namely by reason to proportion,
          moderate,
          and order their advent and first entry,
          or that of their own,
          and also the progress,
          that is,
          the regime and all other things which would have to be done by them 
          concerning those lands and nations inhabiting that world,
          so that they may conduce or be suitable to the preaching and expansion of the faith 
          and the conversion of souls;
          and consequently to guard against all contrary things which can stand in the way of these things,
          or remove or impede them,
          or in any way will be able to retard them.
          For both pertain to the office of the king,
          as appears from what has been said.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e769">
          The consequence is clear with the major through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e773">
            Saint Thomas 3rd part question 67 article 8 in the body
          </ref>,
          where he says that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Qd1e748">
            each one is obligated to execute the office which he receives
          </quote>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e858">on the epistle 1 to Timothy in the prologue</ref>,
          he says that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Qd1e753">
            prelates and superiors are bound by precept to those things which are of their proper office
          </quote>.
          And this obligation can be seen more clearly through the example of one 
          who assumes advocating,
          healing,
          protecting,
          and teaching,
          and thus concerning other ministry,
          and has received payment for its administration or exercise,
          as is proven through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e833">the law qui mercedem ff. locati</ref>,
          with those noted there,
          and what is read and noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e880">l. dominus in principio</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e838" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e2231-Dd1e312">
            C. mandati l.
            <pb ed="#B" n="29-v"/>
            in re mandata.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e804">
          But the minor,
          namely that our kings are also obligated by a certain peculiar law,
          etc.,
          is clear.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e812">
          First,
          from their promise which passed into a pact as soon as the pope accepted it through his letters,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e860" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e5103-Dd1e149">
            l. pactum, ff. de pollicita.
          </ref>
          Hence it is said in the aforesaid decree:
          and moreover we command you by virtue of holy obedience,
          as you also promise,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e826">
          Second,
          because by formal precept the Supreme Pontiff bound them that through suitable ministers 
          they should wish to induce the inhabitants and dwellers of the aforesaid world 
          to receive the faith and be imbued with good morals,
          etc.
          Hence he added thus:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Qd1e805">
            as you also promise (and we do not doubt,
            for your very great devotion and royal magnanimity,
            that you are going to do it),
            you ought to send to the aforesaid mainlands and islands good men fearing God,
            learned,
            skilled,
            and experienced,
            to instruct the aforesaid inhabitants and dwellers in the Catholic faith 
            and imbue them with good morals,
            applying all due diligence in the aforesaid
          </quote>,
          etc.
          These things there in form.
          Where it is clear that our kings are bound by an obligation peculiar beyond that 
          which is common to all kings to the aforesaid things.
          And we have disputed more diffusely concerning this in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-Rd1e961">
            our treatise On the War of Xalisco in the proof of a certain corollary 3 
            near the beginning of the work
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e190-d1e839">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But that our kings are in a certain way hired at a price for the aforesaid care and labor 
          is clear,
          because they have been stipended at great stipend,
          with great gifts and maximum honors and immense dignity by the supreme vicar of Christ 
          from the treasury of the Church,
          that is,
          by ecclesiastical power,
          for the office,
          namely,
          of the apostles,
          that is,
          of expanding the faith and converting souls.
          For our king is a certain apostle of those.
          Moreover,
          by temporal principate and antonomastic height,
          namely a supreme king over many and great kings,
          and also by incomparable riches of gold,
          silver,
          other metals,
          gems,
          pearls,
          emeralds,
          and of other things of that kind and various species,
          and finally by innumerable treasures,
          such as have never been heard of anywhere on earth or among peoples,
          either in number or value—
          provided,
          however,
          that our Catholic kings fulfill those things which they have promised and pledged.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>