<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 35</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 35</title>
          <date when="2025-12-13">December 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="95-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Hd1e97">Section 35</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e99">
          § 35
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e104">
          Corollary From what has been said and proven for the verification of the 5th conclusion,
          it is clear: that said papal institution or concession concerning our kings,
          from the time when our Spaniards wrongfully entered those lands until now,
          has remained suspended and in a pending state:
          just as if it had been granted and issued in Rome today.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e128">
          ¶ Some jurisdiction or faculty, or power,
          is said to be suspended or in a pending state or also that it sleeps:
          when the subject or matter about which it is to be exercised is lacking,
          or when something necessary must be added.
          Which is nothing else in reality than to have it in potentiality.
          As is clear from those things which are read and noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e148">c. ex tenore, through the Gloss</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e150">
            the Doctors, in c. licet ex suscepto de foro competere
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e160">c. Pastoralis at the end de rescriptis</ref> 
          and through the 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e165">doctors in c. si confirmationem de electione lib. 6</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e171">c. Romana de officio ordinarii</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e173">c. Romana de appellationibus in that book</ref> 
          I omit other ways by which the jurisdiction of some judge is usually suspended,
          because it falls under excommunication or suspension by law or imposed by a person:
          because they do not pertain to our purpose.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e185">
          ¶ The corollary is proven first because,
          when said promotion or institution of our kings existed in Rome,
          in order for it to achieve its effect (that is,
          so that by its power our kings might rightly and properly assume in act the principality of
          that world of the Indies and thus have full faculty of exercising jurisdiction and royal
          power),
          there was lacking most principally and necessarily something to be added or supplied,
          namely to observe those twelve things which the order of natural law contains,
          as we showed in the 2nd conclusion,
          most especially the eleventh particular of that same conclusion,
          namely the free consent of the kings and peoples of those nations,
          by which they would approve the aforesaid promotion and hold it ratified,
          and by free will receive our kings as universal lords:
          without which it will be impossible to possess that principality by law:
          as has been most fully proven: 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e220">
          so from the entry of the Spaniards through all continuous time until now,
          there has always been lacking and now is lacking that most principal and necessarily to be
          added or supplied thing:
          namely: those twelve things,
          as is clear from very many things related and decided. 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e229">
          Therefore such a promotion or papal institution has remained and now remains suspended or
          impeded.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e236">
          ¶ The corollary is proven secondly because throughout that entire time there have been
          certain legal impediments preventing said papal promotion or institution from achieving
          its effect,
          which impediments,
          as long as they endure,
          the aforesaid institution will always sleep and be pending and suspended.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e256">
          ¶ The first impediment is:
          because on account of our iniquities,
          impieties,
          tyrannical invasions,
          violences,
          approach and entry condemned by all law into those lands and foreign kingdoms,
          by which we brought such enormous calamities,
          losses,
          and irreparable damages to their inhabitants without cause:
          and on account of the continuous,
          harsh,
          and most atrocious servitude by which they are incessantly afflicted daily,
          by which they are irremediably diminished and perish:
          to which all indifferently,
          great and small,
          kings and subjects,
          have been reduced:
          namely that which they called <mentioned>repartimiento</mentioned> or 
          <mentioned>comenda</mentioned>:
          which truly has depopulated almost that entire world:
          all the inhabitants and dwellers of that entire world have gained the right to wage public
          war against us as against most vile public enemies and destroyers and cruel enemies of
          their entire race.
          War, (I say) not only of defense:
          but truly also of vengeance:
          avenging (namely) and vindicating the injuries and damages received from us:
          occupying our goods if we should have any,
          and capturing persons,
          and slaughtering:
          and also reducing into servitude and all other things which are permitted to a supreme
          prince having a just war.
          For they have just pure and mixed empire and all manner of jurisdiction and the rights of
          a prince recognizing no superior.
          And so their princes or kings have as much power in their kingdoms as the emperor has
          among the Christian people,
          as has been proven above in § 5 and following and in many of our treatises,
          especially in De bello Xalisquino
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e334">
          ¶ And pertinent to our purpose is the notable text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e341">
            c. si quis episcopus de supplenda negligentia prelatorum
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e347">the gloss there in the word <mentioned>libertati</mentioned></ref> 
          where it is held that if a bishop is captured by pagans or schismatics:
          he becomes their slave 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e356">insti. de iure personarum § ultimo</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e358">ff. de captiuis et postliminio lib. l. 5</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e363">ff. de regulis iuris, l. seruus</ref>.
          Whence it is not permitted for Christians thus captured by those Indian nations or by any
          infidels waging a just war,
          as in this case,
          to flee or depart from their infidel masters,
          nor to steal their goods,
          nor to free other Christians captured by them:
          otherwise they are bound to make restitution in the forum of conscience:
          unless there should be imminent danger of the captive abandoning the faith,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e382">
            Hostiensis in summa de penitentis et remissionibus § quibus et qualiter. 12. column with
            the words <mentioned>Quid ergo</mentioned>
          </ref> 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e389">
          ¶ Since therefore they wage the most just war against us,
          it is manifest that by the best right they can resist said papal promotion or institution
          and bitterly complain about it,
          indeed they will consider the vicar of Christ himself who made the institution to be an
          unjust and public enemy of the entire human race,
          since relying on the authority of the aforesaid institution emanating from him,
          the Spaniards have done to them,
          and they see themselves suffering such great and such evils.
          Therefore while this complaint endures and the war itself is terminated (which however the
          right of waging war against us,
          unless interrupted by truce or peace,
          or satisfaction of those causing harm,
          or voluntary remission of those harmed,
          will have no end),
          said institution will be suspended,
          sleeping,
          and pending.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e446">
          ¶ Another legal impediment is recognized to be true from this:
          because regarding the evils and damages which we have inflicted on these nations through
          nefarious wars and oppressions through such servitude:
          we have never made satisfaction,
          nor is there any hope among them that at some future time we will make satisfaction,
          nor will they voluntarily remit:
          because we do not cease to offend them,
          as will be said immediately.
          Therefore they will perpetually have the right to attack us with war.
          Therefore perpetually also the aforesaid institution will sleep and remain pending and
          suspended.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e473">
          ¶ There is a third impediment and indeed one most strongly confirmed and manifest by
          natural law:
          namely: because personal force and injury is continuously and incessantly inflicted on
          them (as has been said) since they are always held in the same most bitter servitude
          (namely the <mentioned>repartimiento</mentioned> or <mentioned>comenda</mentioned>),
          by which both the kings and natural lords,
          magistrates,
          nobles and ignobles of them,
          and all subjects universally are deprived of their natural liberty,
          dominion,
          jurisdictions,
          dignities,
          nobility,
          rights,
          and privileges:
          and all the peoples falling under are harshly and inhumanly oppressed perpetually.
          Whence force or violence is committed against them daily and continually,
          and is always being born and is in the process of happening and in a permanent or flowing
          act:
          by which continuous force is inflicted not only on the subjects and common people,
          compelling them through fear to obey tyrants and violent lords,
          as are each of our people:
          but also force is inflicted on their legitimate lords and kings.
          Indeed compulsive on those,
          but expulsive on these:
          therefore always and perpetually and continuously it can by law be resisted and repelled.
          Both to repel present violence or tyranny:
          both to protect their liberty:
          both to recover the possession of which they have been unjustly despoiled:
          both to reclaim things taken from them:
          both finally to avenge the injuries and offenses done to them.
          As is sufficiently proven in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e536">c. dominus noster. 23. q. 2</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e538">C. de probationibus l. vis eius</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e540">C. de sacrosanctis ecclesiis l. decernimus</ref> 
          and notably 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e545">
            Baldus in l. data opera C. Qui accusare non possunt penultimate column
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e553">repetitione l. 1. C. vnde vi.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e556">
          ¶ For it is the rule that it is permitted to anyone to defend his possession which he
          peacefully possesses:
          and against one attacking and attempting to eject him,
          to protect himself with arms:
          and far more strongly one having jurisdiction in a place can rush to remove every
          obstacle prepared for him,
          both against persons disturbing or impeding,
          and against the doors and walls of the place and other impediments,
          thus breaking them so that he may freely use his thing or his right.
          And if he has been ejected,
          by his own authority even if he exists as a private person,
          he can recover after many years,
          especially where there is no superior who administers justice to him.
          Which is proven by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e589">
            capitulum olim el. 1o de restitutione spoliatorum
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e593">Innocentius and the doctors there</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e595">
            c. dilecto de sententia excomunicationis lib. 6
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e600">c. significasti de homicidio</ref> 
          and in many other laws 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-Rd1e602">Baldus in l. 1 C. vnde vi, 9 column</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e608">
          ¶ Since therefore we do not cease to offend those peoples,
          holding all in that tyranny (I mean the repartimiento or comenda),
          not restoring the kings and nobles or chieftains to their dominions and dignities and
          other rights:
          and the rest of the inhabitants to their pristine liberty:
          so that thus all tyranny might cease:
          but rather adding injuries to injuries,
          evils to evils,
          burdens to burdens:
          worse things to bad things and worst to worst,
          more and more every day:
          it follows that those who exist will never be placated,
          nor will they voluntarily consent to the papal institution,
          and less will they remit the things and goods taken from them by force,
          the injuries and irreparable damages inflicted on them.
          And therefore the potentiality which our kings have acquired by virtue of the
          aforementioned papal institution:
          will not be able to come into act in perpetuity:
          both from the permanence and long duration of tyranny:
          both from the impossibility of restitution and satisfaction,
          as is clear in itself.
          Therefore meanwhile the aforesaid institution will endure suspended and pending. 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e519-d1e663">
          And consequently our Catholic kings have no power (if it is permitted to confess the
          truth) of exercising jurisdiction or royal power,
          nor should they or can they (saving justice) be concerned about taking possession or about
          ordering or disposing of dominion or government throughout that entire world against the
          will of those peoples.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>