<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 9</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 9</title>
          <date when="2025-11-13">November 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="23-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Hd1e97">Section 9</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e99">
          § 9
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore in this manner the jurisdictions and domains of our kings of the Spains 
          and of the natural kings of that world,
          even of individual things,
          are compatible.
          Because our kings have supreme dominion and similar imperial universal jurisdiction,
          but the other individual kings and natural lords in their kingdom or kingdoms and domains,
          and individuals in their own things,
          by relation to the universal hold inferior jurisdiction and immediate dominion,
          without this that so many domains are mutually incompatible.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e126">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          An example of this is ready at hand:
          that any king in his kingdom has dominion and jurisdiction in any thing,
          namely for regulating and protecting it.
          A duke or count obtains inferior dominion and jurisdiction.
          But the farmer,
          if he possesses civilly and naturally,
          has direct and useful dominion.
          But if only civilly and another naturally,
          that one has direct dominion.
          The emphyteuta or usufructuary or feudatory has only useful dominion.
          Hence there are multiple dominions concerning the same thing,
          nor however are they mutually incompatible since they are of diverse species,
          as appears from what has been said.
          And if you wish,
          run to those things which the jurists note,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e154">d. l. possideri § ex contrario.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e153">
          Therefore the Supreme Pontiff understood concerning such supreme and universal jurisdiction 
          and dominion in the aforesaid words when he said 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Qd1e159">
            with all the domains and jurisdictions of those islands
          </quote>,
          etc.
          Indeed he conceded this to our kings,
          <pb ed="#B" n="24-r"/>
          but he left and confirmed to the natural kings and lords and even singular persons 
          those things which pertained to them by the law of nations and natural law,
          although with jurisdiction somewhat diminished and restricted,
          insofar as they had to recognize our kings as superior and universal lords.
          And thus they do not remain as free as before,
          and this could be done in favor of the faith,
          not for any other cause,
          as has been proven above.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e181">
          Hence that clause must be restricted and moderated,
          namely 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Qd1e185">
            with all the domains and jurisdictions of those islands
          </quote>,
          etc.
          It must be understood,
          I say,
          and declared according to the end and limits of natural reason,
          and lest injustices be done or the rights of those peoples which pertain to them 
          by the law of nations and natural law,
          as has often been said,
          lest injustices be born from that place where laws are born,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e206">l. meminerint, C. unde vi</ref>,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e211">l. omnium, c. de testamentis</ref>,
          and we ought not to do that from which we are bound to prohibit another,
          and he who is bound to defend us ought not to fight against us,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e218">c. unico extra de natis ex libero uentre</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e222">ff. si ser ven. l. altius</ref>.
          From this it is that rescripts and whatever emanates from the Apostolic See 
          must always be interpreted so that no one is harmed from it,
          at least gravely or enormously,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e228">c. super eo de officio delegati</ref>,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e234">above § 7</ref>
          was extensively shown.
          It makes 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e236">capitulum ecce 99 dist</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e241">capitulum cum olim de consuetudine</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e243">c. emancipatione l. nec auus.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e220">
          And the reason according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e250">Baldus in d. c. cum olim</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Qd1e224">
            Because a concession from which something absurd follows is called a captious concession
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e257">ff. De transactionibus. l. cum aquiliana</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e262">ff. de heredibus instituendis l. illa institutio</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e264">l. ille autem</ref>.
          And therefore the pope does not concede letters with prejudice to another.
          Moreover,
          nothing ought to be done for emulation,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e270">ff. de operibus publicis l. opus</ref>,
          and the privilege of one ought not to usurp the right of another,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e275">ff. de uulgari sustitutione l. ex facto</ref>.
          Nor to impede natural faculty 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e279">ff. de operibus libertorum l. libertas negotiatori.</ref>
          These things Baldus.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e243">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise privileges and concessions are understood to be made without injury to another,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e292">l. 2. § si quis a principe</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e294">§ merito ff, ne quid in loco publico</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e299">l. si decem. C. de statu et imagi.</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e305">l. cum filius. ff. de mili tasta.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e257">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Again,
          the honors of some ought not to harm others 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e318">C. de statua et imaginibus l. finalis</ref>.
          For it is iniquitous to take something unjustly from one to be given to another 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e322">c. non est 1. q. 1.</ref>
          And Baldus says that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Qd1e268">
            the pope does not wish his own to be taken from anyone
          </quote>,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e330">l. 2. ff. qui sunt sui vel alie iuris</ref>.
          And therefore the words of the rescript receive limitation from common law,
          <pb ed="#B" n="24-v"/>
          and all clauses appended in rescripts are restricted to those litigating.
          And although in the letters appeal is removed,
          nevertheless all whose interest it is can appeal.
          Moreover,
          all whom the business touches could oppose themselves,
          although mention is not made of them,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e348">
            Bernard,
            argument in l. 1, ff. quibus rebus ad eundem iudicem
          </ref>.
          From these,
          although the pope did not except or express that it was not his intention 
          to derogate the rights of natural kings and singular persons or to generate prejudice 
          through such words,
          it is nevertheless understood as if he had declared it in express words,
          since those things which are inherent,
          even if they are not said,
          being expressed and said do not change or add 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e363">
            C. de fidei iussoribus et mandatoribus l. 3 in fine
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e365">ff. de condi. et demonstra l. conditiones extrinsecus</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e370">ff. de legatis 1 l. 3</ref>.
          See 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e373">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Nd1e301">Andreas de Isernia</name>
            de prohibita feudi alienatione § preterea inter duos fratres per fredericum 7th column at the beginning
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e308">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          It is still general that the form of the rescript is not always to be observed,
          according to Bernard,
          namely when the right of a third party would be harmed,
          who is not named in the rescript,
          which is to be held in mind.
          All these things 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e394">Baldus in d. c. super eo.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e320">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For this we have one law canonized by the great Gregory,
          which is contained 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e404">C. de precibus</ref>
          imperatori offerendis,
          registered among the sacred canons 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e408">25 q. 2 c. imperiali</ref>,
          where it is held that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Qd1e334">
            we command all judges to refuse rescripts elicited against law,
            unless perhaps it be something which does not harm another and benefits the petitioner,
            or pardons a crime for supplicants
          </quote>.
          These things there,
          where also there is a good gloss.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e345">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          From which it appears that it is not the intention of the prince,
          especially of the supreme prince of the universal church,
          the pope,
          through his rescripts or through his graces and donations,
          to prejudice or remove the right of another,
          and far less the honors,
          dignities,
          and royal states pertaining to the proper and true kings and lords,
          without a great and arduous,
          examined,
          legitimate,
          and necessary cause.
          And therefore provisions,
          concessions,
          graces,
          and other things of this kind must always be restricted,
          limited,
          and interpreted in such a way that the right of another is not enormously harmed or taken away,
          or great prejudice generated to them,
          as has been sufficiently evidently shown.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e393">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore for the promulgation of the gospel of Christ throughout that whole world 
          and the expansion of the Church 
          <pb ed="#B" n="25-r"/>
          and the conversion and salvation of those peoples,
          it suffices that our illustrious Catholic kings of the Spains be in that whole world of the Indies 
          supreme princes,
          having the height of supreme jurisdiction,
          power and dominion,
          and as it were imperial dignity and authority over all kings,
          princes and lords,
          and also over all the inhabitant nations of the aforesaid world,
          they themselves remaining with their domains,
          jurisdictions,
          honors,
          and royal states,
          unless insofar as it would be necessary for their jurisdiction to be restricted 
          for the benefit of the faith and common utility,
          and not further,
          because then the cause of restricting would cease.
          But if the contrary were said and it should perhaps happen,
          namely that through the aforesaid institution concerning our kings 
          and their supreme principate,
          universal jurisdiction and high dominion,
          the natural princes and lords were understood to have remained,
          by that very fact,
          completely despoiled of their domains,
          dignities,
          and jurisdictions,
          it is manifest that they would be burdened with most grave and enormous 
          and therefore intolerable prejudice and damage,
          and consequently that a maximum scandal would arise among all those peoples and nations,
          and infamy,
          horror,
          and detestation against the faith and Christian religion (as has been said) 
          would be generated in their minds.
          Therefore the said institution,
          concession or donation,
          and apostolic letters or papal decree emanating concerning these things,
          must necessarily be understood,
          interpreted,
          and declared so that the kings and princes of that whole world may have,
          use,
          possess,
          and freely enjoy their dignities,
          domains,
          and jurisdictions and royal states and pristine honors even after the said institution,
          according to what has been said,
          just as before,
          even if the pope makes no mention of this in his letters.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e481">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Otherwise many and great and horrible absurdities,
          inconveniences,
          and inhumanities would follow.
          And the first will be that what has been provided and constituted for the good 
          and utility of those peoples,
          as it were on account of the faith,
          would be turned to their ruin and destruction,
          contrary to that:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Qd1e498">
            What has been introduced in favor of some ought not to be turned to their hatred
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e585">l. quod fauore. C. de legibus</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e590">ff. eodem titulo.</ref>
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Qd1e505">
            No reason of law or equity allows that those things which are wholesomely introduced 
            for the utility of men,
            <pb ed="#B" n="25-v"/>
            we by harsher interpretation should bring them forth against their advantage to severity
          </quote>.
          These things there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e517">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For argument from the absurd to be avoided,
          or from the avoidance of absurdity and inconvenience,
          great scandal and injustice or inhumanity,
          since it is taken from natural discretion,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e640">
            Baldus in Consilium 29 of the 3rd volume in the penultimate column
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e621">l. pompinius 2nd and 3rd column ff. de negotiis gestis</ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Rd1e626">authent de nouo iure in fine C. de episcopis et clericis</ref>,
          where he says:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-Qd1e537">
            this manner of arguing from avoidance or the consequence of absurdity is very useful
          </quote>,
          etc.
          These things from him.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e540">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          It would be a great,
          indeed a maximum absurdity,
          that the Christian religion would be hateful and horrible to infidels 
          and would be defamed among them for injustice and iniquity,
          who are to be invited and drawn to the faith mildly,
          sweetly,
          and gently,
          and also by giving them our things rather than taking away their things from them.
          But they would withdraw from receiving it as if from an irrational,
          cruel,
          inhuman,
          deceptive dogma or law,
          contrary to natural reason,
          and therefore completely iniquitous.
          That this indeed would redound to ignominious blasphemy of the name of Christ,
          no one of sound mind will deny.
          Also a great injury would be committed by despoiling the innocent without fault 
          and without necessary and legitimate cause of their goods and dignities,
          which they justly possess by the authority of the law of nations and confirmed by divine law.
          And then the Roman Pontiff would not proceed as God,
          who is truth,
          but whatever would be done to the contrary would be null by law,
          which anyone sees is a great inconvenience,
          since it is not fitting that the vicar of Christ,
          and those things which he once decreed,
          should be void and unable to subsist by law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e592">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For Baldus says in the book of feuds,
          de pace constantie § in nomine christi,
          that for the exercise of this supreme jurisdiction in the pope concerning the state of temporals,
          the pope ought to proceed as God,
          who is truth,
          whence a cause is required.
          Therefore,
          the cause not existing,
          jurisdiction ceases,
          because when a cause is required as the foundation of jurisdiction,
          the cause must be present and be true and examined;
          otherwise the judgment is null by the law itself.
          And it is the doctrine of Innocent,
          extra de foro competenti c. cum sit generale and c. 1. de foro competenti libro 6 in the novels,
          and de rescriptis c. super literis and by Innocent de officio delegati c. cum super abbatia.
          These things Baldus in form.
          But this would be most absurd in the most holy vicar of Christ;
          therefore it must be avoided entirely.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e628">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Moreover,
          another absurdity not to be dissimulated would follow,
          namely because a cause of most just war would be offered to infidels against us,
          as against public enemies,
          and of all evils and calamities which follow from wars,
          and we would be bound to complete restitution,
          besides the most grave sins which we would commit.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e176-d1e641">
          Therefore,
          to avoid so many absurdities and inconveniences unjust and contrary to natural reason 
          and divine law,
          it must be confessed entirely that the supreme vicar of Christ,
          in the aforesaid apostolic letters and decree of the aforesaid institution,
          concession or donation to our Catholic kings,
          through the same institution or concession,
          by no means intended to deprive the kings and natural lords of that world of their royal dignities,
          domains,
          and jurisdictions,
          and the other individual inhabitants of the dominion of their things.
          And concerning this,
          what has been said suffices.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>