<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 3</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 3</title>
          <date when="2024-11-19">November 19, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
                 url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-11-19" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Hd1e107">Section 3</head>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e109">
          ยง. 3
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e116">
          Proposition 2: 
          Not only does this good of honor and good opinion 
          among posterity accrue to the dead,
          which is in a certain way to live perpetually and always, 
          as has been said,
          but it also greatly matters to the living 
          who were joined to the deceased 
          either by blood or affinity or even friendship.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e132">
          The proposition is proved: 
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          Just as the nobility of parents 
          which they acquired through virtues,
          riches, 
          knowledge, 
          industry, 
          eloquence, 
          military affairs, 
          administration of the republic,
          or greater dignity or any other uncommon excellence 
          descends as if by propagation to posterity,
          so that they follow the condition of their ancestors. 
          As is excellently proved in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e149">
            l. 1 where 
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Nd1e151">Bartholus</name>
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e155">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Nd1e156">Johannes de Platea</name>
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e158">l. si senator</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e161">
            l. mulieres, 
            Codex on dignities, 
            book 12
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e166" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e148-Dd1e158">
            l. senatoris filium, 
            Digest on the senate
          </ref> 
          and from that nobility and virtues 
          by which predecessors attained it,
          posterity and descendants 
          glory and often boast themselves vigorously. 
          So if their ancestors were marked 
          by some disgrace or infamy of morals especially,
          or some injury is inflicted upon them,
          without doubt all descendants are struck 
          by the confusion of the same reproach,
          and the honor of all of them is detracted from. 
          For if some honor is shown to parents already dead,
          such as when their memory is praised and celebrated,
          it is manifest that such honor redounds 
          to sons and grandsons and great-grandsons and to all descendants. 
          On the contrary, however,
          if some dishonors were done to them,
          for example if they were exhumed or their bones were burned,
          great injury would be inflicted 
          on the living and sons and other descendants and relatives. 
          Similarly indeed there redound to deceased parents 
          the good or evil which come 
          to sons, grandsons, great-grandsons and other posterity of theirs,
          namely both prosperities and dishonors,
          infamies or misfortunes,
          that is good and bad operations from which honors or dishonors proceed. 
          For he is more illustrious who leaves excellent successors 
          than he who leaves none or bad ones,
          thus 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e216">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Nd1e217">the Philosopher</name>
          </ref> 
          argues and concludes in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e221">Ethics 1</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e224">
          All these things are clear from that passage of 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e226">
            Ecclesiasticus chapter 3
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Qd1e231">
            Do not glory in the dishonor of your father,
            for it is not glory to you but confusion,
            for the glory of man is from the honor of his father,
            and a father without honor is the disgrace of the son
          </quote>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e238">chapter 41</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Qd1e240">
            Be ashamed before father and mother of fornication
          </quote>.
          And a little below: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Qd1e245">
            Of an impious father the sons complain because through him they are in reproach
          </quote>.
          Whence injury is inflicted on sons from the fornicating birth of their mother,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e253">
            Authenticum on restitutions and that which gives birth,
            final paragraph of the collation
          </ref>. 
          Likewise it is disgraceful to a father if a son takes a dishonorable wife, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e260">
            Digest on contracting purchase,
            law 3
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e264">
          It is relevant to the proposition 
          what <ref>Valerius relates in book 3 chapter 5</ref> 
          or according to <ref>another volume chapter 305</ref> concerning Aeneas Scipio,
          son of Scipio Africanus the Elder,
          who was like a monster considering the glory and virtues of his father,
          from which he himself had greatly degenerated,
          and on account of the stains of his shameful vices 
          among other ignominies inflicted upon him,
          when the honor of the praetorship had been conferred upon him 
          by the Roman people or by a certain scribe of his father 
          to whom the Roman people had granted it,
          his relatives and kinsmen,
          considering that he was going to pollute that dignity 
          on account of his vices and shamefulness 
          and that the reproach and disgrace of him 
          would redound to all of them,
          so terrified him that he did not dare 
          to place the praetorian seat 
          or to pronounce judgment among litigants. 
          And moreover they took from his hand the ring 
          in which the head of Africanus the Elder was sculpted. 
          And Valerius adds: 
          <!-- TODO: quote; trans triage -->
          Good gods,
          what darkness from what lightning did you suffer to be born,
          that is,
          what obscurations of the brightness of name 
          and fame did you suffer to be born.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e302">
          It is clear therefore that 
          all relatives and those who are of the same genealogy or kinship 
          are damaged by the reproach or ignominy of any one of them. 
          From this it is that one who offends someone or some people in person 
          or in goods is said to offend 
          not only them but also whoever is 
          from the kinship of the offended. 
          This is proved by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rf1a333">
            the chapter "olim" on injuries and damage done
          </ref>,
          where an injury inflicted on a bishop 
          seems to be inflicted on all subject churches 
          because he is the spouse of those churches. 
          Whence inferior churches can act for an injury inflicted upon them,
          as there. 
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          And on account of this,
          power of vengeance is sometimes given to the same kinsmen,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rx32aaa">
            l. raptores,
            Codex on sacrosanct churches
          </ref>,
          where it is said that the power of killing 
          by their own authority is given to the kinsmen of virgins 
          and women dedicated to God who have been raped. 
          And from these things 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e337">
            the gloss on l. lex cornelia,
            Digest on injuries
          </ref>: 
          because an injury inflicted on one of the kinship seems done to the whole kinship. 
          This is also clear in <ref>Genesis 14</ref> 
          from the deed of Abraham who avenged the plunder 
          committed against Lot his nephew 
          when he went against four kings,
          and Simeon and Levi against the rapists of Dinah 
          their sister having been killed.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e350">
          The reason for the aforesaid things 
          is that the whole kinship makes one body,
          of which the individual parts or members 
          make individuals of that kinship, 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rvn1fh2">
            l. cum scimus,
            Codex on farmers and those registered,
            book 11
          </ref>. 
          For we are one with our parents, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rf1aazz">
            on penance,
            distinction 4,
            chapter "What is said"
          </ref>. 
          For father and son are reckoned as one head and as one person,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rja1ccc" corresp="#cy8th8-d1e97-Qd1e368">
            l. fine,
            Digest on minors and substitutions
          </ref>,
          where it is said: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Qd1e368">
            Since from nature father and son are understood to be almost the same person,
            they are one flesh
          </quote>, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e400">
            question 35.3,
            paragraph "by this authority"
          </ref>. 
          Likewise a son is part of his father,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e377">
            the Philosopher says in Ethics 5
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Qd1e379">
            for he is his blood
          </quote>, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e411" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e673-d1e139">
            Digest on undutiful testament,
            law "non enim"
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e417">
            the voice of the father is as the voice of the son,
            Institutes on useless stipulations,
            paragraph "ei qui"
          </ref>,
          and the heir is considered one person with the deceased 
          in the 
          <ref>Authenticum on oath sworn by one dying at the beginning</ref>,
          namely for that part by which he is heir,
          note 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e429">
            Digest on praetorian stipulations,
            law 2,
            in the last gloss
          </ref>. 
          Indeed the nature of the father 
          walks in the person of the son,
          and the memory of parents is conserved in children and through children in the same way, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e437">
            Digest on the signification of words,
            law "mulier,"
            paragraph "cum proportionaretur"
          </ref>. 
          And by the appellation of parent 
          not only father but also grandfather and great-grandfather 
          and thenceforth all superiors to infinity are contained,
          but also mother and grandmother and great-grandmother, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e446">
            Digest on the signification of words,
            law "appellatione"
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e451" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e343-d1e144">
            Digest on summoning to court,
            law 4,
            paragraph "praetor"
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e457" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e343-d1e150">
            paragraph "parentes"
          </ref>. 
          Similarly by the appellation of children,
          grandsons and great-grandsons a
          nd all who descend from the same stock 
          and are born are comprehended and make a kinship,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e468" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e5147-d1e2573">
            law "liberorum,"
            Digest on the signification of words
          </ref>. 
          They also make a family,
          house and people,
          that is consanguinity,
          as is proved in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e475">
            law "pronuntiato,"
            paragraph "familie,"
            element 2
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e481">
            paragraph "communi iure,"
            Digest in that title
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e426">
          Since therefore the whole one kinship,
          family, 
          house and people,
          that is consanguinity,
          makes one mystical or imagined body, 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Qd1e435">
            and individually they are members of one another
          </quote>,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e500">
            the Apostle says to the Romans 12
          </ref>,
          and by natural inclination 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Qd1e440">
            the members are solicitous 
            for each other in the same thing,
            and if one member suffers,
            all members suffer together;
            but if one member is glorified,
            all members rejoice together
          </quote>,
          as also 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e512">
            the Apostle says in 1 Corinthians 12
          </ref>. 
          Therefore if a father or superior 
          or any of the ascendants of any family,
          house or people or kinship and consanguinity,
          or a son or grandson or great-grandson 
          or any of the descendants 
          or even collateral relatives acts 
          or suffers some injury 
          or reproach or disgrace 
          or something shameful,
          injurious or dishonorable,
          similarly on account of the illustrious deeds of any of them 
          or glory and honor attained on account of merits,
          it redounds to the whole family or kinship etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e467">
          Therefore not only does any good of honor or happy opinion 
          among posterity accrue to the dead 
          (which is in a certain way to live perpetually),
          but it also matters to the living 
          who were joined to the deceased either 
          by blood, family, kinship, affinity or even friendship, 
          because from such honor or honoring,
          glory or disgrace of the dead 
          they themselves receive advantage or disadvantage. 
          And thus the second proposition is clear.
        </p>
        <!-- end second proposition -->
        <!-- begin third proposition -->
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e483">
          The third proposition 
          which follows from the preceding ones: 
          To store great treasures or riches with the bodies of the deceased 
          is a manifest argument that 
          neither the dead who ordered them to be buried with themselves 
          nor the living successors who permit them to remain in the tombs of their ancestors 
          placed them there with that intention 
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          or allow them to be there so that they would have them 
          or have them as abandoned things,
          or renounced tacitly or expressly 
          the right and ownership which they had in them. 
          And consequently that the aforesaid treasures and riches 
          have an owner and are another's property.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e511">
          The proposition is proved 
          first from the first proposition,
          because the intention and mind of the dead and living 
          who ordered them to be buried with themselves 
          and who permit them to remain in the tombs 
          is so that from this they may obtain 
          honor, glory, and praise among posterity 
          and so that their glorious status, wealth, and magnificence 
          may become known to future ages,
          and so they may live perpetually in the opinions of men. 
          And this is a great interest to them. 
          Therefore neither the living nor the dead had the intention 
          to leave the riches and treasures aforesaid as abandoned things.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e537">
          Secondly, it is proved by a sign thus: 
          When things which are found and whose owner is not known 
          are precious and of great value,
          it is a sign that 
          they are not held or were held as abandoned things 
          wherever they are found. 
          Whence they ought not be thought 
          to lack an owner or owners, dead or living,
          since no one throws away such things from themselves,
          but either possesses and preserves them or gives them away. 
          But the treasures and riches and those things 
          which were stored in the aforesaid tombs with kings and nobles 
          were most precious things. 
          Therefore it is a sign 
          that they were not held as abandoned things. 
          For it is not likely 
          that such precious things would be so disdained.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e561">
          Thirdly, it is proved from the places in which they are found. 
          For they are found in tombs or in temples of their gods,
          and they guarded the doors with locks and bars lest they be taken by thieves,
          as was said in the beginning. 
          Therefore it is a sign 
          that they did not hold them as abandoned things.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e575">
          Fourthly, 
          it is proved from a similar case: 
          for if someone finds in the sea or on the seashore 
          something which was cast out from a ship for the sake of lightening the ship,
          on account of the place in which it is found 
          no one ought to presume or think 
          that it is held as abandoned,
          but rather not the contrary. 
          Since those things which are cast into the sea 
          for the sake of lightening the ship 
          are not held as abandoned things,
          because they are not cast with that mind 
          that they not be possessed further 
          or that the owners lose 
          or throw away their ownership of them,
          but because the possessing owner wishes to save his life 
          which is more precious to him than riches. 
          Whence it is clear that to find things in the sea or on the seashore 
          is a sign that the owner of them did not hold them as abandoned things; 
          things, I say, 
          which are not accustomed to be on the seashore 
          except very rarely and by chance on account of them;
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          I say namely little stones or gems which are born there 
          which are in no one's goods and therefore become the finder's. 
          These things are proved in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e670">
            the Institutes on the division of things,
            final paragraph
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e675">
            Digest on thefts,
            law "falsus,"
            paragraph "si iactum"
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e682">
            Digest on threatened damage,
            law "si finita,"
            paragraph "si quis metu"
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e619">
          In this way 
          it must be said that 
          if someone was carrying great burdens on the road 
          and could not carry further and left them,
          or if fleeing enemies 
          he could not carry his things 
          and therefore leaves them on the road,
          although he thinks that he will not find them 
          when he returns or that perhaps he will never have them,
          he will not be said to hold them as abandoned things.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e640">
          These therefore are manifest signs 
          which make a vehement presumption by reason of place 
          that things which are found are not held as abandoned things 
          nor do they lack an owner,
          and thus they are another's property.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e653">
          Thus therefore 
          it is concerning treasures and other precious things 
          which are found in tombs or in temples of their gods,
          because certainly they were not placed there 
          so that they would be held as abandoned things,
          but so that they would be best preserved there perpetually 
          and from this would bring honor, praise, and good opinion 
          to the owners now deceased and their living descendants. 
          On this see 
          <ref>
            Hostiensis in his Summa,
            title on the cause of property,
            paragraph "what property is,"
            at the word "Likewise through tradition."
          </ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e674">
          And the aforesaid things are confirmed by an example 
          which we both understand and see manifestly among us. 
          Let us ask, I say,
          whether kings and magnates and noble and Catholic men 
          have held as abandoned those precious things,
          namely those standards 
          or insignia or shields of gold and silver,
          tombs covered with cloths of silk and woven with gold 
          which the deceased fathers and their ancestors 
          placed in the chapels of churches where they were buried. 
          And whether the dead and the surviving living descendants of them would be offended 
          if someone should try to take those things either by theft or violently. 
          For it is manifest that 
          not only the dead and the living,
          but also the whole kinship, house, and family 
          would be offended and would take it as injuries.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e704">
          Fifthly, the proposition is proved 
          because those precious things 
          which were stored with the bodies of the deceased in tombs 
          are not properly treasures,
          which are in the goods of no one 
          which are acquired entirely by the finder 
          if he finds them in his own ground. 
          For that is properly a treasure 
          to which the definition of treasure applies,
          which is placed in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e789">
            law "unica,"
            Codex on treasures,
            book 10
          </ref>:
          <!-- TODO: possible quotation here -->
          a treasure is money hidden 
          from unknown owners in more ancient time,
          of which disposition no memory exists,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e795">there</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e797">
            Institutes on the division of things,
            paragraph "thesauros"
          </ref>. 
          From unknown owners,
          that is, 
          money was hidden by some men 
          who never recovered it, 
          and it remained there for the longest time,
          so much so that now through forgetfulness 
          it has gone out from the possession and ownership of humans 
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e811">
            Johannes de Platea on said law "unica"
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e736">
          But improperly a treasure is said, 
          according to the same author, 
          when memory exists,
          as when someone hid it for the sake of profit or fear or custody,
          add also of honor or some other good consideration. 
          And nothing is owed to the finder from this,
          rather he commits theft,
          but it belongs to him who hid it or to his heirs,
          as is the text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e835">
            law "nunquam,"
            paragraph "thesaurus,"
            Digest on acquiring ownership of things at the end
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e839">
            law "thesaurus,"
            Digest on exhibition
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e842">
            law "item habeo,"
            Digest on dividing the estate
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-Rd1e848">
            law "a tutore,"
            Digest on rescinding a sale
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e97-d1e764">
          Since therefore 
          those precious things were placed in tombs 
          for the sake of custody and honor, praise, and glory 
          of the living and deceased 
          and of the whole kinship of kings 
          and other great men,
          ascendants and descendants,
          of whom memory exists through succession,
          namely of king Inca or successors of the kings of those kingdoms,
          and so in other kingdoms of that world,
          therefore they are not treasures properly but improperly,
          and consequently they are not owed to finders. 
          The conclusion is clear 
          because they have not gone out 
          from the possession and ownership of those people,
          and thus they have owners. 
          And thus concerning the third proposition.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>