<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 12</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 12</title>
          <date when="2025-11-13">November 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="32-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Hd1e97">Section 12</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#B" n="32-v"/>
          § 12
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e106">
          Part 4
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e111">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          An ordered descent into or harmless entry upon any land,
          and that it not be done without the license of the inhabitants.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e124">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The reason for this is that if without express or tacit license they should strive to enter 
          or descend,
          or especially if they were prohibited by the inhabitants by words or signs or deeds 
          from descending from ships,
          then indeed the entry would be harmful and injurious.
          Hence the inhabitants would deservedly be disturbed,
          and thus the natural order of justice would be violated on the part of the messengers 
          or legates of our kings,
          and therefore they would inflict violence on the inhabitants,
          and by natural law it will be licit for them to run to arms,
          and not only to impede the descent and entry of those men,
          but truly also to repel justly,
          as hostile attacks unjustly made against themselves,
          and to avenge severely.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e151">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For any people,
          city,
          municipality,
          or kingdom recognizing no superior,
          or the supreme governor of it,
          through a statute or royal law,
          if he sees it expedient for peace,
          for tranquility,
          for avoiding the corruption of evil morals,
          for defense,
          security,
          and preservation of the state of the kingdom or republic,
          can prohibit that no person of foreigners or aliens or of any other kingdom 
          enter the kingdom or province or city of his jurisdiction for any cause,
          whether of trade or exchange,
          buying or selling,
          or for the sake of dwelling there.
          And he would indeed do this reasonably and prudently,
          and by the authority of the law of nations and natural law punish those attempting the contrary.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e187">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          This is proven in many ways by reason,
          authority,
          and examples.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e195">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The first reason is that he does no injury to anyone by providing within the limits 
          of his own territory and jurisdiction what he judges to be necessary or even useful 
          for the peace,
          quiet,
          liberty,
          and security of the state and kingdom or city and people subject to him.
          And it would be foolish enough for another people or city or king of another nation to complain 
          <pb ed="#B" n="33-r"/>
          about such a law or statute,
          or to demand or wish to be rendered a reason for those things which another republic or city 
          or free king recognizing no superior orders or commands in his kingdom,
          as is clear of itself.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e222">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Let the second reason be this:
          it pertains to the office and care of a good and prudent king or of any universal 
          or supreme moderator of a kingdom or republic recognizing no superior,
          that through his industry provision be made so that future dangers and inconveniences 
          which can happen to the whole kingdom and republic may be obviated.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e239">
          But through the advent and entry of foreigners and aliens into the kingdom or fatherland 
          committed to his care,
          for whatever cause they may present,
          many dangers and inconveniences can happen to the kingdom and king and the whole republic.
          Therefore a good and prudent king recognizing no superior,
          if he sees it expedient for peace,
          for quiet,
          for avoiding the corruption of evil morals,
          for defense,
          security,
          and preservation of the liberty of the kingdom and his republic,
          can establish by statute or prohibit by royal law that no one of foreigners and aliens 
          or of any other kingdom or foreign nation enter the kingdom or fatherland or province or city 
          of his jurisdiction,
          whether for the sake of trade,
          etc.,
          or for any other cause.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e270">
          The consequence is clear of itself.
          The major is proven because it pertains to the prudence and circumspection of any prudent person,
          especially one who has the care of many,
          to fear and guard against those things in which the outcome is not determined,
          if they can be turned to an evil exit.
          And the reason for this is that not only is what is present attended to,
          but what can be or can follow,
          because outcomes are in the consideration of men,
          as the jurists also teach in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e288" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e4700-d1e427">
            l. aut facta § euentus ff. de poenis
          </ref>.
          And it is better to occur before the time than to avenge after the exit,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e295">l. 1 c. quando liceat uni se uindicare</ref>.
          And it is a matter of being prevented,
          as is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e300">l. 3. § cum igitur ff. de vi. et vi. armata</ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e297">l. vt vim ff. de iustitia et iure.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e297">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But the minor is proven,
          since if it were licit for all foreigners and aliens indifferently to enter for any cause,
          such as commerce,
          trade,
          etc.,
          the kingdom or fatherland of any other kings or peoples,
          it could happen that foreigners come with evil mind to an alien kingdom 
          with fictitious causes shown,
          namely to explore the weaker parts of the land 
          <pb ed="#B" n="33-v"/>
          to betray it into the hands of enemies.
          For from diverse places mutually considered,
          or from one powerful kingdom,
          with the weakness of the land known and considered or heard,
          very many peoples could be gathered into one,
          and then great armies assemble against that kingdom,
          and thus disturb,
          plunder,
          seize it,
          or subject it to their servitude.
          And without doubt this pertains to anyone,
          unless he be deprived of mind,
          especially to a king to whom the care of the whole community is committed,
          and therefore he ought to be more circumspect than all,
          to premeditate,
          suspect,
          fear,
          and guard against,
          since he sees foreign men in his kingdom,
          unless it is already long known about their intention and end or simplicity.
          Hence,
          because the defense of one's own fatherland and the liberty of the same is known to be 
          by natural law,
          it is clear that any people or populace,
          or him who acts in its place as king,
          can and ought by natural law itself to do,
          if he sees it expedient,
          namely to forbid foreigners of a foreign nation,
          whoever they may be,
          entry into his own fatherland or kingdom,
          at least until he knows that no danger to the fatherland threatens from the entry of such persons.
          Since any free people,
          city,
          or community ought reasonably to fear for itself lest others of a foreign nation,
          stronger than itself,
          strive to subject it to themselves,
          whence it would lose its liberty.
          For it is by the law of nature that any human society (as we have most extensively adduced elsewhere),
          and consequently all things necessary for the preservation of the said community or society,
          is by natural law,
          no one is ignorant.
          And for this 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e373">Durandus said in his treatise on laws</ref>
          that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Qd1e378">
            all that can be done by the community itself (supply: or him who acts in its place) 
            which is for the salvation of the polity and its pacific preservation
          </quote>.
          These things from him.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e389">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The same is also proven by authorities,
          and first through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e408">l. mercatores C. de comerciis et mercatoribus</ref>,
          where the law prohibits that those subject to the Roman empire converse for the sake of trade 
          with peoples,
          and not without reason,
          lest the Romans be believed to be explorers of the secrets of an alien kingdom,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e420">Baldus in the summary of the law</ref>.
          Hence thus says the text:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Qd1e406">
            It is not fitting that merchants subject both to our empire and to the king of the Persians 
            exercise markets beyond those places in which at the time of the treaty it was agreed with us 
            with the mentioned nation,
            <pb ed="#B" n="34-r"/>
            lest they scrutinize the secrets of an alien kingdom (which is not fitting)
          </quote>.
          These things there in form.
          Therefore it is evil or can be and is suspicious to any republic for peoples of a foreign nation 
          to enter an alien fatherland.
          Therefore a king or universal governor or the community itself can reasonably and prudently prohibit 
          entry into it.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e427">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second,
          it is proven through those things which Bartolus notes in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e451">
            l. relegatorum § inter dicere ff. de interdictis et relegatis
          </ref>,
          namely that it can be established that any of the subjects not go to do business outside the territory 
          or to such a city,
          through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e458">d. l. mercatores.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e441">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Third,
          it is proven through 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Nd1e446">Andreas de Isernia</name>,
          on prohibita feudi alienatione per fredericum near the end,
          where he says that a king can prohibit entry or passage,
          as for instance to a multitude and lascivious army,
          because lascivious,
          argument 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e463">ff. locati et conducti near the end</ref>,
          to have a just cause for prohibiting so that an army not pass through his kingdom,
          fearing invasion of his lands or other invasions and dangers,
          through those things which 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e488">Durandus numbers 20 and 21 chapter</ref>.
          Likewise that he can prohibit also to one person from a cause,
          namely so that the secrets of his kingdom not be known,
          argument 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e475">C. de comerciis et mercatoribus l. 3</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e477">6. q. 2. merito</ref>,
          or from another similar cause having a similar reason.
          For where there is the same reason,
          there is the same law,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e481">ff. de fundi l. 1</ref>,
          as if he should not wish aliens and foreigners to live or remain in his kingdom,
          lest they infect the minds of his subjects.
          And it is a just fear and such a cause is true,
          because one can also prohibit that someone odious to him not buy his thing,
          argument 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e493">C. de iure emphiteutico fi. in principio</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e5z9">ff. de actionibus emp. l. si sterilis § si tibi</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e521">de contrahenda emptiane. l. qui fundum.</ref>
          These things 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Nd1e526">Andreas de Isernia</name>
          in form.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e481">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Fourth,
          it is proven through Baldus,
          whom many refer to and follow,
          who on 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e538">feuds, title de forma fidelitatis § dominus vero</ref>,
          asks whether lords of lands can expel foreign merchants from their territories without cause,
          and if they do not depart,
          take away their goods.
          He responded that not unless from a cause.
          But to those coming to an alien fatherland,
          entry can well be forbidden,
          argument 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e519">ff. de usufructu per legatum l. heres</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e524">ff. si seruitus uindicetur l. sicut § Aristo</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e557">Instit. de rerum diuisione § illud in the word apes</ref>
          and l. quod enim de acquirenda rerum dominia,
          in which laws it is prohibited to enter into the fields or lands of others 
          <pb ed="#B" n="34-v"/>
          or to do anything in them without the license of the lords,
          and still less against their will.
          For which the said laws are given by the doctors in argument of this kind,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e576">the gloss in l. quod enim</ref>
          notes that I can prohibit to such an extent my land and resist with armed hand,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e583">ff. ad l. aquiliam</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e585">l. quemadmadum near the beginning</ref>,
          and I can bring an action for injuries,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e548">ff. de iniuriis l. iniuriarum § si quis me prohibeat</ref>,
          where it is held that if someone strives to enter an alien land with the lord unwilling,
          he inflicts disturbing violence,
          since he does not permit him to use his thing freely,
          whence he does injury to him.
          Therefore they do far graver injury who strive to enter an alien kingdom or fatherland 
          with the king unwilling,
          to the whole community.
          The same which Baldus says,
          James of Saint Gregory says in his treatise on feuds.
          Also by examples of divine scripture the aforesaid things are strengthened.
          For 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e614">Genesis 42</ref>
          we read that Joseph imposed on his brothers to terrify them,
          as if they had committed an injurious crime,
          worthy of death,
          against the kingdom of the Egyptians:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Qd1e548">
            You,
            he says,
            are spies,
            to see the weaker parts of the land you have come
          </quote>.
          And he adds:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Qd1e555">
            By the health of Pharaoh you will not go out from here
          </quote>,
          etc.
          And they themselves:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Qd1e559">
            It is not so,
            lord,
            but your servants have come to buy food;
            we are all sons of one man;
            we have come peacefully,
            nor do your servants plot any evil
          </quote>,
          etc.
          These things there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e567">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Behold that evil can reasonably be suspected concerning the advent of foreigners 
          to an alien fatherland,
          until certainty and security about them and the cause of their advent is had.
          For although Joseph was certain that the brothers had not come to plot some evil,
          nevertheless he did not absurdly or irrationally rebuke them under the title that they were spies,
          since he wished thus to terrify and afflict them,
          knowing that any wise person,
          and especially a provident universal and supreme governor of any kingdom or fatherland,
          could not absurdly but most deservedly object the same things to them or suspect the same about them.
          And the Hebrews say that Joseph introduced against his brothers in argument 
          that with the weakness of the land known,
          adverse peoples could gather a great army against the kingdom of Egypt.
          Therefore a provident king and supreme moderator of any kingdom 
          <pb ed="#B" n="35-r"/>
          therefore has reason to fear for his kingdom and fatherland from foreigners and strangers,
          and consequently can and ought deservedly to forbid entry to anyone into his kingdom or fatherland,
          as often as he sees it expedient for peace,
          for quiet,
          for security,
          for defense,
          and for preserving liberty.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-d1e617">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The same appears from the reason which the princes and counselors of the king of the Ammonites 
          put forward,
          1 Chronicles 19,
          who,
          fearing lest the messengers of David,
          whom he had sent to console Ammon over the death of his father,
          were explorers of the land,
          said to the king:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Qd1e627">
            Do you perhaps think that David sent those who might console you for the sake of honor 
            to your father?
            And do you not notice that his servants have come to you that they may explore 
            and investigate and scrutinize your land?
          </quote>,
          etc.
          For although Ammon and his servants or counselors acted inhumanely and sinned gravely 
          by afflicting the messengers of David with a most grave contumely,
          in this that they trampled and shaved them,
          cutting their tunics up to the buttocks,
          and consequently inflicted great injury on David himself,
          nevertheless truly they were prudently and reasonably moved to suspect and fear 
          lest perhaps they were explorers of an alien kingdom.
          Nor were they bound to believe the pacific and officious words of David's messengers,
          since they could be doleful and fictitious or deceptive lies.
          And through this just fear the king Ammon and his men could justly command David's messengers 
          to go out of his kingdom by a direct way,
          so that they not enter into any cities lest they see the weaker parts of the land,
          with whatever threats added.
          But if they did the contrary,
          they would not punish them unjustly.
          Nevertheless King Ammon or his men could not punish by suspicion alone;
          therefore they did badly and contrary to reason.
          Hence David justly moved war against them on account of the injury inflicted on him and his own.
          Therefore any people or city or king who has care of the republic,
          recognizing no superior,
          can prohibit by statute or by royal law,
          if he sees it expedient for peace,
          for security,
          etc.,
          that no one of foreigners enter his own kingdom or fatherland for any cause,
          etc.,
          and punish those doing the contrary by the authority 
          <pb ed="#B" n="35-v"/>
          of the law of nations and natural law.
          Therefore the Indian nations can do this well and justly.
          Therefore the descent or entry of the messengers of our kings into any part of that world 
          ought to be ordered and thus harmless,
          and by the voluntary license of the princes and lords or magistrates of the land.
          If it has been done otherwise,
          by best law,
          as against public enemies,
          they can go out with armed hand,
          and not only resist and prohibit the approach and entry,
          but truly also exercise vengeance for the injury and invasion or violation of empire 
          and the right of another.
          For among all the peoples of the whole world,
          that natural defense is permitted,
          indeed conceded,
          to all men,
          by which we repel force and injury inflicted not only on us but also on our fatherland,
          neighbors,
          and allies.
          And also whatever free communities or republics,
          since they have complete jurisdiction,
          mere and mixed empire,
          just as these are,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e736">§ 5 it was seen</ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e216-Rd1e741">below it will be seen</ref>,
          they avenge.
          We have proven these things most extensively in our book 1 On the Only Way of Calling 
          All Peoples to the True Religion,
          in the 4th incidental corollary,
          and in the treatise On the War of Xalisco.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>