<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 23</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 23</title>
          <date when="2025-11-16">November 16, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-16" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="60-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Hd1e97">Section 23</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#B" n="60-r"/>
          § 23
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e106">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But as regards the second state of those peoples,
          namely after they have already put on Christ through the washing of the sacred bath,
          whether they can be compelled to give such consent:
          The following conclusion is posited.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e119">
          Conclusion
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e124">
          To punish or molest those peoples after their conversion by temporal or ecclesiastical penalties:
          on account of their having denied the said consent:
          or having been unwilling to accept the papal institution concerning our kings,
          is lawful to no one.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e136">
          The conclusion is proved by a single reason:
          because no one deserves to suffer temporal or ecclesiastical penalty:
          who does or omits what he does or omits with just and reasonable cause,
          and thus by the authority of law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e147">
          But those peoples or nations after their conversion,
          by denying the aforesaid consent and not accepting the papal institution concerning our kings,
          do this and omit this with just and reasonable cause,
          and thus by the authority of law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e156">
          Therefore they do not deserve penalty,
          neither temporal nor ecclesiastical.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e161">
          Therefore it is lawful to no one to punish such people with temporal or ecclesiastical penalty.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e166">
          The first consequence is evident with the Major.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e171">
          The Minor is proved in many ways,
          first thus.
          He has just and reasonable cause,
          and thus by the authority of law,
          not to consent or accept,
          or at least to defer the ordinance or even the command of a prince,
          even the Pope,
          to whom it is not fully proved by any kind or species of juridical proof 
          that such an ordinance or command emanated from the prince or Pope,
          especially when the command or ordinance contains in itself something contrary to law 
          or public utility,
          or deviates at first sight from all honesty:
          and in matters of great weight.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e192">
          But it cannot be fully proved to such peoples and nations after they have received the faith,
          by any kind or species of juridical proof:
          that that institution of our kings over that world emanated from the Pope,
          or that it was made by the Pope,
          or even that the Pope could make it.
          <pb ed="#B" n="60-v"/>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e205">
          Therefore those peoples and nations have just and reasonable cause,
          and thus by the authority of law,
          not to accept it or at least to defer it and not to give consent:
          especially since it is contrary to natural law and the law of nations:
          and concerns matters of great weight and great prejudice.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e218">
          The consequence is clear,
          the rest being proved.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e220">
          The Major is proved expressly by the notable text in c. si quando de rescriptis,
          where it is evident that when the letters of a prince contain something contrary to law 
          or deviate from honesty:
          or otherwise there is doubt concerning the mind of the prince,
          or from their execution some scandal is feared,
          or it is vehemently presumed that some evils are coming:
          the mandatary ought not to obey but should await a second command.
          Because he does this by the authority of law,
          as there and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e239">authent. ut nulli iudicum § ex hoc vero</ref>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e244">authent. de mandatis principum § deinde competens</ref>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e249">
            aut. ut determinatus sit numerus clericorum § ex hoc quidem
          </ref>.
          And it is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e254">l. fine C. si contra ius uel publicam utilitatem</ref> 
          Whence in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e259">the said § deinde competens</ref>.
          It is ordered that administrators and judges of provinces should not receive a precept 
          contrary to law or public utility:
          unless a second command should emanate.
          Because it is not to be believed that such letters or such an ordinance or command 
          proceeded from the court of the prince,
          but rather are to be presumed false.
          As is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e260" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t3-Dd1e244">
            c ad hec sumus
          </ref>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e264" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t3-Dd1e169">
            d. c. si quando de rescriptis
          </ref>.
          And to this purpose applies 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e282">
            the statement of Bartholus in authent. ut determinatus sit numerus clericorum in d. § et eos quidem
          </ref> 
          Where it is said that it is lawful not to obey imperial or papal letters,
          according to the gloss there,
          when it is not evident that they are imperial or papal.
          And Bartholus adds 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Qd1e276">
            but certainly,
            he says,
            I say that if it is evident that they are imperial or papal letters:
            it is lawful not to obey them if reasonable cause is rendered.
            The text is in 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e280" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t3-Dd1e169">
              c. si quando de rescriptis
            </ref> 
            and 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e285" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t5-Dd1e184">
              de prebendis c. cum teneamur
            </ref>
          </quote>.
          These words of Bartholus.
          Also to be noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e290">c. ex parte in glossa fine de rescriptis</ref> 
          especially by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e293">Felinus</ref> 
          and others and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e296">the same Bartholus</ref> 
          that judges should not receive or execute precepts of superiors which emanate 
          <pb ed="#B" n="61-r"/>
          contrary to law and public utility:
          except after a second command.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e305">
          If therefore the commissary and mandatary ought not to fulfill such letters or command,
          far more strongly it lies upon those burdened by them not to receive,
          obey or fulfill them.
          To this purpose applies 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e336">l. regni castelle per Ioannem 2m</ref> 
          where he establishes that any city,
          castle or place donated or alienated by the king from the royal crown may resist by arms 
          with impunity.
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e343">
            Gloss in l. puniri C. si contra ius vel vtilitatem publicam
          </ref> 
          applies.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e323">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The Minor,
          namely that it cannot be fully proved to those nations after they have received the faith 
          by any species of proof that that institution concerning our kings was made by the Pope,
          or that he could make it:
          is proved by bringing forth all the species of proof.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e338">
          The first is made by inspection,
          as in what is notorious,
          which is proved by the evidence of fact as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e342" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t19-Dd1e108">
            c. euidentiam
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e348" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t19-Dd1e153">
            c. proposuisti de probationibus
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e352">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second is made by several witnesses,
          as also by one with other vehement presumptions.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e360">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The third by instruments.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e368">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The fourth by confession,
          concerning these four in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e373" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t13-Dd1e320">
            c. cum ad sedem de restitutione spoliatorum
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e379">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The fifth by the writings of ancient books 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e386" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t13-Dd1e275">
            c. cum causam eo titulo.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e390">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The sixth by violent presumption. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e396">32 q. 1 C. dixit dominus.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e400">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The seventh by fame with other presumptions 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e407" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t23-Dd1e290">
            c. Tertio loco eo titulo
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e411">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The eighth by oath 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e417" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t39-Dd1e153">
            de sententia excommunicationis c. si vero
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e421">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And here it should be noted that that proof ought to be introduced by which the defendant 
          can be convinced and to which he himself is bound to stand.
          For proof is the demonstration by certain arguments or means of a doubtful thing 
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e459">jurists in rubrica C. eo titulo</ref>.
          And it must necessarily conclude.
          Now let us see by going through each one whether those peoples will be able to be convinced 
          by any of them,
          so that they are bound to stand by such an institution.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e440">
          For by the evidence of fact and notoriety they will not,
          because they have never even slightly suspected this except by violence,
          and thus in fact contrary to all law:
          after their conversion,
          namely that there is such a man in the world,
          even the Pope,
          who can take away the dominions and jurisdiction of kingdoms which are held 
          by the law of nations and natural law by their own and natural lords:
          and transfer them at will to foreigners and those never known to them for ages.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e461">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          By the second indeed,
          namely by witnesses:
          they will by no means be able to be convinced either.
          <pb ed="#B" n="61-v"/>
          For witnesses ought to be legitimate and above all exception,
          that is most certain and indubitable:
          so that they cannot be repelled by any legitimate exception according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e504">
            the statement of the gloss in c. 1 de consanguinitate et affinit. 
            et instit. de inutilibus stipulationibus § item verborum
          </ref> 
          And although according to the laws and also natural reason:
          many kinds of persons are repelled from giving testimony:
          nevertheless we are content to speak of two.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e484">
          And indeed concerning the first:
          All who are of the family of the plaintiff are repelled from bearing testimony. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e521">l. pen. ff. de eo</ref> 
          And any other familiar 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e523">
            C. de his qui ad ecclesiam confugiunt l. fine § sane
          </ref>.
          Nor can witnesses be produced from the house of the plaintiff or accuser 
          in a civil or criminal cause 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e534">3 q. 5 throughout</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e539">§ item in criminali 4 q. 3</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e502">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly no one is admitted as witness in his own cause or one common to himself and another,
          regularly,
          neither principally nor secondarily 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e552">C. eo l. omnibus</ref> 
          In a common cause someone ought not to be admitted to testimony,
          because the common cause of two is each one's 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e559">ff. de ritu nuptiarum l. illud</ref>.
          And that he indeed ought to be repelled:
          natural reason itself openly teaches.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e521">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore all Spaniards exist as being of the family and house,
          that is of the subjection of our kings who are plaintiffs in this business:
          and this cause is common to all of them with the king:
          indeed most common,
          indeed most proper according to the affection of their greed and ambition:
          and more truly theirs than the kings',
          since no one crosses to these regions:
          except for seeking their own gain and ascent to a new and higher estate:
          torn by such execrable stings of avarice:
          and captured by the white cloud of such deadly blindness,
          the eyes of the mind impeded by a certain lethal insanity 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e594">c. auaritie cecitas de electione. lib. 6</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e599">c. sicut 47 dist.</ref>
          It follows that if those peoples do not stand by the testimony of Spaniards,
          led by natural reason alone,
          they are not to be thought to act contrary to the laws.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e557">
          For they have the exception of suspicion.
          And such an exception is quasi-peremptory because
          <pb ed="#B" n="62-r"/>
          if not directly yet obliquely it destroys.
          For with the proof removed,
          the right of the party remains useless as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e621">c. sepe de restitatione spoliatorum</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e626">l. duo sunt Titii ff. de testamentaria tutela</ref> 
          Concerning which 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e628">Panormitanus in c. 1 de exceptionibus</ref> 
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e633">c. 2</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-Rd1e635">a. de regulis iuris.</ref> 
          Because also in this case the reason of certitude and infallible truth ceases,
          through which alone those bearing testimony are believed,
          and witnesses are made legitimate and above all exception:
          and consequently it is necessary that belief in them cease,
          and they refuse to have faith in them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e361-d1e586">
          Therefore they cannot be convinced by Spanish witnesses,
          nor necessarily concluded to them,
          that that institution emanated from the Pope:
          or that the Pope himself had power in foreign kingdoms to change proprietary kings 
          without fault,
          and to subrogate or institute new foreigners in their place.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
