<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 22</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 22</title>
          <date when="2025-11-16">November 16, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-16" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="56-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Hd1e97">Section 22</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e99">
          § 22
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e104">
          Against this part and its proof there clearly object what was conceded and supposed 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e111">above § 5 at the end</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e113">§ 7</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e115">8</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e118">9</ref>.
          And most fully in our confirmatory treatise they were proved.
          Which we published with deliberate and special reason for the strengthening of the right 
          of our kings,
          namely that those same illustrious kings of Castile and Leon were instituted 
          as supreme princes by apostolic authority over that entire Indian world:
          to whose authority the See itself justly subjected all those kingdoms and all peoples 
          and nations as regards supreme jurisdiction or supreme principate.
          Then it is argued thus.
          For if the Apostolic See justly subjected that world to our kings,
          with a most just cause existing
          <pb ed="#B" n="56-v"/>
          (that is) 
          for the preaching of the faith and the conversion of those peoples:
          what need is there to seek or await their consent with sweet and supplicating words?
          For our kings can compel them by right of war to receive them:
          and thus whether they wish it or not,
          to have them as supreme princes according to what was proved in the aforesaid confirmatory treatise.
          Therefore this part appears to be superfluous:
          nor does it seem to be comprehended under the order of law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e147">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But if their consent must necessarily be required,
          and they should finally be unwilling to give it:
          by what reason I ask will that supreme and imperial power which our kings obtained 
          from the papal donation or institution subsist by itself:
          having no being in itself but in the intellect,
          like beings of reason or of second intention,
          or if it is something else that is supported from elsewhere,
          like a habit?
          Nevertheless it will be in vain,
          lacking proper operation.
          For everything is in vain which does not have proper operation:
          since every thing exists for the sake of its operation,
          as is said in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e171">2 de coelo et mundo</ref>.
          But the operation of any power,
          especially of supreme power,
          is first to take possession of the kingdom,
          that is of the citizens,
          because a kingdom consists primarily in persons according to that passage in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e180">Proverbs 14</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Qd1e182" source="http://scta.info/resource/prov14_28@1-11">
            In the multitude of people is the dignity of the king:
            and in the fewness of the people is the disgrace of the prince.
          </quote>
          And to test whether they willingly receive themselves into such dignity or power,
          prepared to obey.
          But if they should refuse to submit themselves:
          the second operation,
          namely compulsion to compel or punish them as rebels,
          must necessarily intervene.
          This is evident in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e198">Luke 19.</ref> 
          Where it is said: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Qd1e200" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc19_27@1-16">
            But as for my enemies (who did not wish me to reign over them) 
            bring them here and kill them before me
          </quote>.
          But in our case,
          with those peoples unwilling along with their kings and magistrates to consent 
          to the said institution,
          and thus denying consent without fear of juridical compulsion:
          the said papal institution or imperial or supreme power remains empty of its proper operations.
          Therefore in vain we will be able to call our kings supreme princes of the aforesaid world,
          except in name.
          Therefore either 
          <pb ed="#B" n="57-r"/>
          our kings by force and arms can by right compel those denying the said consent 
          to receive them as supreme princes:
          or such supreme power is feigned in vain.
          And our kings are called supreme princes of the aforesaid world.
          Therefore this part (namely) 
          that those peoples ought to be induced by sweet and gentle words to receive them 
          as supreme princes seems to contradict in every way what was determined,
          especially in the said confirmatory treatise etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e245">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          To this doubt we respond that this part does not obstruct what was determined 
          in the said treatise:
          but is comprehended under the order of natural and divine law:
          and therefore must necessarily be observed just like the rest,
          as has been declared in the preceding proofs.
          Nor can they be compelled by any mere man to give such consent unless they wish it:
          although we frankly confess that the Supreme Vicar of Christ justly and prudently 
          constituted our kings as supreme princes of that world,
          and wisely and deservedly adorned them with imperial dignity,
          not feigned or which is nothing in itself,
          with every act of intellect circumscribed,
          as beings of reason are:
          but truly being,
          having true being in the nature of things,
          providently and deservedly adorned them,
          as will be evident.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e282">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For the fuller elucidation of which it should be known that in three ways 
          or according to three states or times of those peoples we can speak concerning this part.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e295">
          First or for that time in which the aforesaid peoples are or were infidels.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e300">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly or after they have already properly received holy baptism.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e308">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Or thirdly after the invasions,
          wars,
          slaughters,
          captivities,
          despoliations of dominions,
          dignities:
          and other evils they have received savagely from the Spaniards.
          If indeed we speak of the first state,
          namely while the veil of infidelity holds those peoples:
          then the following conclusion is posited.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e337">
          <pb ed="#B" n="57-v"/>
          As long as those peoples exist as infidels:
          it will not be lawful for our kings to compel them to give the aforesaid consent.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e353">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The conclusion is proved in many ways,
          first thus:
          Our kings,
          as appears in the aforesaid confirmatory treatise in the second principal reason 
          for the proof of the first conclusion,
          have no coercive or contentious jurisdiction over the aforesaid peoples 
          except in potency while they are in their infidelity,
          but only voluntary in act.
          But compulsion,
          which will not occur without warlike apparatus,
          pertains to contentious jurisdiction which is rendered against the unwilling,
          as by the doctors in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e378">l. 2. ff. de officio proconsulis</ref>.
          For it lacks the foundation of all judgment,
          that is jurisdiction,
          according to that passage in Exodus 2 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Qd1e385" source="http://scta.info/resource/ex2_14@3-10">
            Who made you prince and judge over us?
          </quote> 
          And it can be objected to him: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Qd1e390" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom14_4@1-12">
            Who are you that judge another's servant.
            To his own lord he stands or falls
          </quote>. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e395">Romans 14</ref>.
          For jurisdiction must always precede the office of the one declaring law.
          Because it is born before it is exercised into act. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e416">C. qui pro sua iurisdictione. l. 1</ref>.
          And it is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e420">l. instar. C. de iure fisci lib. 10.</ref> 
          Whence such judgment is called usurped.
          Contrary to that in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e424">Deuteronomy 1</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Qd1e406" source="http://scta.info/resource/deut1_16@4-16 http://scta.info/resource/deut1_17@1-17">
            Hear them and judge what is just,
            because the judgment is God's
          </quote>.
          That is,
          judgment is rendered by divine authority.
          But he who judges concerning non-subjects or concerning those things to which 
          his jurisdiction does not extend:
          usurps the judgment of God.
          And is injurious to God himself as Augustine says 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e419">2, q. 1, c. Nomen</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e421">
            St. Thomas on the epistle to the Romans where above lectio 1
          </ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e426">2 2 q. 60, article 2, 3 and 6 in the body</ref>.
          Violence would also thus be inflicted on those judged and injury would be done.
          Contrary to that precept of law not to harm another 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e455">ff. de iustitia et iure l. iustitia.</ref> 
          Therefore 
          <pb ed="#B" n="58-r"/>
          it will not be lawful for our kings to compel them to give consent.
          The consequence is evident because then our king is a private person lacking contentious jurisdiction.
          As is proved explicitly in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e466">l. preses. l. et a, 2a ff. de officio presidis</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e471">a good gloss there</ref>.
          And it is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e473">d. l. de officio proconsulis</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e445">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore no other remedy remains to him to obtain possession of the aforesaid world 
          except that by the sweetest words and pleasing inducements those peoples be moved 
          and benevolently attracted so that they may give free consent:
          which this part intends.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e460">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly the conclusion is proved:
          the Church of God has no right to judge regularly concerning infidels 
          who have never received the faith,
          and far less concerning those who have not heard:
          especially if they have separate kingdoms,
          nor have they ever had anything good or evil to do with us.
          And this is evident in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e509">1 Corinthians 5</ref> 
          who himself frankly confesses saying:
          For what have I to do with judging those who are outside?
          Which opinion is common to all the holy Doctors,
          both Greek and Latin,
          namely that it pertains nothing to the Church to judge because they are not of its forum:
          except to have care for their conversion:
          as we have proved most extensively in our apology chapters 7, 8, 9.
          And this has finally been decided today by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e525">the Council of Trent Session 14 c. 2</ref> 
          where it is said thus: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Qd1e493">
            It is certain that the minister of baptism ought not to be a judge:
            since the Church exercises judgment on no one who has not first entered into it 
            through the gate of baptism. 
            <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Qd1e499" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor5_12@1-9">
              For what have I,
              says the Apostle,
              to do with judging those who are outside?
            </quote>
            It is otherwise with the domestics whom Christ the Lord once makes members of his body 
            by the washing of baptism
          </quote> 
          these words there:
          But to compel these infidels who are entirely outside the Church,
          dwelling in most separate kingdoms,
          to accept our kings as universal princes:
          is to judge concerning them and to judge them rather badly.
          Therefore it is not lawful for our kings to compel them.
          Therefore no remedy remains to them etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e519">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Thirdly the conclusion is proved:
          because such compulsion,
          since it must necessarily be warlike,
          would be done against those invincibly ignorant.
          And thus they would be punished without fault,
          which is most unjust,
          just as if children of 
          <pb ed="#B" n="58-v"/>
          five years old were punished for not knowing the articles of faith.
          For there is invincible ignorance which cannot be overcome by any study or diligence 
          according to the doctors.
          For no one sins in that which he cannot avoid 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e574">56 dist. c. satis peruersum</ref> 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e579">16 q. 7, c. inuentum</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e581">c. cognoscentes de constitutionibus</ref> 
          There:
          it is not fitting that a thing which lacks fault be called to harm.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e588">de restitutione spoliorum c. conquerente</ref>.
          Note in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e590">l. genero. ff. de his qui notentur infamia</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e595">l. 2, C de iuris et facti ignorantia</ref> 
          And such ignorance ought to harm no one 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e600">
            l. 52 25 § si seruus ff. de acquirendo rerum dominio
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e605">ff. ad l. aquil., l. si putatur</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e607">C. de poenis l. sancimus</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-Rd1e609">ff. de iuris et facti ignorantia l. iniquissimum.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e555">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But such infidels,
          especially the Indian nations,
          are invincibly ignorant of the papal institution and who the Pope is 
          and with what power he shines,
          what the Gospel is and its preachers:
          since these things are of the faith.
          Similarly who the kings of Spain are and by what title,
          for what reason or end they have sent their peoples to completely foreign kingdoms,
          and similar things.
          Nor can they overcome that ignorance by any study,
          unless you say that they are bound to divine.
          Therefore they are invincibly ignorant.
          And thus being ignorant they lack fault.
          Therefore to compel them by war would be most unjust.
          Therefore it is not lawful for our kings as long as those peoples remain in their infidelity 
          to compel them to receive them or to give consent,
          as we have said.
          Therefore no other remedy remains to them except that by flattery and sweet persuasions 
          they be induced to consent.
          If they wish to enter rightly and correctly into the supreme principate of that world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e596">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Fourthly the conclusion is proved thus:
          our kings of Spain are bound by natural and divine law,
          and thus from necessity of salvation,
          to order and dispose their first entry or that of their messengers into those parts of the Indies,
          and also their progress and all other things which would have to be done by them,
          so that they may be suitable for the preaching of the Gospel 
          and the conversion of the aforesaid peoples:
          and to avoid all contrary things which might in any way be able to impede 
          or even retard such preaching and conversion,
          as is evidently apparent through the fifth consideration.
          But if our kings should compel such peoples to give consent:
          or by their own authority take possession of that world by force:
          <pb ed="#B" n="59-r"/>
          will not all be disturbed,
          great and small:
          kings and subjects,
          peoples,
          rulers and magistrates,
          and will they not flee energetically to arms:
          whence it is certain that all things will be filled with human blood,
          slaughters and devastations of lands,
          as is evident in the preceding §?
          Will all these things make the entry of our kings into that world suitable for the preaching 
          of the faith and conversion of souls as to the end of this entire great business,
          proportionate?
          Or will they not be a vehement and efficacious obstacle to such an end?
          Indeed most efficacious for despising Christ and his religion:
          for holding them in horror and perpetually blaspheming.
          Let there be added to these what consideration 3 proclaims.
          Therefore it is not lawful for our kings to compel those peoples to receive them 
          as supreme prince unless they wish it voluntarily.
          Therefore no other remedy remains to them except by flatteries and good works 
          and gracious persuasions those peoples be induced and provoked to give free consent.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e668">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Nevertheless with all these things it stands well that the Supreme Vicar of Christ 
          from the duty of pastoral office could,
          indeed was bound (as we have proved in the often-mentioned confirmatory treatise) 
          to institute some Catholic king and bestow upon him a certain imperial and supreme dignity 
          and power over that world for the favor of the faith:
          who would cause it to be preached according to the form established by Christ:
          would remove impediments,
          if any should happen to arise from some powerful infidel princes,
          for instance Turks and Mohammedans,
          according to place and time:
          and would preserve in the solidity of that same faith those coming to 
          and receiving the same faith.
          Surely always preserving in his acts the law,
          especially divine and natural,
          whose eleventh part,
          namely that those peoples willingly receive our kings as universal princes,
          we have assigned.
          But in the meantime while they give consent,
          the aforesaid imperial power will not be idle or in vain,
          lacking its operations:
          even if there should never be any hope concerning the giving of consent 
          by those same peoples:
          since they have very many things in which operating our kings will certainly not be idle
          <pb ed="#B" n="59-v"/>
          as in the preceding ten parts in conclusion 2 § 11 and following,
          and in the corollary after the 3rd conclusion § 30 and § 39 will be shown more extensively.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e720">
          From which it appears that the aforesaid supreme dignity is not a being of reason:
          but real,
          having being in the nature of things,
          with every act of intellect circumscribed:
          although it does not subsist by itself.
          Nevertheless it subsists positively and subjectively in another,
          just as also a habit.
          For a habit is reduced to the command of the will and is that by which someone acts 
          when he wishes.
          But the will has itself indeterminately to infinite things.
          Nor is this in vain,
          although it does not actually tend to all:
          provided it actually tends to that which is suitable to place and time.
          And therefore also a habit is not in vain,
          although not all things are reduced into act,
          that which is suitable to the due end of the will according to the exigency of business and time.
          So it is concerning that power which we call supreme and imperial,
          conferred on our kings,
          which they have in potency,
          is not in vain nor idle.
          For they can accomplish very many things in order to extend the faith 
          and gain such peoples for Christ:
          although for a small or great space of time they are by no means received as universal princes,
          as is widely evident in the places immediately alleged above.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e348-d1e762">
          But the aforementioned power will have its perfection when such peoples and nations 
          shall have given free consent,
          accepting the papal institution concerning our kings over that world.
          But if they should never wish to give it as long as they remain infidels:
          our kings will be able to inflict no force on them without violation of divine and natural law:
          as already clearly appears from what has been said.
          Therefore it is easy to see:
          how necessary it is to induce them to consent by sweet words and gentle persuasions,
          which our eleventh part intends.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
