<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Preamble</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Preamble</title>
          <date when="2025-11-10">November 10, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
              >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex
            Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-10" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"> </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e58">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e58-Hd1e97">Preamble</head>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e58-d1e99"> This book was composed by the Most Reverend Don Friar
          Bartolome de las Casas, Bishop of Chiapa, in the year 1563. </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e58-d1e117">
          In the kingdoms which by common name are called Peru in our
          world of the Indies, there have been found and are found daily in the most ancient tombs
          of the dead, which are called Guacas in their language, great and marvelous treasures of
          diverse precious things: namely vessels or flasks of various shapes made of purest gold
          and silver, precious stones, emblems or furnishings made of precious material fabricated
          in wondrous ways; also accumulations of gold and silver and riches of such quantity and
          quality that they seem not to exist in the nature of things but to be formed by the
          imagination of dreamers while sleeping. Now therefore it is asked whether these things
          will belong indifferently to anyone who, either by his own authority or by license of our
          kings of Spain or of governors ruling those regions in the royal name, has sought, dug up,
          found, and taken them with the intention of keeping them for himself, and thus whether he
          acquires ownership of those precious things or treasures and can retain them with a safe
          conscience. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
