<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 26</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 26</title>
          <date when="2025-11-20">November 20, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-20" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="67-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Hd1e97">Section 26</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e99">
          § 26
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Against what has been decided,
          it seems that something not slight can be objected:
          namely that since to believe that the Supreme Pontiff is the Vicar of Christ 
          and can order and work all things in the Church for the utility of the same universal Church 
          which Christ was able to do,
          is of the necessity of faith:
          it seems that those peoples also are bound to believe that the Pope could order that world 
          in favor of the faith to be preached,
          and consequently to make the aforesaid institution.
          For it is manifest from what was determined above,
          especially in consideration 3,
          that the institution itself is ordered to the preaching of the Gospel:
          and the conversion of those peoples as for an end.
          But if they are bound to believe,
          therefore to obey and put into execution by working (that is) 
          to admit that institution and freely give consent,
          just as to other articles of faith.
          Otherwise 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Qd1e141" source="http://scta.info/resource/iac2_20@8-12">
            faith without works is worth nothing
          </quote> 
          James.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e146">
          Whence they will necessarily sustain one of two inconveniences:
          either they will not escape heresy if they do not believe:
          or they will commit grave contumacy if they do not obey.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e155">
          And then the Supreme Vicar of Christ and any bishop could hurl ecclesiastical censures 
          against them,
          which is contrary to the conclusion.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e163">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But it should be said that this does not obstruct.
          Indeed those peoples after they have entered through the first gate of the sacraments 
          and have been fully instructed in those things which are of the faith for several years,
          and sufficiently informed,
          are bound to believe:
          that the Pope is the Vicar of Jesus Christ,
          the supreme and unique head of the universal Church:
          having principate over all of it,
          to whom God has committed the care of both the earthly and heavenly empire:
          that is all are subject to him as regards
          <pb ed="#B" n="68-r"/>
          spiritual matters,
          and in case also as regards temporal matters,
          as we have proved extensively in our confirmatory treatise.
          And for this reason having an inferior or equal to none,
          but a superior and having jurisdiction over all and above all:
          and having fullness of power:
          and being the general prelate of all.
          And that the Roman Pontiff himself can establish firm,
          perpetual and immutable statutes:
          which firmness Christ indicates saying: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Qd1e202" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt16_18@9-15">
            and upon this rock I will build my church
          </quote>:
          as if namely Christ himself is the natural foundation 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e213" target="http://scta.info/resource/Icor3_11">
            1 Corinthians 3
          </ref> 
          but Peter and his successors are as it were the first rock in the foundation.
          Whence he after Christ is the foundation of the Church according to Jerome,
          Chrysostom,
          Origen,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e229">
            St. Thomas: 1. p. q. 112. 2. 2 2 q. 1 article 10 c. opusculum 1. c. 65 and c. 66
          </ref>.
          Likewise they are bound to believe that the Pope gives strength and authority to councils 
          and to the statutes of councils 17 dist. concilia:
          and who finally judges all:
          and can be judged by no one: 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e241">40 dist. c. si papa</ref>, 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Qd1e246" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d40-d1e202@62-66">
            unless he is found straying from the faith
          </quote>: 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e249" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c9q3-Dd1e219">
            9, q. 3, c. conquestus.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e253">
          And all the aforesaid are proved in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e257" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d12-Dd1e112">
            c. non decet 12 dist.
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e261" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d19-Dd1e225">
            19 dist. c. ita dominus
          </ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e264" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c2q6-Dd1e311">
            2, q. 6, c. qui se scit
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e267" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1430-d1e124">
            c. pro humani de homicidio, lib. 6
          </ref> 
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e273" source="http://scta.info/resource/kdhaWs-d1e301-d1e116">
            clemen. Romani de iureiurando
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e278" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d22-Dd1e115">
            c. omnes, 22 dist.
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e281">extravagant. unam sanctam per bonifacium</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e286" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d17">
            17 dist. throughout
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e289">2, q. 5, c. ideo</ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e298" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c3q6-Dd1e235">
            3, q. 6, c. dudum.
          </ref> 
          All of which are ecclesiastical privileges of the Roman and universal Church 
          conferred by God as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e303" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d22-Dd1e115">
            c. omnes 22 dist.
          </ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Qd1e308">
            which whoever does not believe or tries to take away,
            is a heretic
          </quote> 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e313" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d22-Dd1e115">
            d. c. omnes.
          </ref> 
          For all this is of divine law.
          Whence concerning this one special article of faith is proposed to be believed by all 
          in the Symbol:
          I believe in the holy catholic Church.
          Which is understood to be the universal church with its supreme head,
          namely the pontiff,
          that is the Pope,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e333" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d22-Dd1e115">
            d. c. omnes
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e336" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d12-Dd1e112">
            d. c. non decet
          </ref>.
          St. Thomas also says in opusculum contra errores Gregorum and 2 2 q. 1 article 10.
          That because the Pope has the primacy of the universal Church,
          <pb ed="#B" n="68-v"/>
          to whom it pertains to determine those things which are of the faith 
          so that they may be held by all with unshaken faith:
          and in him principally resides the authority of the universal Church:
          and therefore it also pertains to the faith to adhere to the determination 
          of the Supreme Pontiff in those things which are of the faith:
          and in those things which regard good morals.
          Because in such matters the Church cannot err,
          and consequently neither can its head insofar as he is head or insofar as he is pontiff.
          Which is understood when he is questioned in doubtful matters,
          not as a learned man or such a person,
          but as the head of Christianity.
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e367" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q1-Dd1e283">
            c. quoties
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e370" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q1-d1e255">
            c. a recta
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e374" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q1-Dd1e313">
            c. hec est fides 24 q. 1
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e380" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c25q1-d1e175">
            25, q. 1, c. violatores
          </ref>.
          Wherefore to him belong greater matters concerning baptism and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e385">c. 42 dist.</ref> 
          And generally he has the right to interpret all doubts which have arisen 
          in the Church of God 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e392" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l4t17-Dd1e214">
            extra qui filii sint legitimi cap. per principalem
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e403">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But in other matters which do not regard the faith and good morals,
          as in sentences and determinations which pertain to particular facts,
          as when there is a question of possessions or of crimes or of such things,
          the Pope can err because he follows human reason which can be deceived,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e418">St. Thomas says Quodlibet. 9 article last</ref> 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e422">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Nd1e419">John of Naples</name> 
            after him Quodlibet, 11
          </ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e427">
            extra de sen. excomunionis c. a nobis el. 2
          </ref> 
          applies,
          where it is stated that the judgment of the Church deceives and is deceived.
          Indeed one is not a heretic who thinks contrary to the determination of the Church 
          in matters other than those regarding faith and good morals.
          Just as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e443">
            Pope John XXII determined in extravagant. ad conditionem
          </ref>:
          that right cannot be separated from use in the use of consumables:
          and yet he says that those contradicting this sentence are contumacious 
          and rebels of the Church,
          but not heretics.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e445">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But of such a kind is the business which we are treating at present.
          For it does not pertain to faith or good morals that the Supreme Pontiff has granted 
          dominion or principate of those lands to the kings of Spain,
          since such institution is neither included in nor founded on faith or divine 
          or natural law or reason,
          nor is it found in the doctrine of the saints,
          but rather the contrary will be found.
          But it is rather a certain determination of human law which could be otherwise,
          and depending on human will,
          <pb ed="#B" n="69-r"/>
          that is of the Pope.
          Whence even after the reception of the faith and full information of all things 
          which regard the faith and which they are bound to know:
          although such peoples are obligated to believe that the Pope is the Vicar of Christ 
          and has from Christ all the authority which he has,
          and jurisdiction over every man in the manner that has been said,
          and other such things:
          nevertheless they are not bound to believe:
          that the Pope could,
          by the authority divinely granted to him,
          have instituted the kings of Spain as universal princes to the prejudice 
          of the natural kings and magistrates without their fault of that entire world:
          so that if they do not believe it,
          they incur the fault of heresy.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e497">
          Which can be proved in two ways.
          First thus:
          No one is bound to believe except those things which fall under faith,
          either directly and principally,
          for instance the articles of faith,
          which namely are concerning those things which we will see in the homeland,
          such as the Trinity of persons:
          or through which we come to the homeland,
          such as the mystery of the incarnation of Christ,
          or indirectly and secondarily,
          such as those things from which,
          if they were not believed:
          the corruption of some article would follow,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e526">St. Thomas 2 2 q. 11 article 2 c.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e528">q. 1 article 6 1</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e531">article 8 in the body</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e534">q. 2. article 5 c. article 7. c.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e519">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          All things which are in scripture pertain also to the faith by accident 
          as declarative of the aforesaid,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e546">St. Thomas says where above q. 1 article 6 ad 1</ref> 
          moreover all things which are contained in the doctrine of the Church pertain to the faith 
          by accident.
          Because as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e553">the same Holy Doctor says q. 5 article 3</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e555">3 sententiarum dist. 23, q. 3 article 3. q. 2</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Rd1e560">Quodlibet 6 article 6.</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-Qd1e535">
            Whoever does not adhere to the doctrine of the Church as to an infallible 
            and divine rule,
            that is does not believe all things which the Church believes and holds,
            which proceed from the first truth manifest in the scriptures,
            does not have the habit of faith:
            but holds those things which are of faith otherwise than through faith
          </quote> 
          these from him.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e548">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But neither in the articles of faith which pertain to divinity or to humanity:
          nor in the divine scriptures,
          nor in the doctrine of the Church is it found that the universal principate of that world 
          is owed to the kings of Spain because of the fact that they take care 
          of preaching the faith in it:
          or that the Pope can grant it:
          nor that by not believing this the corruption of some article follows.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e565">
          Therefore those nations are not bound to believe that the Pope could institute our kings 
          as universal princes of that world.
          The Minor 
          <pb ed="#B" n="69-v"/>
          is clear by examining each one.
          The consequence is proved because we are not bound to believe and adhere to all the acts 
          and determinations of the Supreme Pontiff by necessity of faith:
          but only to those which regard the faith and good morals,
          as appears from what has been said.
          Therefore neither that he could institute our kings as universal princes of that world 
          or grant the empire of it:
          because this does not regard faith or good morals:
          but only regards the will of the Pope himself who wished to grant it 
          to the aforesaid most illustrious kings:
          which if he had not done:
          the faith would always remain uncorrupted.
          Nor by not believing this does the corruption of some article follow:
          because if it would follow,
          it would be an article:
          it is not corrupted by this since we can think the contrary of this,
          which is:
          that the Pope cannot err in any case which does not regard faith or good morals:
          and yet that article will remain uncorrupted,
          because it is not doubted that the Pope is the Vicar of God or the head 
          of the universal Church,
          or that in those things which are of faith and good morals he determines things 
          true and without error and salutary etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e400-d1e616">
          Therefore the corruption of some article does not follow.
          Therefore not to believe that the Pope could make such an institution:
          the fault of heresy is not incurred.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>