<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 16</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 16</title>
          <date when="2025-11-13">November 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="44-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Hd1e97">Section 16</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e99">
          § 16
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e104">
          Part 11
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e109">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          After the demonstration concerning the title,
          that as modestly,
          as gently,
          as discreetly and as sweetly as can be done,
          the peoples and nations and their kings ought to be persuaded,
          moved and induced by good reasons,
          sweet and gentle words and pleasing inducements:
          with the advantages shown which they will obtain daily,
          to this end that they may voluntarily consent to the aforesaid papal institution 
          concerning our kings as universal princes and lords of that world etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e135">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          This part is proved in many ways,
          but first some things previously set forth must be recalled,
          <pb ed="#B" n="44-v"/>
          the first of which is:
          that among those infidels and similar peoples,
          dominions and jurisdictions,
          principalities and royal dignities exist justly and legitimately 
          by the law of nature and of nations,
          confirmed by divine law of both testaments.
          As was proved above § 5 and 6 in the first consideration.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e160">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second thing to be remembered is that such peoples and nations 
          with their kings and princes are or were free when we found them:
          recognizing no superior outside themselves,
          having dominion both pure and mixed,
          imperium and all manner of jurisdiction and all the rights of a prince 
          which among us we attribute to the emperor,
          as was evident where immediately alleged and will be more expressly evident below § 25,
          conclusion 4.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e179">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The third thing is that the Supreme Pontiff by the said institution 
          or provision concerning our kings:
          did not intend to deprive the natural Kings and lords of their dominions 
          or jurisdictions,
          rights or dignities etc.
          Because no cause existed for it,
          as we proved at length in the 4th and 2nd considerations.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e196">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          These things therefore being recalled,
          this part is proved first thus.
          Such a promotion or papal institution concerning our kings as superiors of that world 
          and over the natural kings of that place:
          brings great prejudice to their freedom,
          since they are free,
          recognizing no superior.
          Therefore it is necessary that by good reasons they be persuaded,
          moved,
          and induced to this end that they may freely consent to the said institution 
          or promotion and hold it as valid.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e218">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The antecedent is evident:
          because since those peoples and communities,
          by giving them a new king over their natural kings or lords:
          would henceforth be burdened with a double burden because they would be forced 
          to serve two,
          indeed multiple lords and keep fidelity.
          Whence they would be led into double and harsher servitude.
          Similarly their Kings and princes would be made to have a lord over themselves 
          and to recognize a superior,
          which is horrible to free kings.
          It is manifest that such a promotion or papal institution concerning our kings 
          over that world brings great prejudice to the freedom of both,
          namely of the subjects and of the natural kings or lords.
          For it is a certain species of servitude as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e243">ff. de usufructu l. si cuius § 1</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e249">l. cum seruum ad fi. C. de seruis fugitivis</ref>.
          And he who is subject to someone's jurisdiction is called as it were servant of that person.
          And jurisdiction is equated to dominion according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e266">Baldus in d. l. cum seruum</ref> 
          and the 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e269">gloss notes d. l. si cuius</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e274">c. cum olim el. 2o de priuilegiis</ref> 
          There 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Qd1e262">the right of profession</quote> 
          which is contrary to freedom,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e281">c. ne dei de symonia</ref> 
          in all of which it is noted that the oath of fidelity or fidelity itself 
          and subjection itself is a certain servitude.
          As 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e286">
            Baldus notes in l. si aquam. C. de seruitutibus et aqua pluuie
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e270">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Moreover servitude is that by which someone is subjected to another's dominion 
          contrary to nature,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e297">l. libertas ff. de statu hominum</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e299">institut. de iure personarum § seruitus</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e304">1 distin 6. ius gentium</ref> 
          For in this a slave differs from a free person:
          because by servitude that is taken away which otherwise would belong to him,
          namely to act freely and to be able to dispose of his person 
          and his property at will.
          Whence someone does not have free dominion over an act concerning which,
          when he wishes to exercise it,
          he is impeded in some way.
          For every contradiction or prohibition,
          whether temporary or perpetual,
          contradicts freedom as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e322">d. l. libertas</ref>.
          Whence the definition of freedom is the natural faculty (that is) 
          the possibility of that which it is permitted for each one to do,
          unless what is prohibited by force or by law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e301">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But when force or necessity is inflicted,
          any faculty of acting or disposing freely is taken away 
          and thus freedom is prejudiced and consequently sadness and misery is caused.
          Thus says the Philosopher in Metaphysics 5,
          speaking of the violent and necessary,
          that the violent brings this:
          that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Qd1e321">
            everything violent is sad or lamentable
          </quote>.
          Which he proves through the saying of a certain poet saying 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Qd1e325">
            that every necessary or violent thing is sad or lamentable
          </quote>.
          For necessity is a certain violence. 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Qd1e333">
            Force,
            says the poet,
            compelled me to do this,
            that is necessity
          </quote> 
          Where St. Thomas says 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Qd1e337">
            the violent is what is contrary to the natural inclination of a natural thing
          </quote>.
          And it is what impedes the purpose in the prosecution of a voluntary movement 
          already begun.
          And it also prohibits it from beginning.
          Whence when the will is impeded,
          we are saddened.
          For sadness is from those things which happen to us against our will.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e350">
          But everything sad is hateful and horrible because nature always,
          insofar as it can,
          flees from the sad:
          for it seeks the delightful according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e386">the philosopher in Ethics 8</ref> 
          and such is servitude,
          which for this reason is called the image of death according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e390">Polycraticus lib. 7. c. 17.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e396">ff. de regulis iuris l. quot attinet.</ref> 
          and it is the extreme of all evils,
          to be repelled not only by war but by death according to 
          <pb ed="#B" n="45-v"/>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e403">Cicero in Philippics c. 2</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e405">Sallust in Catiline</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Qd1e367">
            no good man loses freedom except along with his life
          </quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e370">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore by instituting over those nations and their kings another king or lord,
          they are led into servitude by which it is taken away from them to act freely 
          and they cannot dispose of their own persons and estates and those belonging to them at will:
          whence they do not have free dominion over the acts concerning which,
          when they will wish to exercise them,
          either publicly,
          that is for the common good of their republics,
          as regards kings and lords:
          or privately (that is) each private person for the private good,
          they are impeded:
          and consequently all these things are contrary to their will,
          as being against natural inclination.
          Therefore the aforesaid papal institution concerning our kings brings great 
          and enormous prejudice to their freedom,
          and therefore rightly these things will be lamentable to them 
          and very saddening.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e402">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The consequence is truly proved because free persons or free communities 
          or free peoples can of their own accord subject themselves to the judgment 
          or governance of others,
          although they are not superiors.
          Whence through pacts which intervene between men,
          someone can obligate his person and make his condition worse. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e461">l. cum scimus C. de agricolis et censitis lib. 11o</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e466">l. 1 § 1.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e468">l. iuris gentium et pretorum ff. de pactis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e473">c. 1 et 2, extra de pactis</ref>.
          The same is true in kingdoms and in any free communities as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e481">l. vt preiudicium</ref> 
          that they may wish to bear that patiently,
          they are to be moved,
          persuaded and induced by good reasons and pleasing inducements,
          and certainly requested.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e433">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly the same is proved thus:
          Those kingdoms and peoples of that entire world are or were free 
          by the law of nature and of nations at the time when we found them,
          having kings or princes,
          not recognizing any superior outside themselves either by right or in fact,
          as has often been repeated.
          Therefore without their free consent and approval another new king cannot be given to them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e451">
          Therefore so that they may freely give such consent,
          it is necessary that they be moved,
          induced and persuaded by the sweetest,
          gentlest,
          indeed simple words,
          pleasing inducements and good reasons.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e460">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second consequence is evident.
          The first is proved,
          first because a most grave injury and most enormous damage 
          would be done to them by violence,
          <pb ed="#B" n="46-r"/>
          namely we would subject kings and subjects,
          lords and subordinates to servitude contrary to natural law and reason.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e479">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second because such a principate would be violent,
          usurped and tyrannical.
          As proved 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e541">1. q. 1. c. principatus</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e543">C. de sacrosantis ecclesiis l. decernimus</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-d1e489">
          Where Baldus says that provinces which have been accustomed to be ruled by Kings 
          through their Kings and princes are said to be under their natural dominion 
          (that is) by the law of nations as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e561">l. ex hoc iure ff. de iustitia et iure</ref> 
          and if another takes dominion there against the will of the king 
          (add: and of the people according to what is to be said 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e568">below § 28</ref>) 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Qd1e506">
            that one is a tyrant because,
            says Baldus,
            usurped dominions are called tyrannies
          </quote>.
          These his words in form.
          Where he also adds that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Qd1e512">
            to those invading camps pertaining to just lords,
            those camps cannot be conceded by a prince,
            whether the invaders are private or singular persons:
            or whether they are communities as in 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e582">l. 2. C. de fundis et saltibus lib. 11o</ref> 
            where this is noted
          </quote> 
          these words of Baldus.
          The same opinion holds in formal words 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e269-Rd1e588">
            Angelus de Perusio in repetitione l. ciuitas ff. de rebus creditis
          </ref>.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>