<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 19</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 19</title>
          <date when="2025-11-14">November 14, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-14" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="50-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Hd1e97">Section 19</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e99">
          § 19
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The same is evident in the 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e110">second King</ref>,
          namely David.
          Who although he too had been anointed as king by the prophet Samuel 
          at God's command as is found in Kings,
          nevertheless did not dare to involve himself in exercising royal power 
          until after Saul's death he was established and admitted or received 
          and approved by the authority and consent of the people,
          namely by the tribe of Judah first in Hebron over that same tribe as king,
          as is evident in 2 Kings 2,
          and then was established and accepted as king by the other tribes,
          as is written in 2 Kings 5.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e131">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          From which it appears evidently that David,
          although he had through the first anointing made by divine command the institution 
          and through this had right to the kingdom:
          nevertheless he did not have right in the kingdom to the execution of royal power
          <pb ed="#B" n="51-r"/>
          in the people of Israel until,
          with Saul dead,
          who was the true and legitimate king (although rejected by God,
          most wicked,
          sacrilegious and a tyrant in practice),
          the people received him and placed and instituted him over themselves as king,
          approving and consenting voluntarily to the divine nomination or institution.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e157">
          Whence two things were required so that David might have right in the kingdom 
          even after divine institution.
          One that Saul should die first.
          The other that he should be received and instituted as king by the people.
          For never as long as Saul lived was it God's intention to deprive him of the use of the kingdom,
          but only of succession.
          The other was namely the acceptance and free handing over of possession of the kingdom 
          by the consent of the people,
          before which David did not wish to involve himself in the administration of the kingdom 
          by his own authority,
          although he knew very well that he had been elected by God and anointed at his command 
          as king by Samuel,
          and had the title and right to the kingdom.
          Nor even immediately after Saul's death did he assume the kingdom for himself:
          knowing it to be a divine precept that it ought to be established and enthroned 
          by the consent and authority of the people. 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e189">
            Him,
            he says,
            you shall set up whom the Lord your God shall choose
          </quote> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e191">Deuteronomy 17.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e195">
          Whence in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e199">2 Kings 2</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e201">
            having heard of Saul's death,
            he immediately consults the Lord,
            asking whether he should go up to any city.
            And having received a divine oracle that he should go up to Hebron:
            he remained in the towns of Hebron until the people should gather.
            And the men of Judah coming anointed David there that he might reign over Judah
          </quote>.
          These words there.
          Behold the handing over of possession.
          The same appears in chapter 5 of the same book where it is said: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e214">
            All the tribes of Israel came to David in Hebron saying: 
            Behold we are your bone and your flesh
          </quote> 
          and a little below. 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e222">
            The elders of Israel also came to the king in Hebron,
            and King David struck a covenant with them in Hebron before the Lord,
            and they anointed David as king over Israel
          </quote> 
          etc.
          These words there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e235">
          Josephus in book 7 chapter 2 of the Antiquities says that by one decree 
          they confirmed David's rule.
          But the Master of Histories on 2 Kings,
          chapter 6,
          says:
          that first David was anointed as a sign,
          namely by Samuel at God's command,
          by which anointing the title and right to the kingdom was conferred on him.
          Secondly as king over Judah,
          namely by the consent and acceptance of the people holding as valid the election 
          or institution of God and the handing over of possession of the kingdom.
          Thirdly as king over Israel by all the tribes etc.
          Behold how David beyond the institution and nomination and divine anointing:
          needed the authority,
          approval,
          establishment,
          anointing,
          and handing over 
          <pb ed="#B" n="51-v"/>
          of possession of the kingdom by the free consent of all the people,
          so that he might actually be legitimate,
          true and natural king,
          and might have legitimate and juridical entrance into the kingdom:
          and also might obtain the right and exercise of royal power in that kingdom:
          so that those two things which the Lord had previously commanded concerning establishing a king 
          should be observed (namely) 
          that God should choose or nominate the one he wished:
          and that the people by their own and free consent should approve the said election 
          and should establish for themselves as king him thus elected by God 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e300">Deuteronomy 17</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e296">
          Concerning these matters see 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e307">
            Burgensis on 1 Kings c. 28 in the first addition to Nicholas de Lyra
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e312">
            Conrad on contracts,
            treatise 1 q. 7 at the beginning
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e303">
          Therefore by the example and authority of divine scripture,
          indeed as it seems by the precept and divine ordinance,
          without the free consent and approval of those peoples and their kings themselves,
          another new king cannot be given to them or established over their natural kings.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e314">
          That this is indeed a precept and must necessarily be observed even now among Christians 
          in the new testament is proved:
          because all precepts insofar as they contain what is moral and insofar as the reason of justice 
          which they contain are immutable for all time according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e324">St. Thomas 1 2 q. 100 article 8 throughout</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e330">
          And the reason is twofold according to him there in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e344">a. 1 and 3</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e346">q. 109 article 4 in the body</ref> 
          because they contain the very intention of the legislator,
          namely God,
          as appears in the precepts of the first table which are ordered to God 
          and contain the very order to the common good which is God.
          And in the precepts of the second table which contain the very order of justice 
          to be observed among men,
          namely that nothing undue be done to anyone and what is due be rendered to each one.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e347">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second reason is because moral precepts are from the dictate of the law of nature 
          which in themselves pertain to good morals and agree with natural reason:
          and therefore always in every time and place they have the reason and force of obligating:
          instit. de iure naturali gentium et ciuili § nam et naturalia.
          But this precept concerning establishing a king by divine ordinance,
          although it is partly judicial and consequently does not oblige for all time 
          unless it is established anew by divine or human law according to that passage in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e368">Hebrews 7</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e370" source="http://scta.info/resource/hebr7_12@1-10">
            The priesthood being translated,
            it is necessary that a translation of the law be made
          </quote> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e392">St. Thomas 1 2 q. 104, article 4 in the body</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e394">q. 105 article 1 c.</ref>
          Nevertheless it contains part of a moral precept and thus today has the force of obligating.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e377">
          This is evident thus.
          For it was judicial insofar namely as God spoke expressly to that people through an oracle 
          and assigned a certain person whom they should establish as king,
          and that he should be of that Hebrew race 
          <pb ed="#B" n="52-r"/>
          and not of another nation:
          and that he should not lead the people back to Egypt according to the letter etc. 
          which specially pertained to that people alone.
          But partly it was moral insofar namely as it pertains principally to every community 
          by natural law from the beginning to establish for itself someone who may rule all of it,
          even without new divine ordinance.
          And the law of nature has never been revoked but confirmed and established by divine law,
          as was said above 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e405">Exodus 20</ref> 
          there 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e407" source="http://scta.info/resource/ex20_17@1-5">
            You shall not covet your neighbor's house
          </quote> 
          etc 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e409">Leviticus 19</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e411" source="http://scta.info/resource/lev19_13@1-9">
            You shall not defraud your neighbor:
            nor oppress him by violence
          </quote> 
          etc.
          In which all injustice is prohibited.
          And for this reason the Lord willed that in the establishment of a king,
          the consent and approval of the people should be required,
          and without it the king would not have the exercise of royal power,
          although divine institution alone would suffice,
          since to the people and that community otherwise it would pertain by the law of nature 
          without new divine institution.
          And therefore although from that part by which that precept is judicial 
          it does not have perpetual obligation but was emptied out like the other judicial precepts 
          by Christ,
          nevertheless from the part by which it is moral it has the force of obligating perpetually 
          from the very dictate of natural reason.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e442">
          Because natural reason dictates that this ought to be done,
          namely that any free people by their own consent should elect,
          accept,
          approve and establish him who is to reign over them and to whom they commit themselves,
          not for his own but for the common utility of that same people:
          and consequently no one,
          not being his own judge,
          especially without legitimate,
          true and examined cause,
          should deprive such a people of the right of electing,
          accepting,
          and establishing for themselves a king or ruler.
          From which fact that God himself did not wish a king to reign in his peculiar people 
          without the free consent of the people to reign,
          for grave injury and great injustice would be done to any free people 
          if against its will and free consent:
          or if it is compelled to consent,
          a king or lord is given to it.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e478">
          For this is included in those precepts of nature 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e482">Tobit 4</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e484">
            What you do not wish done to you by another:
            do not do to him
          </quote> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e489">Matthew 7</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e491" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt7_12@1-8">
            All things whatsoever you would that men should do to you
          </quote> 
          etc.
          It is also included in the precepts of the Decalogue of the second table there: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e500">You shall not steal</quote>:
          in which all violence inflicted on one's neighbor and every illicit 
          <pb ed="#B" n="52-v"/>
          usurpation of another's property:
          and whatever of one's neighbor's things is illicitly taken away,
          and rather those things which touch freedom,
          are understood to be prohibited as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e544">c. poenale 14, 5</ref>.
          But the precepts of the second table contain,
          as we said,
          the very order of justice to be preserved among men,
          namely that nothing undue be done to anyone.
          And according to this reasoning such precepts remain indispensable 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e523">St. Thomas 1 2 q. 100 c. 8</ref>.
          And therefore that precept concerning establishing a king by the consent 
          and approval of the people is moral and immutable,
          and consequently has the force of obligating even in the new testament:
          although it has been revoked from that part by which it was judicial.
          It is confirmed because a law abrogated as to one part,
          as to the part not abrogated,
          is still in green observance.
          This is noted by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e569">Canonists in c. 1 de constitutionibus</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e574">l. 1. de latina libertate tollenda</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e576">Baldus there</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e542">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          How much more so that we can say that that law as regards the judicial part which it has 
          seems to have been absorbed and renewed and instituted again by the authority of the Church 
          because of its reason.
          For a law can be alleged although it has been abrogated because of its reason,
          since the reason is not removed as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e593">l. eas ff. de capite dimi.</ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e598">
            gloss in l. 1 at the beginning de coniungendis cum emancipato liberis
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e602">gloss in the first constitution C.</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e604">l. 2, c. de ueteri iure enucleando</ref> 
          thus blessed Jerome alleges that law because of its reason 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e560">on Leviticus and is found 8 q. 1 c. licet</ref> 
          where it is said 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e565">
            although therefore concerning establishing a prince he had commanded and chosen,
            nevertheless the synagogue is also convoked
          </quote> 
          etc.
          For the reason of the law is that he who is to be placed over the people 
          should be known and approved by that same people and not be placed over the unwilling.
          Whence Jerome immediately adds 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e580">
            Therefore in ordaining a priest the presence of the people is also required 
            so that all may know that the one who is more excellent
          </quote> 
          etc.
          To this purpose 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e587" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d63-d1e273">
            68 dist. c. ples dictrensis
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e592" corresp="#cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e596">
            chapter nosse
          </ref> 
          apply.
          Where it is said 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e596" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d63-d1e288@59-84">
            that with the clergy and people convoked,
            such a one may be elected there by God's mercy against whom the sacred canons do not object.
            For the election of priests and the consent of the faithful people must be applied
          </quote>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e603">c. ultimo</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Qd1e606" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d63-d1e663@26-40">
            that no one be given to the unwilling and those not seeking:
            lest the unwilling people despise or hate a bishop not desired
          </quote>.
          The same is prohibited 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-Rd1e611" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d61-d1e299">
            61 dist. c. nullus in uitis
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e308-d1e617">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          It appears therefore that even now what God commanded concerning establishing a prince 
          ought to be observed:
          namely:
          that always the free consent and acceptance of the people be awaited:
          and that unless the consent and acceptance or voluntary approval of the people 
          intervene in the establishment of a new prince:
          that prince or king 
          <pb ed="#B" n="53-r"/>
          himself will not be able to have the exercise of royal power,
          as has been proved.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>