<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 37</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 37</title>
          <date when="2025-12-13">December 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
          John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
      url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="101-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-Hd1e97">Section 37</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e99">
          § 37
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> From what has been concluded and determined 
          through the conclusions and their corollaries,
          with their proofs,
          there follow other things for the response to the doubt touched upon above 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-Rd1e5">§ 5</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e121">
          First Corollary
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e126">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> It is not lawful for our kings of Castile and Leon,
          our lords (saving justice),
          just as it is not for other kings of the world,
          without the permission and good pleasure of King Inca or his successors,
          and similarly for the other kings of that world:
          to interfere or to order inquiry to be made concerning treasures that are 
          in those kingdoms or other precious things,
          or to take them from there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e148">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> The corollary is proven in multiple ways.
          First,
          because as to entry into those regions without permission of the natural 
          kings and lords or peoples:
          it was no more lawful for our kings (saving justice) than for other kings 
          of the world,
          since during all that time when those nations with their kings did not 
          consent to said institution and did not spontaneously accept our kings as 
          universal lords or princes,
          they would have had no acquired right,
          indeed they do not have it in the thing but only to the thing,
          they have nothing else but a title:
          not act but habit,
          and not yet fully in habit,
          nor any juridical but only an occupied possession,
          as has been most fully proven above in many places,
          especially in conclusion 2 through all its sections,
          most especially through the eleventh,
          and in conclusion 3 and the following corollary,
          and in the 5th conclusion with its proofs.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e185">
          Therefore it is no more lawful for our kings (saving justice) without 
          permission of King Inca or his successors to interfere in inquiring about 
          or taking treasures by their order or command than for the other kings of 
          the world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e196">
          The consequence is clear because,
          setting aside the papal institution and other qualities that proceed from it,
          and which nevertheless do not help toward properly and correctly assuming 
          the principate of that world in act and exercising royal power without 
          those things that are necessarily required for observing the order of law,
          as is contained in conclusion 2,
          it is manifest that the same reasoning applies to our kings as to the 
          other kings of the world.
          And thus the oft-mentioned papal institution does not stand in the way,
          which above 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-Rd1e196">§ 5</ref> 
          was opposed as standing in the way.
          Therefore it is no more lawful for our kings,
          saving justice,
          to do those things etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e222">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Secondly,
          the corollary is proven because if any king of the world or people of that 
          world should attempt to enter to search out and take treasures and other 
          precious things without permission of King Inca and other kings his 
          successors,
          and more forcefully if they should contend against his or their will,
          they would do injury to them and gravely disturb them,
          committing violence,
          theft or rapine,
          as was deduced above 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-Rd1e241">§ 5</ref>.
          Therefore similarly if our kings should attempt to do the same things,
          they would inflict injury on King Inca,
          they would commit violence,
          theft,
          and rapine (saving the reverence of their highness),
          since our Catholic kings themselves are subject to natural and eternal or 
          divine law and reason just as much as the others,
          as appears in consideration 2.
          Therefore etc.
          For the vicar of Christ does not grant permission to our kings or their 
          messengers by said institution to disturb,
          scandalize,
          despoil that whole world and to place it in implacable hatred against the 
          Christian religion and Christ's name,
          as appears in the 3rd and 4th considerations.
          Therefore our kings can in no way (saving justice),
          just as other kings of the world cannot,
          order entry to search out or seek treasures etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e285">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Indeed,
          the messengers sent by our Spanish kings greatly disturbed all those 
          nations,
          although certainly against the will of our kings,
          as has been said.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e301">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> For it was seen above 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-Rd1e301">§ 21</ref> 
          that someone disturbs another by simple entry into his possession against 
          his will.
          They indeed entered the lands and foreign possessions against the will of 
          all kings and peoples universally like a most turbulent wind.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e323">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Someone disturbs by taking away fruits.
          Thus our men disturbed those peoples by carrying away all the fruits of 
          those lands,
          of forests,
          mountains,
          rivers,
          waters,
          gold,
          silver,
          metals and the rest etc.,
          as appeared above 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-Rd1e345">§ 33 in the proof of the 5th conclusion</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e348">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Again,
          someone disturbs by plowing and sowing etc.
          Thus our men disturbed and disturb by usurping all those lands not their 
          own,
          with which they do and dispose of whatever they please at will.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e363">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Moreover,
          someone disturbs by resistance:
          behold these disturb and have disturbed by most unjust bloody wars,
          impiously slaughtering all the inhabitants universally,
          and those whom they leave alive,
          reducing to servitude.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e377">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Someone also disturbs by selling another's thing 
          and handing it over to a buyer.
          Behold all things that these have wrongly seized,
          as if they possessed by best right and were owners,
          they sell,
          transfer,
          give,
          and do whatever they wish with them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e391">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Moreover,
          someone disturbs who asserts that he has servitude in another's thing.
          But these not only assert:
          but they seize and usurp violently,
          and not only in the things of others but innumerable persons themselves,
          like notorious kidnappers,
          reducing them to most bitter servitude.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e410">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Finally,
          he disturbs who brings annoyances and provides impediment to another's 
          right.
          But who,
          I ask,
          ever brought such bitter annoyances to men and provided impediments to 
          foreign rights as these have?
          Both through wars,
          through captivities,
          through insults,
          through bereavements,
          through deprivations of dignities even royal,
          honors,
          dominions,
          jurisdictions and absolutely all goods,
          through violations of wives and daughters,
          and through immense other calamities,
          our men have disturbed and today disturb (as has been proven),
          and the whole world is witness,
          and consequently they have provided most effective impediment,
          denying that they might use peacefully every right that pertained to them 
          either publicly or privately,
          as is manifest from what has been said.
          Therefore the Spanish messengers of our kings have inflicted the greatest 
          injuries on King Inca and other kings,
          and they have greatly disturbed by entering those lands or kingdoms and 
          their places to search out or inquire about treasures or other precious 
          things without their permission,
          especially against their will,
          committing execrable violence,
          thefts and rapine.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e484">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Thirdly,
          the corollary is proven:
          Our kings of the Spains are obliged by necessity of justice and salvation 
          to avoid all things that can irritate or scandalize the aforesaid 
          inhabitants,
          disturb them,
          and impede or retard them from receiving the faith,
          and every irregularity,
          injustice,
          scandal or other undue work and not done according to reason or against 
          the order of law,
          which is of itself apt to generate in such infidels a sinister or perverse 
          opinion about the faith or Christian religion etc.,
          as was proven at length in the 5th consideration.
          But to enter into those lands and kingdoms and to inquire or search for 
          treasures and other precious things and to take them without permission 
          and good pleasure of the kings and lords would be against the order of law,
          unjust,
          scandalous,
          disorderly,
          disturbing,
          irritating,
          defamatory of the Catholic faith,
          and impeding that infidels might be converted,
          and productive of sinister and perverse opinion about the Christian faith 
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e575">
          Therefore our kings are bound by necessity of justice and salvation to 
          avoid such things.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e580">
          Therefore it is no less illicit for our kings to order or procure those 
          things than for other rulers of the world,
          and thus the same as before.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e591">
          And this is understood even if such peoples and nations had received the 
          faith and been initiated in the sacraments,
          provided they had not given free consent by handing over to our kings the 
          supreme principate of that world,
          since before their consent our kings have no power to enter by themselves 
          or through their agents into that world,
          even if those peoples meanwhile should be converted to Christ by receiving 
          the sacrament of faith.
          And all these things are sufficiently clear from the foregoing.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e617">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Fourthly,
          finally the corollary is proven,
          or the things proven are confirmed:
          first because our kings have no voluntary subject in that whole world from 
          among the natives.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e629">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Secondly because all their power is in habit,
          indeed not yet fully in habit.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e638">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Thirdly because they are in that state in which 
          they were when the letters of the aforesaid institution of the Roman 
          Apostolic See were issued.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e648">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Fourthly because the papal institution now sleeps 
          and is suspended or remains in pendency.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e662">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Fifthly because the Spaniards viciously and 
          improperly,
          and therefore in no way validly,
          delivered to our kings the usurped possession of that world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e545-d1e672">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Sixthly,
          finally,
          because all things that from the beginning have been done by the Spaniards 
          throughout that whole world up to this very day inclusive have lacked 
          force,
          and thus have remained entirely void.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>