<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 15</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 15</title>
          <date when="2025-11-13">November 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="42-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Hd1e97">Section 15</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#B" n="42-r"/>
          § 15
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e106">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Part 8
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e114">
          In the meantime,
          for the protection or defense of the preachers of the faith and the ambassadors of our kings:
          there should be made some tower or house that is somewhat fortified under the pretext of some necessity
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e123">
          whose construction will be very easy to accomplish:
          since it is not necessary to make it from polished and squared stones:
          but it is sufficient for it to be either earthen or wooden because of the weakness 
          and scarcity of weapons of the natives.
          Nevertheless it would be better to construct it from earth with a wooden roof 
          covered with tiles because of the danger of combustion.
          For to do this would pertain to the prudence of the leader of the ambassadors of our kings 
          so that future dangers and inconveniences may be prevented:
          and therefore it is better to forestall in advance:
          than after the outcome etc.
          As we said above.
          For one should not immediately trust foreign and unknown nations:
          although they may display signs of love,
          peace and courtesy.
          Although concerning our Indian peoples,
          before they knew us from our works,
          there was nothing at all for us to fear from them:
          since they knew how to carry nothing feigned,
          nothing deceitful toward us inwardly or outwardly:
          but with simple heart,
          with great admiration,
          joy and eagerness,
          with a certain paternal humanity,
          wonderful hospitality,
          with every kind of benefits they received us and treated us etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e167">
          Part 9
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e172">
          Exhortation by gentle and sweet word etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e179">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Namely,
          that in some suitable place they may gather together to hear
          <pb ed="#B" n="42-v"/>
          those things which are of the faith etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e188">
          This part is sufficiently evident from the proof of the preceding matters,
          especially those (namely) humble greeting and address:
          and exemplary conduct and timely notification,
          quiet,
          gentle,
          friendly,
          most modest and conciliatory of the spirits of the hearers,
          patient etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e206">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          By a similar consideration the subsequent part is covered (namely) 
          the preaching of the faith,
          distinct,
          discreet and regular according to the form established by Christ:
          so that the desired effect (that is) 
          the conversion of those souls with divine help may follow through their entry into the most holy Catholic Church,
          voluntarily having received the sacrament of holy baptism.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e226">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Part 10
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e234">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Information,
          by the same heralds of the faith,
          concerning the title of our kings etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e243">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          That this information concerning the title is necessary is proved
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e250">
          first thus:
          one alleging a singular title according to the laws must prove it even if he is a son,
          since there is a presumption in favor of the universal heir 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e257">l. siue possidetis</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e261">Baldus there C. de probationibus</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e259">
          But on behalf of our kings is alleged a singular title,
          foreign,
          new and remarkable as regards those peoples.
          Those peoples indeed and their kings presume,
          indeed they know and we know that they are the true lords and just possessors of that world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e272">
          Therefore it is necessary that the title which our kings claim to have to the dominion 
          or jurisdiction of those lands be proved to them on behalf of our kings:
          and they should be fully taught concerning the title.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e279">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The consequence is clear with the Major premise.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e288">
          The Minor is proved:
          because any possessor is presumed to believe himself owner 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e297">Cynus in l. cum alienum C. de lega</ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e305">
            Bartholus in l. 1. si de momem. posse fue. appel. 1 colu. verb. extra no.
          </ref> 
          For a possessor is held as owner if he possesses as owner 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e311">
            gloss, Bartholus and the doctors in l. quidam in fine ff. de conditionibus institutionum
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e306">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly it is proved thus:
          the burden of proof lies on him who asserts or claims 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e312" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e2052-Dd1e342">
            l. actor C. de probationibus
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e317">l. ei qui ff. eo titulo</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e319" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e701-Dd1e137">
            l. qui accusare C. de 
            <pb ed="#B" n="43-r"/>
            edendo
          </ref>
          Likewise the agent and whoever alleges or acts must prove what he alleges 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e339">d. l. actor</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e341">Cynus, Bartholus and Baldus there</ref> 
          which is true unless he has a presumption 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e345">prose l. ei incumbit</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e347">
            Bartholus there ff. de probationibus,
            especially a special one l. cum indebito eo titulo.
          </ref> 
          Likewise if the plaintiff is not in quasi-possession of the right which he asserts 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e355">l. circa eum per Bartholum eo titulo.</ref> 
          Likewise it is true even if the defendant has violent possession. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e362">d. l. circa eum</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e364">l. vis eius</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e366">Baldus there in the words</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Qd1e330">I ask here whether the agent</quote> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e373">C. de probationibus.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e333">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But our kings in this business do not have a presumption in their favor with respect to those peoples,
          nor are they in quasi-possession of the right which they assert themselves to have:
          Those peoples however and the whole world are not in violent possession 
          but in proper,
          due,
          true,
          natural and peaceful possession.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e347">
          Therefore the burden of proving what they assert lies upon our kings.
          And consequently they ought to teach concerning the title 
          to prove and establish their claim.
          The consequence is clear.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e356">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Moreover it is a general maxim that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Qd1e363">
            whoever seeks dominion in any thing: 
            it is necessary that he prove it
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e410">
            C. de rei vendi. doce et de alienatione iudicii l. 1
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e412">
            Innocent in C. inter quatuor de maioritate et obedientia.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e370">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Again,
          thirdly thus:
          when someone seeks some debt with the debtor denying it,
          proof lies upon the one seeking.
          Particularly when the claim is not founded by the adversary:
          because a negative should not be proved by the one denying 
          but by the adversary in the said case,
          namely when his claim is not founded 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e432">Baldus in l. si ex cantione 2 columna</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e390">
          But our kings if they should seek a debt,
          namely obedience and subjection from those peoples of the Indian world:
          and they themselves deny it as they rightly can since they are free,
          as is evident from what has been said and will be more clearly evident below,
          nor do our kings have their claim founded,
          but those peoples do.
          Therefore the negative should be proved by our kings.
          But this means teaching concerning the title.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e408">
          Therefore our kings are bound to teach and give proof to such peoples 
          concerning the title which they claim to have to the universal dominion 
          and sovereignty of that world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e417">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Fourthly it is proved by argument from the greater:
          for if one having possession when he has contrary right is compelled to show title,
          therefore much 
          <pb ed="#B" n="43-v"/>
          better and more forcefully one who is known to have had hitherto neither right nor possession.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e434">
          For wherever right resists someone wishing to claim some thing for himself,
          especially to the prejudice of another:
          it is necessary to show and teach concerning the title,
          as in one wishing to prescribe,
          as is the case in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e493">c. 1, de prescriptione lib. 6</ref> 
          and this even if he has possession of the thing without which prescription cannot occur 
          de prescriptione 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e498">c. illud 16 q. § potest</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e505">regula sine possessione lib. 6</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e449">
          To our purpose a text sufficiently fitting and notable is found in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e513">C. cum persone de priuilegiis lib. 6</ref> 
          where 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Qd1e455">
            subjects of a bishop if they say that they are exempt from the bishop 
            because of the resistance of right which they have against themselves:
            it is necessary before all else to show the title of their exemption,
            and if they do not show it and they try to prove prescription,
            with the proof of prescription preceding:
            since by common law the ordinaries,
            their claim being thus founded,
            can use their jurisdiction freely over them 
            until they have given full proof concerning the prescription,
            although those are in possession of the exemption.
            From which that text infers according to some 
            that during a pending suit that possessor against whom common law works 
            can be disturbed and violently expelled,
            just like one who possesses by force or stealth or by precarious right
          </quote> 
          Thus says Ancharanus there in the 11th notable point.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e485">
          Therefore someone is compelled to show by what title he possesses 
          or seeks some thing when it is contrary to common law:
          otherwise he will be able to be deprived of it if he possesses,
          or his petition repudiated if he seeks to possess.
          As is evident from the aforesaid,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e553">
            Baldus holds in l. 2, 2 columna C. quomodo et quando iudi.
          </ref> 
          saying that one who claims the title of his possession:
          whom 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e561">
            Alvarotus reports and follows in c. 1 in prin. de controuertis inuestigandum
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e502">
          If therefore someone existing in possession of a thing,
          when he has law against himself,
          is compelled to show title,
          it follows by stronger reason that our Kings of Spain are bound to show the title 
          by which they would be supported in seeking from those peoples and nations 
          to be received as Lords and thus obedience etc.,
          since they are known to have had hitherto neither possession nor property 
          nor any right in and to those kingdoms and peoples:
          and consequently all common law,
          natural,
          human and 
          <pb ed="#B" n="44-r"/>
          divine resists them.
          Which nevertheless entirely favors and supports the inhabitants and dwellers of that world 
          who justly possess those things.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e528">
          For it is greater to have possession of a thing 
          and to have legitimately acquired right:
          than merely to claim title to a thing in another's property.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e535">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          To the purpose is what Panormitanus says:
          after 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e608">
            Innocent in c. post electionem de concessione prebende
          </ref> 
          that against one acting in a possessory manner,
          exception is made of defect of power in the one conferring or in the one electing.
          And such exception is admitted as in c. cum olim de causa possessionis et proprietatis.
          For possession should not be given to anyone which he never had:
          unless his legitimate title is first established 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-Rd1e624">l. fi. C. de edicto diui adriani tollendo</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e556">
          Therefore our kings never had possession or property of that world 
          before that world was discovered.
          Likewise all those peoples with their lords and kings can by the best right 
          make exception of defect of power in the Supreme Pontiff that he might have handed over 
          to the dominion and jurisdiction and servitude of another foreign king:
          great Kings and peoples and nations and free kingdoms possessing freedom 
          by the law of nature and of nations.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e255-d1e574">
          Whence it is evident:
          that our kings are bound to teach those nations concerning the title which they put forward 
          so that the natural and juridical order may be preserved,
          as is said in the conclusion.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>