<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 1</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
            <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
            <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 1</title>
          <date when="2025-11-10">November 10, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a critical edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-10" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-Hd1e97">Section 1</head>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e99">
          ยง. 1
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e106">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> For the response to this question, it must first be presupposed 
          that there was a custom among the ancients, not only among the nations who were 
          lacking knowledge of the true God, but also among the faithful worshippers of the true God himself: 
          Kings and nobles would place whatever precious things they had in life 
          with themselves after death in their tombs. And the greater and richer 
          the things that were placed in their tombs, the more they excelled others in power 
          and were wealthier in riches. For through this 
          their glory and magnificence were rendered more illustrious in the memory 
          of men in future ages.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e130">
          This is clear from that passage in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-Rxj2as3">Job 3</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-Qaj822a">
            As those digging for treasure, 
            they rejoice vehemently when they have found a tomb
          </quote>. 
          And in <ref>Baruch chapter 6</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-Qd1e138">
            Or as to a tomb with a dead man brought in: so the priests guard 
            the doors with locks and bars lest they be despoiled by thieves
          </quote> 
          (namely, the treasures) stored there with the dead. 
          Thus the gloss says: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-Qd1e149">
            In ancient times (it says) precious things were placed in the tombs of the powerful, 
            on account of which they were shut strongly and with diligence lest 
            they be extracted by thieves
          </quote>, 
          thus far that passage. 
          <ref>
            Saint Thomas says the same 
            on Job in the cited place
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e161">
          Likewise it appears from the example of the magnificent King 
          Solomon who buried his father David in Jerusalem 
          most fittingly with other things and ceremonies which are customarily 
          administered around funerals. And he stored many riches with him. 
          For he had made for him an honorable tomb around which 
          he established seven treasury chambers which he filled with gold and 
          precious stones. The magnitude of these riches is 
          manifestly shown through those things which were afterwards extracted from David's tomb. 
          For after a time of thirteen hundred years, 
          Hyrcanus the high priest, while the city of Jerusalem was being besieged 
          by King Antiochus, wishing to give him money so that 
          he would withdraw from the siege and take away his army, not 
          having the means to fulfill this, opened one chamber of David's 
          tomb and, having taken from there three thousand talents, 
          gave part to Antiochus and thus removed the anxiety of the siege.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e199">
          Now of talents, as the <name>Master</name> says in the histories, 
          there were three kinds, namely the least, the greater, and the greatest. 
          For the least was fifty pounds in weight; the greater seventy pounds; 
          but the greatest one hundred twenty pounds. Moreover, each 
          pound was worth fifty gold pieces. Whence it is clear that even if each 
          of the talents were of the least kind, still three thousand talents amounted 
          to a great sum of gold pieces. Rather, if they were of 
          the greatest kind, as seems reasonable...<!-- some kind of confusion here -->
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e219">
          After these things, however, much 
          time having passed, again King Herod, 
          hearing that Hyrcanus the king before him had opened the tomb of David and 
          found three thousand talents, believing much 
          more was deposited and would suffice for all his expenses, 
          opening the tomb entered by night since he did not wish 
          the city to know of this. Therefore taking only his most faithful friends, 
          he did not find the deposited money as Hyrcanus had, but 
          he took ornaments and many golden vessels. But while he applied all diligence 
          and made more careful investigation and wished to enter further 
          to the tombs in which the bodies of David and Solomon were 
          placed, two of his guards were consumed by flames 
          coming from within. 
          Then he, terrified with fear, went out. 
          Never afterwards was there anyone who could find the other chambers, 
          although great treasures in the tomb of David and Solomon 
          are believed to exist even to this day. For it was done by magic <!-- check this word --> so that it would not 
          be permitted to anyone either to find or, if they found, to be able 
          to take anything from there. All these things <ref>Josephus relates in book 7 chapter 16</ref> and <ref>book 13 chapter 18</ref> 
          and <ref>book 16 chapter 7 of the Jewish Antiquities.</ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e269">
          Moved by the fame of these things, 
          the Turk named Suleiman in our times, 
          namely around the year of our Lord 1520, when he captured Jerusalem, 
          sought the treasures in David's tomb with great diligence, but he was never 
          able to find them, as is read in the history of the Turks. 
          The reason for this frustration is that such chambers were 
          hidden under the earth in a <unclear>mechanical</unclear> way, that is, by <unclear>magic</unclear>, so that 
          to those entering the monument they could in no way be 
          manifest, as Josephus says.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e291">
          It is clear therefore that to store treasures 
          and other precious things with themselves in their tombs 
          was a thing licit and customary among the ancients, whether faithful 
          or unfaithful, common and general. And the reason for this can be assigned 
          as follows: the natural inclination which is in all 
          men insofar as they are rational, that due honor be preserved 
          to human nature above other animals, namely that the human body 
          be buried (that is) that it have this honor, because 
          just as among all animals man alone is a sacred 
          and divine animal, so to him alone is this honor granted that his corpse 
          be buried lest it be torn apart by birds and other animals, while 
          the corpses of others remain unburied. Whence the <ref>Philosopher in Rhetoric I</ref> 
          places burial among the other parts of honor.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e322">
          Moreover, there is a certain honorable good for the dead insofar as they live 
          in the memories of men, that their bodies be buried. 
          For all think there is nothing by which we do greater injury 
          to the dead than if we drag his body through the earth 
          and give it to dogs and beasts to devour. 
          Thus it is gathered from 
          <ref>
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-Nd1e338">Aristotle</name> in Ethics 5
          </ref> when he speaks of one who kills himself, 
            whether he does injustice to himself. 
            And he responds that no, but to the city. 
            And therefore the city or community inflicts punishment on him, namely 
            dishonor concerning the body, <!-- translation triage here -->
            namely that it causes the corpse to be
            dragged through the earth or that it remain unburied. 
            Therefore it must be said that a certain evil comes 
            to the dead from the fact that they are not buried. For they are considered 
            unhappy who lack burial. On the contrary, however, good comes to 
            the dead from the fact that they are buried honorably. Thus it is clear in <ref>Isaiah 11</ref> where 
            many honorable things are said about Moses and afterwards it is added about 
            the honor of his tomb: his tomb will be glorious. And 
            yet if glory and honor of the tomb did not pertain to Christ, 
            nothing would be said prophetically about this. 
            Therefore the glory of the tomb pertained to Christ. 
            Therefore some good happens to the dead if their bodies 
            are committed to burial, insofar as they have being 
            and a way of living in the opinions of men. 
            From this therefore there arose among all nations 
            this natural conception: that the bodies of the 
            deceased should be buried or cremated. 
            Those who decreed cremation preserved the ashes 
            and kept them in tombs or in some 
            distinguished and honorable and eminent place. Just as the ashes 
            of <name>Julius Caesar</name> to this day in Rome upon a certain huge stone 
            of pyramidal shape which is called a needle behind the church of Saint 
            Peter are said to remain. For the ancients judged, and also 
            the moderns, it to be shameful and injurious that human bodies 
            should remain unburied. And on account of this we see men solicitous in life 
            about constructing tombs and funeral rites and other things pertaining 
            to them. And the more powerful and wealthy they are in riches, 
            the more honorable, beautiful, and expensive they prepare 
            tombs for themselves. Whence one and the same principal thing which most 
            brings honor to the deceased and so that their names may possess 
            possible immortality among posterity, in that way 
            by which they have being and live in the memories of men, 
            seems to be the tomb, especially if it has been built from precious material and very 
            expensively and with subtle and optimal workmanship, adorned 
            moreover with most beautiful and precious other fitting things, and far 
            more especially if with human corpses great wealth and precious treasures 
            are placed in tombs.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-d1e426">
          But because among kings 
          and the powerful in the world such magnitude 
          and opulence of riches is easily found, by this the more their glory, power, and royal 
          excellence grew and increased and 
          was made known to future ages: the more treasures and riches of gold and silver and 
          precious stones 
          and other diverse furnishings of great value 
          they ordered to be stored with themselves in their tombs or to be buried with them.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>