<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 2</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 2</title>
          <date when="2025-11-10">November 11, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
              >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex
            Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-10" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"> </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e71-Hd1e97">Section 2</head>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e100"> §. 2 </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e109">
          From the preceding we can draw three conclusions. 
          The first is that those who wish to bury their riches or treasures with themselves or with their own
          bodies intend a great interest, namely: honors, praise, and glory, which are the effects
          of honor and parts of happiness according to the <ref>Philosopher in Rhetoric I</ref>, and through
          these to live perpetually in the opinions of men. And they hope to achieve this if their
          status, riches, opulence, sublime works, and magnificence, such as they were, should be
          made known to posterity. </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e130"> For praise is an encomium celebrated by the mouth of
          another, or praise is discourse elucidating the magnitude of virtue according to Saint
          Thomas on the Psalms, and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e140">
            the Philosopher in Rhetoric I
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e145">
            praise is speech showing the magnitude of virtue
          </quote>. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e151"> 
          But glory is frequent fame about someone with praise
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e157">
            Cicero in his Rhetoric
          </ref>. 
          And as he
          himself says in his oration for 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e161">M. Marcellus</name>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e164">
            It is the illustrious and promulgated fame of merits, 
            either toward one's citizens or toward one's country or toward the whole human
            race
          </quote>. 
          Or according to Augustine: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e169">
            it is the judgment of men thinking well about people
          </quote>. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e176">
          The proposition is proved first because the desire for
          praise, honor, and glory is naturally in men, whence it is frequent and daily, so that
          there is no one who does not desire it. 
          Indeed 
          <ref><name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e184">Valerius</name> says in book 8</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e186">
            no one is so humble and of such abject condition 
            whom the sweetness of glory does not soften and
            touch
          </quote>. 
          And <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e194">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e195">Cicero</name> in the Tusculans
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e200">
            honor nourishes the arts
            and we are all inflamed to the pursuit of glory and praise
          </quote>; and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e205">in De Officiis I
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e207">
            one will scarcely find anyone who, when labors and dangers
            are added, does not desire as if a reward for things done, beyond this glory and
            praise
          </quote>. 
          And in <ref>his book of orations</ref> he says there is nothing in life to be
          greatly sought except praise and honor. 
          But in pursuing it, all tortures of the body, all
          dangers of death and exile should be considered of little importance. 
          Indeed because, as
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e223">
            Gregory says in book 6 chapter 209 of the Register</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e225">
            just as fire blown by wind becomes greater, 
            so the endeavors of good minds profit by commendation
          </quote>. 
          Hence the emperors and ancient kings, 
          considering this inclination or condition of mortals, 
          in order to encourage virtuous citizens 
          to undertake labors especially for the republic 
          and to act strenuously in all things according to virtue, 
          acted in three ways according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e246">Albert the Great on Ethics I</ref>. 
          And here they showed by rewarding the well-deserving with that praise, 
          namely that they would be displayed in glory so that they might receive titles of praise, 
          and they made an eternal memorial of them sitting upon snow-white horses 
          (as <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e257">Titus Livius</name> says), 
          which belonged to the king's chair, surrounded everywhere by a
          herald crying with public voice and setting forth their virtues and the works of their
          virtues by which they had merited this. 
          And this does not differ much from what King Ahasuerus did concerning 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e268">Mordecai</name> whom he
          ordered to ascend a horse that belonged to the king's chair, 
          dressed in the king's garments, 
          and received the royal crown and to be led through the city square with 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e277">Haman</name> crying out: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e279">Thus shall it be done to the man 
            whom the king desires to honor
          </quote>. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e282">Esther 6.</ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e285">
          And secondly, they also had titles inscribed in the temple
          and hall, so that even when they were not present, their virtue might be known. </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e294"> 
          Thirdly, they also received memorials in statues and
          arches, so that even after their death that virtue might not be destroyed by oblivion. On
          account of which victors are still found depicted with round shields tied to the back of
          the head, so that on the shield it might be seen how strenuously they fought for the
          republic. For a shield is cut where it receives the blows of the enemy, and therefore a
          soldier protected by a shield crowned signifies that he strenuously withstood the assaults
          and blows of enemies. Hence it is that in temples the heads of gods and saints are painted
          in circular form in the manner of a shield <!-- transl triage --> fitted to the back of the head. 
          Therefore such praises are rewards of virtue, etc. Thus Albert. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e327"> 
          Behold how greatly the ancients valued honor, praise, and
          glory, not only for the praise of those present, 
          but rather they intended that their virtue, opulence, greatness of status, 
          and works strenuously done by them might be
          established for future ages, so that thus they might live, 
          as was possible, eternally.
          And this was a great interest to them.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e344">
          Therefore, since, <!-- translation triage --> through the placing of those treasures in tombs, 
          they intended praise, honor, and glory, 
          to which men are naturally inclined, by
          which they strove to acquire a great interest. </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e355"> 
          Secondly, the proposition is proved: the desire for living
          forever is naturally in all mortals, as is clear in <ref>Ethics X</ref>, the reason for which can be
          assigned because, according to the same <ref>Philosopher in De Anima II</ref>, all created things
          according to the nature and condition of each desire to participate in divine being, and
          for its sake they do whatever they do according to nature. And yet since they had learned
          from experience that it would be impossible to live forever in that mode of living which
          is somewhat similar to the eternal, namely in the memory and opinion of men, they were
          content. And therefore in this mortal life they worked certain outstanding things
          according to the inclination, strength, power, or riches of each, so that they might
          provide material to coming men (when they themselves had been removed by death) for
          thinking well of them, revering them, and praising and exalting them, so that thus they
          might live in a certain way eternally. Therefore through the fact that most noble kings
          and powerful men ordered such treasures to be stored with them in their tombs, they strove
          to claim for themselves honor, good opinion, fame, praise, and glory, and thus a great
          interest.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e400"> 
          Moreover, among other things which the ancients were
          accustomed to care for in order to achieve perpetual memory of men, praise, etc., through
          death (which custom endures to this day), this was one and not less principal: namely that
          arms or insignia, which were substituted in place of images, were placed in temples or in
          tombs, walls, or arches and other solemn buildings, so that they might be manifest to all
          and henceforth they might have knowledge of whose or of whom they had been and might begin
          to revere them. This is touched upon in 
          <ref>
            l. 1, §. casum, ff. de postulando
          </ref>. 
          This also appears 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e423">
            in 1 Maccabees chapter 13
          </ref> where it is
          read of Simon Maccabee that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e428">
            he built a tomb for his father and his brothers, 
            a building high to see, 
            of polished stone behind and before
          </quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e436">
          And he set up seven pyramids, 
          one opposite another, 
          for father and mother and four brothers, 
          and around these he placed great columns, 
          and upon the columns arms for eternal memory.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e448"> 
          And next to the arms, 
          sculpted ships which would be seen by
          men sailing the sea. 
          <!-- translation triage -->
          Thus far that passage. 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e454">1 Kings 13</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e456">
            the Philistines placed the arms of the
            slain Saul in the temple of Ashtaroth, 
            but his body they hung on the wall of Beth-shan
          </quote>. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e464"> 
          Finally in <ref>Song of Songs 4</ref>, 
          Solomon mentions that King
          David his father had made a tower from which 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e472">
            hung a thousand shields, 
            all the armor of the strong
          </quote>,
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          which perhaps were the insignia 
          and arms of a thousand nobles,
          both of parents and of friends or subjects to him, 
          which he placed on a thousand shields
          hanging from the said tower.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e483">
          <ref>Pliny also in book 35 chapter 3</ref> 
          relates that certain ancient Romans, 
          leaving shields, 
          arms or bucklers for the perpetual memory of their own, 
          did the same. 
          For <name>Appius Claudius</name>, 
          who was consul with <name>Servilius</name>, 
          first established the custom of privately 
          dedicating shields of his family 
          in a sacred or public place. 
          For he placed in the temple of Bellona his ancestors, 
          and it pleased him that they be viewed on high 
          and that the titles of honors be read.
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          A beautiful thing indeed if a crowd of
          children with small images, 
          or some offspring equally displayed. 
          Such shields everyone
          views with joy and favor.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e508">
          After him 
          <name>Marcus Aemilius</name>, 
          colleague in the consulship of
          <name>Q. Lutatius</name>, 
          placed them not only in the Aemilian basilica 
          but also in his own home. 
          By <name>Marcius's</name> example, 
          the Carthaginians also made shields 
          and images of gold 
          and carried them with them in camps, etc. 
          Thus Pliny. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e521"> 
          And it should be known that in ancient times 
          it was the custom at Rome that images of ancestors 
          be carried in funerals and in tombs 
          to show gentility, that is, genealogy, 
          and in the atria there were images that would be viewed,
          expressed faces were arranged in individual shrines 
          so that there might be images that
          would accompany family funerals. 
          Others were affixed at doors and around the threshold,
          images of great souls with the spoils of enemies attached, 
          which not even a buyer would be permitted to break, 
          and which even when masters changed were ornaments of the house
          according to the <ref>same Pliny in the book quoted above, chapter 2</ref>. 
          Therefore in place of images arms or insignia 
          were substituted (as we said), 
          and <name>Budaeus</name> thinks that later times
          had family insignia instead of images, 
          which are commonly called arms, 
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          which themselves also at first, as is likely, 
          were rewards of virtue and honors of deeds excellently done.
          If you wish to see more of these to satiety, read 
          <ref>
            <name>Casaneus</name> 
            in the first part, 
            conclusion 10, 
            in the Catalogue of the Glory of the World
          </ref>. 
          It is clear therefore that among the ancients, 
          just as is done now among the moderns, 
          for the sake of honor and praise and good opinion and fame, 
          either of their own persons 
          or of their ancestors 
          or of the antiquity of the origin of their family or gentility and nobility, 
          there was great care and the highest study 
          in the judgment of perpetual memory among men.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e574">
          What, I ask, do we now see also among Catholics, 
          especially noble men indeed powerful and great in riches, 
          kings and magnates, except to place banners, insignia, shields and arms 
          either golden or gilded or silver or iron 
          in chapels at churches erected by themselves 
          with great study and at great expense; 
          moreover to raise tombs or mounds in them as high as they can; 
          and also to adorn them with silk or gold-woven coverings 
          and many such kinds of precious furnishings. 
          And this indeed for no other reason 
          than for the sake of honor and perpetual fame. 
          But because burying treasures and precious furnishings 
          with the bodies of lords manifested 
          their glory, nobility, riches, excellence of status and eminence, 
          thence a motive and material was given to those
          seeing and hearing to revere them, 
          value them greatly, 
          and also to praise and magnify them, 
          and all other things looking to honor and glory. 
          Therefore those who ordered their
          riches and treasures to be placed with them in their tombs 
          intended a great interest,
          namely perpetual honor and things looking to honor.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-d1e631"> 
          For the interest of honor is greater than any other interest. 
          For as 
          <ref>Cicero says in De Amicitia</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e638">
            Where will you find someone 
            who would place the honor of a friend before his own?
          </quote>. 
          And 
          <ref>Aristotle in the Economics</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Qd1e642">
            Someone bears it much
            more grievously if he is deprived of his honor 
            than if his goods are taken from him
          </quote>. 
          And such earthly honors are desired more than heavenly ones. 
          <ref>
            De renuntiatione. C. nisi cum pridem § pro graui
          </ref>.
          And for the sake of sustaining honor,
          action must also be brought for injuries, 
          as 
          <ref>
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e657">Baldus</name> 
            says in L. observare § antequam ff. de officio proconsulis
          </ref>. 
          Indeed, 
          for the protection and defense of one's own honor, 
          a duel and war can be initiated by law
          against those injuring or detracting from our honor. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e670">
            Baldus in cap. circa principium 
            et columna de pace tenenda. in de feudis
          </ref> 
          because no one is bound to suffer injury 
          or small consideration of his own honor 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e678">
            argumentum ff. de postulando in principio
          </ref>. 
          Indeed, 
          he is cruel who neglects his own reputation. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e682">
            c. nolo 12 q. 122
          </ref>. 
          Hence it is said that 
          the causes of life and honor are equated 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e687">
            l. Iusta, ff. de manumissionibus
          </ref>. 
          And so someone can kill an assailant in defense of his honor 
          just as for the defense of his person, 
          as per the doctors in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e699">
            l. 1. Codex, Unde ui.
          </ref> 
          and through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e702">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e703">Jason</name> 
            in l. vt vim ff de Iustitia et iure
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e706">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e707">Petrus Gerardus</name> 
            in his Singula singulum 33
          </ref>.
          Whence the text in 
          <ref>
            l. miles, § socer de adulteriis
          </ref>: 
          <!-- quote? --> 
          It is shameful to leave one's honor unavenged. 
          For honor cannot be estimated by monetary price, 
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e719">
            Baldus says in the chapter 
            De vita et honestate
            clericorum
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e721">
            the chapter ex tenore column
            2 de appellationibus
          </ref>. 
          And what is more, 
          honor brings utility 
          <ref>
            l. si longius, at the end, ff, de iudiciis
          </ref>, 
          and wherever there is a question of honor, 
          it is said to be an
          arduous cause in 
          <ref>
            l. si inimicitie at the end ff de his quibus ut indignis
          </ref>. 
          Thence moreover
          it is that what cannot be done without honor being preserved cannot be done, 
          thus the text has in 
          <ref>
            l. in eadem causa ff ex quibus causis maiores
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Rd1e741">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e84-Nd1e742">Gerardus</name> 
            notes in Singula, singulum.
          </ref>
          And thus concerning the first proposition.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>