<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 20</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 20</title>
          <date when="2025-11-15">November 15, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-15" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="53-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Hd1e97">Section 20</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e99">
          § 20
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e111">aforesaid can be confirmed l. per hoc</ref> 
          because the Book of Deuteronomy,
          in which that ordinance is found:
          is interpreted as the second law according to Jerome and Isidore and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e117">
            Innocent III in c. per venerabilem extra qui filii sint legitimi
          </ref>.
          And it is a figure of the new law,
          since according to the Apostle all things happened in figure 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e125">1 Corinthians 10</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e119">
          Therefore what is said there must be adapted,
          especially what pertains to moral understanding and to regulating the acts of men 
          which are to be done in the time of grace.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e128">
          Since therefore the intervention of the consent and approval of a free people 
          for the establishment of a new prince is natural or of natural law 
          and thus moral for regulating the acts of men:
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e138">
          It follows that it ought thus to be observed in the time of grace:
          and consequently in our case the consent of those peoples and their kings themselves 
          must necessarily be had for receiving our king,
          indeed far more strongly.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e147">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise secondly another confirmation can be added by argument from ecclesiastical 
          to secular institutions,
          which is a good argument because Jerome uses it in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e165">d. c. licet 8 q. 1</ref> 
          and in many other places the Church has used it.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e157">
          But in ecclesiastical institutions the consent and approval of the people is required.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e167">
          Therefore it ought to be so in secular matters.
          Indeed far more,
          especially as regards those peoples who,
          as we suppose,
          are either still infidels or very recent,
          like delicate little plants in the faith,
          to whom rather one should be gentle:
          than they should be exasperated,
          as for instance neophytes 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e188">35 q. 2 et 3 c. quedam lex</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e178">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The Minor is sufficiently evident in the chapter in nomine domini 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e185">23 dist.</ref> 
          where Pope Leo says: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Qd1e187" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d23-d1e124@26-43">
            No reason permits that those be held among bishops who have not been elected by clerics 
            nor sought by the people
          </quote>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e196">d. c. plebs, 63 dist.</ref> 
          with what follows,
          where the people are summoned not indeed to choose but to consent to the election of a prelate,
          by that rule of law: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Qd1e203">
            What touches all must be approved by all
          </quote> 
          with its concordances. lib. 6 and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e205">gloss in c. 1, 62 dist.</ref> 
          note in a contrary sense that if the people do not wish to consent 
          <pb ed="#B" n="53-v"/>
          to the election made by the college:
          the election can be annulled:
          indeed even if they object without reasonable cause and do not wish to consent,
          the election ought to be annulled if scandal would be generated in the people,
          from which the said glosses 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e237">Panormitanus notes particularly in c. 1, de electione</ref> 
          saying:
          that with scandal of the people no one ought to be placed in office,
          even with a legitimate election intervening.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e226">
          For which 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e246">c. cum teneamur de prebendis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e249">c. nisi cum pridem de renuntiatione</ref> 
          apply very well.
          And see the singular 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e251">statement of Innocent there</ref> 
          where he says that,
          if the people persecute a bishop or prelate already instituted,
          nor can they be restrained from such persecution,
          so that the people may be quiet and the church not be disturbed,
          the prelate ought to withdraw or be removed by a superior,
          with good exchange assigned elsewhere.
          Which is singularly to be noted according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e267">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Nd1e243">Panormitanus</name> 
            it applies c. si forte 63
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e272">c. nullus inuitus</ref> 
          a bishop is not to be given:
          if they have just cause of contradiction.
          And it is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e247" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d23-d1e185">
            c. illud 23 dist.
          </ref> 
          even if he is given by the Pope 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e250" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d22-d1e139">
            22 dist. c. sacrosancta
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e257">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          If therefore a bishop ought not to be given to unwilling Christian peoples,
          lest the unwilling people despise or hate a bishop not desired,
          far less should a temporal ruler or king be given to a free,
          foreign,
          gentile and infidel people,
          having their own and natural kings,
          not recognizing a superior,
          so unknown to them,
          suspect as being of another race or almost nation,
          and with great,
          most dangerous and most certain and unquenchable scandal,
          not of one people only,
          but truly also of an infinite number of peoples,
          and of diverse nations.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e290">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And that the argument proceeds by place from the greater is evident,
          because Christian peoples or the Christian populace are more obligated to undergo a bishop 
          given or instituted by the Pope and exhibited or proposed to the people,
          or elected by clerics,
          than free peoples of gentiles or infidels:
          or even of recently converted peoples to suffer or accept a temporal king or ruler 
          of another race and foreign people,
          since in all ways they are outside the doors of the Church:
          or if some have already been converted,
          nevertheless they have their own and natural princes,
          free,
          recognizing no superior,
          on account of which they can justly and by the authority of the law of nature 
          oppose any other institution concerning 
          <pb ed="#B" n="54-r"/>
          another superior,
          since they certainly have just cause of contradicting.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e324">
          If to those,
          namely to old Christians,
          a bishop ought not to be given even by the Pope against their will:
          much less to infidels of whom we speak,
          or to recently converted,
          should a foreign King be given without their free consent and voluntary acceptance.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e335">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Thirdly the aforesaid are confirmed by using also the same argument from the lesser thus:
          The Church now in modern times (as it has used from old) 
          in the establishment of the supreme prince in any part of the Christian people:
          does not take away but permits and confirms the consent of the people,
          or of those to whom by right or custom it belongs to elect and accept him of their own accord.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e352">
          Therefore neither ought it to be taken away from those infidels and similar peoples,
          or even from those recently converted from them etc.
          The consequence is evident from what was said a little above.
          The antecedent is proved:
          because the Church in God's place approves and confirms the election which Christian peoples make 
          of a ruler or supreme prince,
          as appears in the empire and in the city of Venice and others who have the power 
          to elect their ruler by right or custom as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e370">93 dist. c. legimus</ref> 
          there 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Qd1e374" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d93-d1e49y@51-55">
            how if the army makes an emperor.
          </quote> 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e377" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t6-d1e119">
            extra de electione c. 1
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e383" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t6-Dd1e603@5-5">
            c. venerabilem
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e386" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c8q1-d1e347">
            8, q. 1, c. licet
          </ref>.
          Nor is succession to successors taken away as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e391" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t34-Dd1e184@7-7">
            c. licet, de voto
          </ref> 
          with what is noted there.
          Where the kingdom is transferred by succession.
          Nor is the specially expressed judgment of the Pope required for this even within the Church:
          but it suffices that he tacitly consent to him who is worthy to rule 
          and is a zealot of the faith and obedient to the holy Roman Church,
          argument 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e403">c. Adrianus el. 2 63 dist.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e410">96 dist. c. quis dubitet</ref>.
          It applies that Baldus says in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e414">d. c. venerabilem de electione 1 columna</ref> 
          that the Pope ought not to suppress the office or power of the electors of the empire,
          in which nevertheless he obtains greater authority as is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-Rd1e454">c. ad apostolice de re iudicata lib. 6</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e424">
          And thus by stronger reason in our case.
          For if where there appears and is greater evidence of the power of the Church 
          in the institution of a king or supreme prince,
          that very power and authority or right of electing by the free consent of the peoples 
          to whom it belongs by right or custom is not taken away:
          much less by right can such power or authority and consent be taken away 
          <pb ed="#B" n="54-v"/>
          from gentile and infidel peoples existing entirely outside the Church,
          in whom a lesser evidence of the power of the Church appears to be,
          and in truth is less:
          since it does not have coercive power over them,
          but only in potency,
          nor yet fully in potency,
          as will be seen below.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e321-d1e454">
          Therefore a new King cannot be given to them unless those same peoples 
          and those whose right is diminished have voluntarily consented.
          If therefore it is necessarily required that those peoples and their princes consent 
          to the election or institution concerning our Kings of Spain made by the Pope 
          as universal lords of that world:
          since the business is most grave and very burdensome,
          namely against the natural freedom of those kingdoms and the servile 
          and worse state of all the inhabitants and of their kings or magistrates,
          and therefore extremely odious:
          it is manifest that it is necessary,
          so that they may freely give such consent:
          that they be moved,
          induced and persuaded by the sweetest,
          gentlest,
          indeed supplicating words and pleasing inducements and good reasons:
          and not perfunctorily.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

