<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 38</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 38</title>
          <date when="2025-12-13">December 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Hd1e97">Section 38</head>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e99">
          § 37
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e108">
          ¶ From the preceding corollary and its proofs follows another Corollary 2
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e117">
          ¶ All gold, 
          silver, 
          precious stones, 
          pearls, 
          gems, 
          any other metal and whatever other precious things which the Spanish had under the earth or under water or above, 
          from the time when that world was discovered until now, 
          except that which the inhabitants from the beginning of the aforesaid discovery, 
          before they had received evils from the Spanish, 
          either gave as a gift or freely, 
          or by reason of exchange made in certain places voluntarily, 
          all was stolen, 
          unjustly usurped and extracted as wrongfully taken, 
          and consequently the Spanish committed theft or robbery, 
          and it was and now is subject to restitution.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e164">
          ¶ Here we do not speak of things stolen through wars and violent invasions, 
          which either kings and lords or private persons had in their goods, 
          because concerning these who could doubt that they were taken unjustly and tyrannically and are subject to restitution, 
          unless he be a bestial man. 
          But we understand in this corollary concerning those precious things which were extracted from gold and silver mines and from the sea or rivers by the industry of the Spanish.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e189">
          ¶ The corollary is proved because all those things had a lord and lords, 
          and now in many places they have their own, 
          namely kings and princes of provinces, 
          or the peoples themselves and communities, 
          or certain particular persons in whose fields or estates or land they are found.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e204">
          Therefore without the permission of the prince or magistrate or of the people itself or the lord, 
          it was not lawful for anyone to seek, 
          take away or carry off those things. 
          Therefore it was robbery and unjustly usurped, 
          etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e220">
          The antecedent is clear from those things which were 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e224">discussed and proved in the first consideration</ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e229">§ 5</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e231">6</ref>, 
          where it was shown that that entire world which is in the highest Ocean sea and the kingdoms which it contains, 
          and all things that are in them, 
          belong to no men or peoples of the world except to those Indian nations and their kings, 
          with complete jurisdiction by natural and civil law confirmed by divine law, 
          old and new.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e251">
          Therefore all those things which the corollary contains had and have proper lords.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e256">
          ¶ Moreover the first consequence is proved. 
          Both because it is not lawful for anyone to cross the boundaries of others, 
          as it is said in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e265" target="http://scta.info/resource/prov22_28">Proverbs 22</ref>, 
          after the division or distinction of things and provinces. 
          As 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rj28ddd" corresp="#cy8th8-d1e558-Qd82asd">l. ex hoc iure ff. de iustitia et iure</ref>, 
          there: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Qd82asd" source="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e59-d1e162@14-17">"the kingdoms are distinguished."</quote>
          
          Because although before the division of provinces and kingdoms all things were most common, 
          after the division was made, 
          however, 
          they became not so common but public, 
          that is, 
          belonging to whatever people or nation which first occupied them. 
          Whence they did not remain common to all nations as before, 
          but to the nation first occupying them and the members of the same, 
          as is expressly proved in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e301">Inst. de rerum divisione § fere</ref>, 
          there: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Qd1e307">"For what before was no one's is granted by natural reason to the one occupying it"</quote>
          
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e312" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e5147-Dd1e297">ff. de verborum significatione l. inter publica</ref> 
          with the notes there.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e318">
          ¶ Both because it is not lawful for anyone to disturb another or inflict injury, 
          much less a king or an entire city or community. 
          For one disturbs and does injury (as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e329">appeared in the preceding §</ref>) 
          by simple entry into another's land or house without the permission of the lord, 
          and if he takes anything from it, 
          especially something precious, 
          all the more so, 
          as is clear in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e338" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e903-Dd1e296">ff. de servitutibus rusticorum praediorum l. divus</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e343" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e2502-Dd1e216">ff. de usufructu per legatum l. heres</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e345" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e926-d1e253">ff. si servitus vindicetur l. sicut § Aristo</ref>, 
          in which laws it is prohibited to enter into the fields or lands of others or to take anything from them or to do anything without the permission of the lords. 
          But by entering into a foreign kingdom, 
          especially with an army, 
          and taking from it anything, 
          especially precious things, 
          without the permission of the king or people, 
          one does injury and disturbs both the king and the entire community of the kingdom, 
          as above § 5 and from many other things above it is clear. 
          Therefore such a one does something illicit.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e371">
          ¶ But our people without the permission of either kings or peoples, 
          indeed against their will, 
          violently stealing, 
          killing, 
          slaughtering, 
          devastating, 
          with slaughter, 
          with fires, 
          despoiled the proper lords (namely those peoples, 
          their kings and all the peoples) of their Dominions, 
          jurisdictions, 
          dignities, 
          lands, 
          forests, 
          mountains, 
          fields, 
          rivers, 
          waters of the sea, 
          minerals or veins of gold and silver, 
          and all other things which were born in them and which nature produced for the common necessity, 
          ornament, 
          sufficiency and utility of the common good of each kingdom or community and the solace of the inhabitants, 
          as appeared above § in the proof of the 5th conclusion, 
          and from them they usurped and carried away infinite weights of gold and silver and pearls and gems and other precious things. 
          Therefore all gold, 
          silver and whatever precious things, 
          etc., 
          which our people had throughout all the aforesaid time were stolen and unjustly usurped and wrongfully taken. 
          And consequently they committed theft, 
          robbery and the greatest tyranny. 
          Both parts of this consequence 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e477">appeared clear above § 3</ref> 
          in the proof of a certain conclusion and in what follows.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e482">
          ¶ Of this opinion was the most learned 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e488">
            
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Nd1e489">Master Friar Dominic de Soto</name> 
            in De iustitia et iure, 
            Book 5, 
            Question 3, 
            Article 3, 
            Argument 2, 
            in a certain doubt: 
            Whether it is lawful for anyone of one nation to travel to another seeking gold</ref>. 
          For it appears that this is lawful to each by the same reason, 
          namely by which little stones found on the seashore become by the law of nations the property of the finder, 
          after the shores remained common by the law of nations. 
          He responds that this 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Qd1e508">"by law is not entirely lawful unless the inhabitants themselves consented, 
            or held those same treasures as abandoned. 
            For regions are divided by the law of nations. 
            And therefore, 
            although those things of that region are common to the peoples of that region, 
            nevertheless foreigners cannot usurp those same things against the will of the inhabitants. 
            For neither would the French be able to penetrate to us for this reason, 
            nor we to them against their will"</quote>
          
          these are his words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e536">
          I add whether our most serene king Philip would patiently endure, 
          and also the kingdom of Castile, 
          that the King of France or the French of the same kingdom would come without his permission, 
          penetrating all the way to the silver mines of Guadalcanal or other places, 
          and from there would collect silver or even gold or other precious things. 
          And if in fact they entered, 
          they would be held for theft or robbery if violently. 
          Likewise they would do injury and disturb the kingdom of Spain. 
          Again, 
          would the king of Spain then sleep with hand upon hand? 
          Do you believe not? 
          Without doubt no.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e576">
          From these things arises another corollary
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e581">
          Corollary 3
          Every part of the earth, 
          fields, 
          mountains, 
          lands, 
          forests, 
          rivers in which the Spanish built cities, 
          towns and places, 
          constructed buildings and have estates, 
          meadows, 
          pastures, 
          or common fields where their cattle and herds (if indeed they are theirs) graze, 
          were usurped and unjustly possessed by them and tyrannically held, 
          and unless they restore them to the proper lords or communities or particular persons, 
          they cannot be saved. 
          Nor does it relieve or excuse them that the Catholic kings or governors whom they send there either donate or grant permission to take lands and fields, 
          mountains, 
          etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e629">
          And whatever they built and planted belongs to the land and to the lords of the land.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e640">
          ¶ The first part of this corollary appears sufficiently from the 2nd and from the 1st corollaries and from other preceding things,
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e648">
          both first because without the permission of the natural kings and their peoples, 
          indeed against the will of all of them, 
          by force and hostilely, 
          with injuries and disturbances and irreparable damages and evils, 
          they entered those foreign lands and occupied the aforesaid things, 
          and today they do not cease to occupy them, 
          with the proper lords and natural possessors wrongfully despoiled, 
          as appears superabundantly from things said and proved.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e665">
          ¶ Both second because the tyranny of the Spanish is now permanent and actual, 
          by which they oppress all those peoples and are consumed.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e674">
          ¶ Both third because the right of war to pursue their enemies the Spanish, 
          to kill them and to destroy their name from the earth is perpetual among those peoples, 
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e685">was proved in § 29 in the proof of the corollary placed there</ref>. 
          From which things it is manifestly shown that those peoples always have and most deservedly maintain perpetual hatred of the Spanish, 
          and always consider themselves and their things unwillingly detained by them, 
          and consequently think night and day about expelling them and shaking off from themselves their tyrannical and intolerable yoke. 
          Which they have shown in deed a thousand times and a hundred thousand times in various places when they tried to rebel or rise up against them, 
          although they were not able to achieve or accomplish this because they are unarmed, 
          naked, 
          weak, 
          and inexperienced in war compared to our people.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e706">
          Both fourth because all things which were done by the Spanish were always void by law and are void, 
          lacking force. 
          As done by tyrants, 
          with the order of natural and divine law being despised by them. 
          Concerning all of which things, 
          evidence has been made sufficiently above in various places. 
          Therefore all those things which the corollary contains were usurped and unjustly held and tyrannically possessed by the Spanish. 
          And that they cannot be saved unless they restore them is clear, 
          because sin is not forgiven unless what was taken is restored, 
          as was proved in §.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e730">
          ¶ The second part of the corollary, 
          namely that it does not relieve or excuse the Spanish that our kings grant permission to take those things or make a grace of such things, 
          etc.,
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e746">
          is proved because our Kings have no jurisdiction, 
          no royal power in that entire world of the Indies in act, 
          as was concluded at the end of § 29.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e753">
          Both first because none of the kings nor any particular person has thus far rightly and correctly received our kings as lords and universal princes, 
          nor has ever consented to the aforesaid papal institution, 
          as is clear in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e764">§ 31, 4th conclusion</ref> 
          with its proof.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e767">
          ¶ Both second because the said papal institution concerning our kings is not of greater efficacy than was the election of God concerning Saul and David, 
          the first kings among the Jewish people. 
          But the election of God does not suffice alone without the consent and acceptance of the people 
          so that the aforesaid kings would have right in that kingdom, 
          that is, 
          the exercise of royal power and of jurisdiction. 
          And consequently they did not make any grace nor could they make it, 
          since they lacked actual jurisdiction and the exercise of royal power, 
          nor did they occupy themselves in anything concerning the rule or disposition of the people, 
          as was shown evidently in § 18 and 19. 
          Therefore neither does the aforesaid papal institution suffice or sufficed alone without the consent and acceptance of the peoples with their kings of that world, 
          so that he might have right in it and the exercise of jurisdiction or royal power, 
          and consequently our people could not occupy themselves with the rule or disposition of those peoples, 
          nor with any grace to be made to the Spanish, 
          especially in such notorious prejudice to those peoples.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e812">
          ¶ Both third because, 
          as was clearly shown in conclusion 3 and in its proof, 
          our illustrious kings have only a title to those kingdoms, 
          that is, 
          a cause of acquiring dominion or supreme principate of that world, 
          with the order of law being observed and the due circumstances which are numbered in conclusion 2. 
          That is to say that they have only a right to those kingdoms, 
          lacking all actual jurisdiction, 
          at least coercive, 
          and they can attend only to preparatory matters, 
          as appears from things said above.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e834">
          ¶ Both fourth because, 
          as was declared in the following corollary after the 3rd conclusion with its proof, 
          our kings have the principate and royal power in habit only, 
          and not yet fully in purified habit, 
          but to be purified when those things which the 2nd conclusion contains shall have been fulfilled.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e853">
          ¶ Both fifth because our kings, 
          as was also determined in conclusion 5 with its proof, 
          as to actual dominion and jurisdiction and juridical possession or the exercise of royal power, 
          now are and always have been in that state in which they were when their promotion or institution was made in Rome.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e872">
          ¶ Both sixth, 
          and it appeared in its proof, 
          the often-mentioned institution concerning our kings remained suspended and pending, 
          and now it is so from the time when our Spanish wrongfully entered those lands, 
          and such will it remain until the tyranny which is continuous ceases and satisfaction for damages or voluntary remission is made, 
          according to things said above § 35.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e891">
          ¶ Both seventh because our kings have no juridical possession, 
          but an improper and usurped one, 
          on account of the malice and tyranny of the Spanish, 
          as was concluded above § 33.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e905">
          ¶ Both eighth because all things which were done by the messengers or officials of our kings in the royal name, 
          as to entry and progress, 
          were void of all juridical effect, 
          as we have proved at length and manifestly in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e926">§ 34 in the 9th proof of the 5th Conclusion</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e932">
          ¶ Both finally ninth because even if our kings had actually had complete jurisdiction and also the free exercise of royal power, 
          they could not have granted such ample graces in such enormous prejudice to those inhabiting those lands and their proper lords, 
          such as those things which the Spanish have usurped. 
          For the prince cannot dispose at will concerning the substance of his subjects, 
          nor do anything in prejudice of the people itself without its assent being required, 
          as 
          <ref>Innocent and others note in c. quae in ecclesiarum de constitutionibus</ref> 
          and 
          <ref>the legists in l. fi. C. si contra ius vel utilitatem publicam</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref>c. inquisitioni de sententia excommunicationis by Innocent</ref> 
          and 
          <ref>c. quanto de iureiurando by Panorimitanus</ref>. 
          Therefore it does not relieve or excuse the Spanish in those things which they have tyrannically occupied, 
          namely parts of lands, 
          fields, 
          forests, 
          pastures, 
          etc., 
          that the Catholic kings our lords made a grace of such things or gave permission to take them, 
          or even their governors.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e989">
          Nor does 
          <ref>l. bene a Zenone C. de quadriennii praescriptione</ref> 
          stand in the way, 
          where a donation by the prince of another's thing is validated after four years have elapsed, 
          so that the lord of the thing is no longer heard, 
          although he whose thing it is can act for the price against the fisc. 
          But truly 
          <ref>said l. bene a Zenone</ref> 
          does not stand in the way in those things which are stolen against the law of nature because they are void, 
          nor can the prince validate them, 
          since he can do nothing against the rules of reason or natural law, 
          to which like other men he is subject, 
          as is clear in the 2nd consideration. 
          Nor does it avail even if he says "supplying every defect," 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e1021">Clementine Pastoralis de re iudicata</ref> 
          with the notes there. 
          Nor does the tolerance of the prince justify the act, 
          however much time passes, 
          in those things which are not obtainable without the approval of law, 
          as 
          <ref>Geminian says in a similar case in c. licet de praebendis lib. 6</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e1030">
          ¶ Likewise 
          <ref>said l. bene a Zenone</ref> 
          does not have place when the prince does not possess the thing either alienated or conceded, 
          according to 
          <ref>Bartolus in said l. fi. C. si contra ius vel utilitatem publicam</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e1042">
          ¶ The same if he alienates before delivery, 
          according to 
          <ref>Baldus in c. 1 § fi. de nova forma fidelitatis</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e1052">
          ¶ But our kings have neither juridical possession, 
          but one against all law (as has been proved), 
          nor have those things nor any part of that world been rightly or correctly delivered to them. 
          For the praetor does not protect an unjust possession, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e1063">ff. de publicis l. cum sponsus § si res</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e1069">
          ¶ Moreover the last part, 
          namely that whatever the Spanish built in those lands they lose and it belongs to the land and to the lords of the places, 
          is proved.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e1079">
          Both first because a building regularly belongs to the land, 
          as Institutes de rerum divisione § cum autem in suo.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e1084">
          Both second because one building on another's land knowingly and in bad faith, 
          as these do, 
          loses the part of his thing, 
          namely the material if he placed it.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-d1e1089">
          And he is said to offend, 
          Inst. de re divisione § si quis rei, 
          ff. de rei vindicatione, 
          and it can be destroyed by the proper authority of the lord of the land. 
          Bartolus and the doctors in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e1097">l. sed si inter ff. de servitutibus urbanorum praediorum</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e558-Rd1e1102">l. quemadmodum ff. ad legem Aquiliam § 1</ref>. 
          And the building must be removed at the expense of the one who built illicitly, 
          Speculator de censibus actionibus § 1 verbis ut autem, 
          and thus is clear the 
          <ref>3rd corollary</ref>.
        </p> 
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>