<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 11</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 11</title>
          <date when="2025-11-13">November 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="30-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Hd1e97">Section 11</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#B" n="30-r"/>
          § 11
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e106">
          With the five considerations premised,
          supposed for the full solution of the objection placed in § 5,
          namely that although as regards any other kings of the world,
          the Indian kings and lords are free,
          recognizing no superior,
          and therefore no one without their license and good pleasure can enter those kingdoms 
          without injury and seek or scrutinize what is in them and take those things,
          nevertheless this does not have place as regards our kings of the Spains,
          who have been constituted supreme princes of that world by the Supreme Pontiff,
          etc.,
          the following conclusions are placed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e131">
          First Conclusion
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e136">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The intention of the supreme pastor of souls was that our kings should entirely observe 
          the order of law and due circumstances in approaching and entering through their messengers 
          or legates those regions and taking possession of them,
          nor did he give them license to do the contrary.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e152">
          The conclusion is proven through those things which were proven in the second consideration,
          because the Supreme Pontiff professes that he wishes to preserve divine and human laws,
          and has no power to transgress divine and natural laws.
          And there is a certain order in things to be done,
          necessary and natural,
          and similarly circumstances such as time and place and the rest,
          by which any human act is rightly and congruently clothed so that it may have goodness.
          All of which the Divine Paul comprehended:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Qd1e171" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor14_40@1-7">
            Let all things,
            he says,
            be done honestly and according to order among you
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e176">1 Corinthians 14</ref>,
          and 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Qd1e178" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_1@14-20">
            those things which are from God are ordained
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e184">Romans 13</ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e189">chapter 10</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Qd1e184" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor10_31">
            Whatever you do in word or in work,
            do it to the glory of God
          </quote>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e191">to the Colossians 3</ref>
          he says the same and adds 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Qd1e193" source="http://scta.info/resource/col3_17@10-13">
            in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ
          </quote>.
          And concerning circumstances which render human acts good,
          it is contained 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e212">29 dist throughout</ref>.
          Therefore 
          <pb ed="#B" n="30-v"/>
          the intention of the Supreme Pontiff was that our kings should observe the order of law 
          and due circumstances,
          etc.;
          consequently he did not give them license to do the contrary.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e216">
          Second Conclusion
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e221">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The necessary order of law and circumstances which by natural reason ought to be observed 
          in this matter contains the following twelve parts.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e230">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          First,
          that the advent,
          approach,
          or application of the messengers of our kings,
          among whom the preachers of the faith will be numbered,
          to the Indian regions should be pacific,
          most modest,
          and lacking all complaint.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e243">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Slow,
          not sudden,
          and through that part of any province or kingdom by which the inhabitants and dwellers of it 
          and their princes can be least disturbed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e253">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          An ordered descent into or harmless entry upon any land,
          so that,
          namely,
          they may not first touch land or descend from ships into a port or go out before having obtained 
          the voluntary license,
          express or tacit,
          of the princes or magistrates of that land.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e268">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          A humble and gracious salutation and address to the princes and peoples and individuals who occur.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e276">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          An exemplary,
          gentle,
          and Christian conversation,
          and so that their advent may be more pleasing to them,
          a liberal offering of some small gifts on the part of our kings.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e287">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          A timely,
          quiet,
          sweet,
          and friendly notification or signification,
          most modest and conciliating of the minds of hearers,
          slow and successive with an interval of several days,
          explicative of the end or final cause of their legation and advent,
          namely that they have been sent to teach them concerning one great and true God,
          Lord of all,
          the creator,
          that is,
          to preach to them the faith of Jesus Christ whom they do not know.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e318">
          Again,
          for the protection or defense of the preachers and their own,
          the cautious construction of some strong house or tower under some pretext,
          namely for dwelling or avoiding rain or cold or heat,
          which indeed will be easy to do.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e329">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Then would follow an exhortation by mild,
          sweet,
          and placid word of the religious or preachers to making a gathering of them,
          that is,
          that all together,
          or the greater ones among them first,
          <pb ed="#B" n="31-r"/>
          then others,
          may gather in some congruous place to hear the word of life.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e344">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But after these things will supervene a discrete,
          distinct or explicit,
          and salutary and full preaching of the faith according to the form given by Christ;
          also the entrance,
          with divine help,
          of those infidels into the Catholic Church of God through faith 
          and the reception of holy baptism,
          and their voluntary incorporation into the mystical body of Christ.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e362">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Again,
          further information by the same heralds of the faith concerning the title of our kings,
          and to receiving them as it were for rendering back to our kings,
          and for so great a good of the faith,
          a recompense or some kind of gratification as universal princes,
          and an exposition of the goods which are going to come from this.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e376">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          A timely,
          most discreet,
          most modest,
          very bland,
          and most salutary exhortation to consenting to the aforesaid apostolic institution concerning our kings,
          a sweet and mild admonition and inducement.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e388">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Finally,
          having obtained their free consent and such papal institution concerning our kings 
          voluntarily accepted,
          a treaty with a pact concerning the manner of reigning,
          concerning tributes,
          and concerning services to be shown to our kings,
          with the rendering of an oath by both parties concerning the convention and pacts to be observed,
          and similar things.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e407">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore this is the order of law,
          the acts and necessary circumstances which it is necessary to observe,
          so that rightly and correctly our kings of the Spains may be able to obtain 
          the supreme principate of that world of the Indies,
          without which nothing will be valid by law,
          whatever may have been done otherwise,
          as will be clear.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e426">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Now therefore let us proceed to the proof of the conclusion and its individual parts.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e435">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The first part of the conclusion,
          namely that the first advent of the Spaniards with the preachers of the faith 
          ought to be pacific,
          etc.,
          is proven.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e447">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Through the precept and form of Christ which he established for preaching his gospel,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e465">Matthew 10</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e467">Mark 6</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e469">Luke 10</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Qd1e454">
            But entering into a house,
            he says,
            greet it,
            saying: Peace to this house.
            And if indeed it be worthy,
            your peace will come upon it;
            but if it be not worthy,
            your peace will return to you
          </quote>.
          For every salutation is an imprecation of good things.
          And yet in this salutation very many good things are enclosed,
          <pb ed="#B" n="31-v"/>
          because peace is the tranquility of order,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e470">
            Augustine says in book 19 chapter on the City of God
          </ref>.
          But no good is lacking where the tranquility of order remains.
          And according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e498">Isidore in the Etymologies</ref>,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Qd1e482">
            it is tranquility and a quiet state and the friendship of many among themselves
          </quote>.
          And therefore the pacific king with pious mercy disposed that his subjects should be chaste,
          pacific,
          and modest,
          as is said in the proem of the Decretals.
          Hence the Lord taught (according to Remigius) that the preachers of his law 
          should offer peace at their entrance,
          so that by the salutation of peace (indeed a thing so loved by all,
          so sweet and delightful),
          they might render the inhabitants of a city,
          castle,
          or house grateful and benevolent to receive and host them graciously and kindly,
          and also allure them to listen willingly to their doctrine.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e512">
          Part 2
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e514">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Lacking all complaint
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e521">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          So that in no matter,
          neither the leaders themselves nor their companions or any ministers,
          should do anything by word or deed whereby they may be troublesome or burdensome 
          to the inhabitants of any place,
          especially those things which could offend against honesty.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e537">
          Part 3
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e542">
          Namely a slow approach,
          not sudden,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e548">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Because if it were sudden or abrupt,
          it would not lack suspicion,
          and consequently they would be unduly disturbed,
          since all new,
          unusual,
          unexpected,
          and sudden things are apt to cause great disturbance,
          because they are especially feared.
          For they seem to be greater evils and less remediable,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e566">Augustine in book 2 of the Confessions</ref>.
          For every sudden change of things does not happen without a certain conflict,
          as it were,
          of minds,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e597">Boethius in book 2, prose 1 of the Consolation</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e578">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          These things are sufficiently expressly proven through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e583">
            l. obseruare § antequam ff. de officio proconsulis
          </ref>,
          where it is said:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Qd1e588">
            Before the proconsul enters the boundaries of the province decreed to him,
            he ought to send an edict concerning his advent containing some commendation of himself,
            namely "I love you,
            I come for your utility,"
            and similar things,
            and he should signify on what day he is going to enter the boundaries.
            For very often these uncertain and unexpected things disturb the provincials 
            and impede their acts at entry.
            He also ought to observe this,
            that he enter the province through that part through which it is customary to enter,
            and to observe to which city first he will come or apply.
            For the provincials consider it important to preserve for themselves the custom 
            and prerogatives of this kind,
            etc.
          </quote>
          These things there.
          Where Baldus notes that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Qd1e612">
            uncertain and unexpected things disturb the provincials,
            and that a city is said to be disturbed when,
            by reason of some case,
            men abandon their arts and ministries.
            And that someone ought to enter into his own land or city (certainly more strongly into another's) 
            through customary places.
            For if a prince commits a proconsul or governor to his kingdom to moderate 
            a province subject to him,
            it is altogether necessary to observe that before he enters the boundaries of that province,
            he signify his advent and make commendation of himself,
            namely with what love he pursues the provincials,
            and that they may know he is sent for their common utility,
            so that he may be able to conciliate the benevolence of the provincials to himself.
            Finally,
            let his entry and by what part he is going to enter be clear,
            lest the inhabitants of cities and places be able to be disturbed by the uncertain 
            and unexpected advent and entry of the proconsul.
            How much more reasonably and strongly,
            indeed far more and most greatly will it be and would it have been necessary to observe this 
            before any messengers or legates of our kings act or may act or may have acted,
            so that by peace,
            gentleness,
            and good and Christian acts they might capture the benevolence of those peoples,
            saying or doing nothing troublesome or from which they can or could be disturbed
          </quote>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-d1e657">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Again,
          Baldus notes that he who wishes to disturb the order is bound by an action of injuries,
          and can resist even with armed hand,
          because no one is bound to suffer injury or to think little of his own honor,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e203-Rd1e677" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e483-Dd1e104">
            ff. de postulando l. 1
          </ref>.
          To the same is referred another part.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
