<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 18</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 18</title>
          <date when="2025-11-14">November 14, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-14" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="49-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Hd1e97">Section 18</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e99">
          § 18
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Fourthly it is proved that without the free consent and approval of those peoples 
          and their kings themselves,
          another new king cannot be given to them or established over their natural kings,
          thus.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e115">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          We can allege the authorities and examples of sacred scripture for the decision of causes 
          and determination of doubts,
          as is the text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e125">c. per venerabilem extra qui fil sint legitimi</ref>:
          and what is noted there and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e132">c. 2 de prescriptionibus</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e137">c. cum apostolus de censibus</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e139">de prebendis c. cum secundum</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e132">
          This is also proved by two glosses of civil law. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e146">
            One in authent. Ut iudices: sine quoquo suffragio § cogitatio in verbo eloquiorum
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e151">The other in l. illud ff. ad l. aquiliam</ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e156">Baldus in authent. ad hec 2 columna C. de usuris</ref> 
          The same 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e161">Baldus alleges the Apostle in rubrica C. de fide instrumentorum</ref>.
          And the jurists say this is true unless there were a law contrary to divine authority,
          because then one would stand by the law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e149">
          This is however limited:
          unless divine authority were speaking concerning things pertaining to the soul,
          because then it is superior not only to civil law § finali de secundis nuptiis:
          but also to canon law or to the hearer of canon: 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e177">25, q. 1. c. sunt quidam</ref> 
          concerning this see Felinus in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e182">c. ex parte el 1o 20 columna de scriptis.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e160">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But in sacred scripture it is found ordained:
          in order that in the giving or establishment of a new and supreme prince from the beginning,
          even concerning a prince whom God had designated or chosen,
          there should intervene the free consent and authority and voluntary acceptance of the peoples:
          without which even divine institution concerning the supreme prince did not obtain effect.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e179">
          Therefore without the free consent and approval of those peoples and their kings themselves,
          a new King cannot be given to them or established.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e186">
          We say notably from the beginning,
          namely before the kingdom or principate is transferred by succession.
          Since from the beginning every principate or governance of a people has drawn its origin 
          from the consent and election of the people 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e219">l. ex hoc iure ff. de iustitia et iure</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e221">
            ff. 
            <pb ed="#B" n="49-v"/>
            de origine iuris l. 2 § deinde cum essent
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e229">§ nouissime</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e231">ff. de constitutione principum l. 2</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e236">
            instit. de iure naturali gentium et ciuili § sed et hoc studiosum
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e241">
            authent. de instrumentorum cautela et fide § et quia imperium
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e206">
          The consequence is evident.
          The Minor is proved by that passage in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e251">Deuteronomy 17</ref> 
          where it is said thus: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e212">
            When you shall enter the land which the Lord your God will give you 
            and shall possess it and shall dwell in it,
            and shall say: I will set a king over me,
            as all nations have round about,
            you shall set him whom the Lord your God shall choose from among the number 
            of your brethren
          </quote> 
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e227">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          In which words indeed the Lord decreed that two things ought to concur 
          for the institution of a king and the exercise of royal power.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e238">
          One from the part of the one instituting,
          namely that he should have been elected by divine providence,
          awaiting in the election the judgment of God.
          The other from the part of the people:
          namely that the people should voluntarily receive such a one elected by God as king 
          and willingly hold it as valid and hand over possession of the kingdom.
          Which two things the aforesaid words clearly denote,
          namely "you shall set him whom the Lord your God shall choose" 
          where a voluntary act,
          that is the consent and approval of the people,
          was required.
          There "you shall set him" that is you will hold as valid or will accept 
          and will have as king over you him whom God will have indicated to you 
          as having been chosen:
          or as having been pleasing to him to be king.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e258">
          Whence although God could have established a king over the Hebrew people even unwilling:
          both because he is the Lord of all according to Hebrews,
          and any man and any people is a servant of God by nature:
          and more than a servant,
          namely like inanimate property to its possessor,
          and thus he could do with his property whatever he wished,
          and especially because with him are the dominions and rights of the kingdoms of the earth:
          and he can give them to whom he wills,
          as appears in Daniel 4: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e275">
            Until you know that the Most High rules in the kingdom of men 
            and will give it to whom he will
          </quote> 
          Especially because that people was governed under the special care of God,
          as appears in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e282">Deuteronomy 7</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e284">
            The Lord your God has chosen you to be his peculiar people
          </quote> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e293">Exodus 19</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e295">
            You shall be to me a peculiar possession from among all peoples
          </quote>.
          Nevertheless he did not wish to deprive them of the privilege of natural law 
          by which it pertains to every man and to every free people 
          to submit themselves of their own accord to another's governance if they see it useful to them.
          For God does not destroy or abrogate his work or natural law which from the beginning 
          he himself so wisely,
          so ordinately,
          as if immutably,
          instituted.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e312">
          For it does not belong to divine 
          <pb ed="#B" n="50-r"/>
          providence to compel or corrupt natures,
          as the great 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e362">Dionysius in D 4 de diuinis nominibus</ref> 
          says:
          Whence just as by divine ordinance it had the force of a precept 
          that the people should voluntarily set over themselves as king the one whom the Lord chose,
          that is they should hold such an election of God as valid and hand over to him 
          possession of the kingdom:
          so equally by divine ordinance the consent and ratification of the people 
          and the handing over of possession of the kingdom were necessarily required 
          for the exercise of royal power.
          Which consent of the people and acceptance and handing over of possession of the kingdom,
          if God did not require:
          he would certainly have said only: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e336">
            He shall be king over you whom the Lord your God shall choose
          </quote>.
          Nor would it be necessary to say 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e341">you shall set him whom the Lord</quote> 
          etc.
          Because however he said 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e349">you shall set him</quote>:
          he clearly indicates that by divine ordinance it is also necessarily required 
          from the part of the people:
          some act,
          namely consent and ratification or voluntary acceptance:
          and also the handing over of possession must truly intervene.
          For the words of sacred scripture must be weighed since they are full of mysteries:
          and to think that anything improper,
          superfluous or diminished can be found in it would be impious.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e365">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          This is most evident in the establishment of the first two kings,
          namely Saul and David.
          For as is found in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e422">I Kings c. 10</ref> 
          although Saul had previously been anointed as King by Samuel at God's command 
          and through that anointing had acquired the right and title to that kingdom:
          nevertheless afterward it was necessary that he be instituted and accepted by the people as king 
          and that possession of the kingdom be handed over to him.
          Nor did Saul dare to exercise the jurisdiction or authority of royal power,
          nor could he by full right,
          until the people should consent to the election made concerning him 
          and should hand over or grant to him possession of the kingdom.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e390">
          For thus it is read at the beginning of that tenth chapter:
          And Samuel took a flask of oil and poured it upon Saul's head and kissed him and said:
          Behold the Lord has anointed you over his inheritance as prince.
          Then indeed after some days had passed:
          Samuel called the people together to the Lord at Mizpah:
          and made them stand by tribes and families,
          and lots were cast first to determine the tribe,
          then the family,
          down to the men,
          and the lot came to Saul (when he was brought forth,
          because he had been hidden),
          the Lord said.
          Samuel said to all the people: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e408">
            Surely you see whom the Lord has chosen:
            for there is none like him among all the people
          </quote>:
          and all the people cried out and said: Long live the King etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e414">
          Behold the consent,
          ratification or acceptance of the people.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e420">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          After these things and not before,
          Saul began 
          <pb ed="#B" n="50-v"/>
          to use royal power when having cut an ox in pieces,
          he sent it into all the territories of Israel by the hand of messengers saying. 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e431">
            Whoever shall not come out and follow Saul and Samuel
          </quote> 
          etc. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Rd1e437">cap. 10.</ref> 
          And because some of the people had not willingly consented to God's election of Saul,
          although the title to reign had been conferred through anointing 
          and again he had been voluntarily elected as King by lot and by God's command:
          but rather many were saying 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e447">Can this one save us?</quote>
          Therefore to induce the people to consent Samuel said again to all the people: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-Qd1e454">
            Come let us go to Gilgal and renew the kingdom there
          </quote>.
          And all the people went to Gilgal:
          and they made Saul king there before the Lord in Gilgal etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e461">
          Where it appears how much care and solicitude was applied by the will of God 
          so that the privilege of natural liberty,
          namely of consenting voluntarily to a prince,
          should be preserved to the people,
          nor did he compel or reproach them:
          but he waited until they should voluntarily give consent to receiving the king 
          and should hand over possession of the kingdom:
          although from the beginning he had been divinely chosen and the royal title conferred on him.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e295-d1e480">
          Therefore so that the king might have the exercise of royal power in that people 
          and right in that kingdom:
          from divine ordinance divine institution concerning the king is not sufficient 
          without the consent and acceptance of the people.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>