<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 33</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 33</title>
          <date when="2025-12-13">December 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="87-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Hd1e97">Section 33</head>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e100">
          § 33
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e111">
          Conclusion 5
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e116">
          ¶ Our Catholic Kings of the Spains are now in that state with regard to dominion 
          and actual jurisdiction or the exercise of royal power over that world of the Indies 
          in which they were when their institution over that world was made in Rome by the 
          Supreme Roman Pontiff.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e132">
          ¶ The conclusion is proven in multiple ways and first thus, 
          namely by argument from correlatives. 
          Concerning which according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e140">
            Baldus in l. conuenticula C. de episcopis et clericis
          </ref> 
          and by the second mode in which said argument is formed, 
          namely destructively. 
          So that the removal of one of the correlatives follows the removal of the other. 
          A notable text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e145">
            l. fi. ff. de acceptiliationibus
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e147">
            l. 1, C. de Cypressis libro 11o
          </ref> 
          and what is denied or corrected in one is denied or corrected concerning the other. 
          The text is in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e161">
            l. fi., C., de iudii. vidua.
          </ref> 
          and there the 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e169">
            legists.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e172">
          ¶ For our kings and all those peoples are correlative with regard to universal 
          jurisdiction: 
          but the right or burden of having or recognizing our kings as superiors and 
          of granting consent to this has always been removed from all the kings, 
          inhabitants and peoples of that world: 
          since always and now the right of actual dominion and of exercising actual 
          jurisdiction or royal power throughout that entire world of the Indies is removed 
          from our most illustrious and Catholic kings, 
          therefore our kings are in that state etc.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e201">
          ¶ Secondly the conclusion is proven because just as then our kings had a right 
          to the thing and not in the thing with respect to that Indian world: 
          so also now they have a right to the thing and not in the thing as in conclusion 3.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e212">
          ¶ Thirdly because just as then they had only a title to those kingdoms, 
          so now they have only a title to those kingdoms as appeared in the same 
          3rd conclusion.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e223">
          ¶ Fourthly because just as then they had dominion in habit and jurisdiction 
          and not in act: 
          so now they have these not in act but in habit and still not fully in habit. 
          As is clear in the preceding corollary.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e235">
          ¶ Fifthly because just as then those twelve things required and necessarily to 
          be observed which conclusion 2 contains, 
          namely the order of natural and divine law committed to execution, 
          had not yet been fulfilled: 
          so also now and in the intermediate time they have never been observed: 
          but the contrary has been done in every way as evidently appears throughout 
          this entire treatise.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e253">
          ¶ Sixthly because just as then our kings did not have the consent of the kings 
          and peoples by which they would ratify said papal institution and by free will 
          deliver themselves to their rule and empire 
          (which is the foundation and efficient cause of this whole affair as has been proven) 
          so also now they lack the aforesaid foundation and efficient cause as was proven 
          in the penultimate part of conclusion 2.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e273">
          ¶ Seventhly because just as then none of the kings and peoples of that world 
          rightly, 
          that is juridically: 
          nor correctly, 
          that is with due circumstances, 
          recognized our kings as superior lords: 
          so now there is no one who rightly or correctly from that time until now has 
          recognized or recognizes our kings as superiors as conclusion 4 sufficiently declares.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e297">
          ¶ Finally eighthly the conclusion is proven: 
          because just as then when the apostolic letters of the aforesaid institution 
          were expedited in Rome our kings had not yet apprehended rightly or correctly 
          the possession of that world or of any part of it: 
          so also now no possession has been apprehended rightly nor correctly on the part 
          of our kings: 
          nor do they have any juridical possession now.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e316">
          ¶ We speak here of possession with respect to those nations inhabiting the 
          aforementioned world of whose right we treat here. 
          But with respect to other kings of the world, 
          especially Christians, 
          it is otherwise. 
          Since it is true that the first admiral or sea captain who first discovered the 
          aforesaid world and all other ambassadors of our kings in whatever place to which 
          they first came apprehended juridical corporal possession. 
          Whence no prince of the world especially of Christians has anything to do in that 
          entire world of the Indies except the Kings of Castile and Leon our lords on account 
          of said institution made concerning these our kings by the Roman pontiff: 
          and the simultaneous apostolic prohibition that no other whatsoever of whatever 
          condition or dignity dare to intrude himself as we touched upon above for any cause 
          of going or sending without the license and good pleasure of our kings to that world.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e356">
          ¶ But that no possession has been apprehended rightly or correctly thus far on 
          the part of our kings in that entire world: 
          certainly through many of those things which have been disputed and declared above 
          it can be seen in clear light.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e370">
          Nevertheless we wish to prove this anew and especially. 
          And first, 
          thus.
          ¶ Possession is not to be taken from anyone before cognizance of the cause: 
          nor should the possessor be expelled without him being summoned and heard: 
          even if someone has license to expel. 
          Otherwise what is done is worthless: 
          and the one expelling falls from his right if he has any in it.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e395">
          But all the peoples of that entire world of the Indies were in possession of it: 
          from whom nevertheless all possession has been taken away by the Spaniards both of 
          dominions, 
          jurisdictions and rights (public and private) corporal and incorporeal: 
          as well as of lands, 
          woods, 
          mountains, 
          rivers, 
          waters and all things that were born in the aforesaid: 
          as in the mines of gold and silver, 
          salt works: 
          of gold and silver and other metals, 
          salt: 
          pearls, 
          gems, 
          unions, 
          precious stones and other things of price and estimation incomparable: 
          and thus possessors and proprietary lords of so many and such great things and of 
          immense value of which like things Solomon in all his glory neither had nor saw 
          nor could nature of things dream: 
          they were expelled and despoiled before cognizance of the cause without them being 
          summoned or heard.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e441">
          Therefore the apprehension or rather the taking of such possession by the Spaniards, 
          indeed the violent despoliation and usurpation was not done rightly nor correctly 
          on the part of our kings: 
          and consequently it is worth nothing or was worth nothing: 
          and if they had had any right in that world they would fall from it. 
          How much more so having acquired no right in the aforesaid world.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e454">
          ¶ Moreover cognizance of a cause 
          (according to the jurists) 
          is the deliberation of a judge from the assertion of the plaintiff and the 
          contradiction of the adversary solemnly made to investigate the truth of causes in 
          which the right is deposited as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e468" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e924-Dd1e126">
            l. 3, ff. De restitutione in integrum
          </ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e475" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e965-d1e986">
            l. si ex plagis, §  in cliuo, ff., Ad Legem Aquiliam.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e479">
          ¶ The minor through evidence of the fact is clear to the whole world. 
          ¶ Moreover the consequence with the major is proven first by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e489" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e5001-Dd1e157">
            l. meminerint C. unde vi
          </ref> 
          where it appears that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Qd1e496">
            if the pope or emperor grants castles to someone he cannot occupy them by his 
            own authority unless the order of law is observed. 
            But if he invades the possession he is deprived of his right. 
            Likewise if a judge gives license to someone it is not valid unless the order of 
            law is observed and those abusing it fall from their right. 
            For the order of judgments is to be observed. 
            In which judgment the possessor must be cited if he is found otherwise a procurator 
            is cited who denounces to him
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e513">
            these things Baldus in the summary of said law: meminerint
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e518" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e5001-Dd1e170">
            l. si quis in tantam C. eo titulo
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e523" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e5013-Dd1e119">
            C. si per vim l. 2
          </ref> 
          where it is said that the possessor not summoned nor cited should not be disturbed 
          in his possession even by rescript of the prince or interlocution of the judge, 
          these things from that. 
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e533">
            capitulo conquerente de restitutione spoliatorum
          </ref> 
          where possession taken without judicial order is to be restored before all else.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e542">
          ¶ But since those entire peoples disturbed by so many violences, 
          not summoned: 
          not heard: 
          and with the order of law not observed, 
          were despoiled of the possession of all their rights by the Spaniards, 
          therefore no possession has been apprehended rightly nor correctly until now on 
          the part of our kings nor do they have any juridical possession now in that entire 
          world. 
          And consequently our kings are in that state today which conclusion 5 declares.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e567">
          ¶ Secondly the same is proven. 
          Because if possession is not to be taken from heretics without a declaratory sentence 
          although they lose the dominion of their things by the law itself as is expressly 
          provided in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e583">
            c. cum secundum de hereticis libro 6
          </ref> 
          in the word 
          <mentioned>confiscationis</mentioned> 
          where 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e589">
            petrus de ancharano
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e596">
            c. licet de prebendis eo libro
          </ref> 
          says that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Qd1e598">
            although in the case of heresy and similar cases dominion is acquired without 
            tradition or the heretic loses it by the law itself: 
            nevertheless he does not lose possession
          </quote> 
          as is 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e607">
            a notable gloss in l. fi. C. de sacrosanctis ecclesiis
          </ref> 
          How much less therefore is possession to be taken from those who justly possess: 
          nor are they deprived or to be deprived of their dominions like the aforesaid nations. 
          Whence 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e623">
            Ancharanus adds in c. licet
          </ref> 
          that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Qd1e624">
            no disturbance or violence is to be inflicted on one possessing peacefully that 
            he might not use his possession until by sentence another is declared lord even 
            if at first sight it is unjust. 
            For such injustice must be established before the judge as judge. 
            Which cannot happen unless the party is summoned as 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e637">
              l. fi. C.
            </ref> 
            si per vim vel alio modo.
          </quote>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e642">
          The reason for which according to the same Ancharranus is because from some cause 
          a right of retaining can be competent to him from which 
          (he says) 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Qd1e648">
            note that however much common law makes against one possessing so that his 
            possession is patently improper, 
            nevertheless it is not to be taken away without him being summoned. 
            And hence it is that in notorious crimes citation is required according to what 
            is noted in 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e661">
              c. uestra de cohabitatione clericoram et mulierum
            </ref> 
            for there is no crime so notorious: 
            that it does not have an excuse for avoiding punishment as says singularly 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e673">
              Innocentius in c. preterea de dilationibus
            </ref> 
            to this 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e675">
              c. cum dilecti de accusationibus
            </ref> 
            where plundering, 
            rapine, 
            and Simony can be excused: 
            although by confession in judgment they become notorious
          </quote> 
          these things Ancharanus. 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e698">
            baldus says in c. inter quatuor de maioritate et obediendia
          </ref> 
          that possession is the legitimate shield and sword of the possessor until he is 
          defeated by the judge as indeed 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e708">
            ff. de euictionibus l. habere licet
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e710">
            C. de iure fiscis l. prohibitum lib. 10
          </ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e714">
            C. de meta. l. deuotum. lib.
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e716">
            C. si per vim vel alio modo l. fi.
          </ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e721">
            C. si propter publicam poenam l. si deserit.
          </ref> 
          And what is done without citation: 
          must be revoked without citation. 
          So that just as the judge was easy in sending, 
          so he should be prompt in correcting 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e706">
            l. 1, § 1, ff. simul ven. enim
          </ref> 
          where there is a singular text. 
          these things baldus.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e715">
          ¶ Since therefore even notoriously unjust possessors and those against whom common 
          law makes: 
          are not to be disturbed or any molestation inflicted on them that they might not 
          peacefully use and enjoy their possession. 
          Until they are summoned and heard and all those things which the order of law 
          requires are observed: 
          and finally by sentence it is declared and it is established to them possessing 
          wrongly how rightly and correctly they should be despoiled, 
          how much more these things should be observed and should have been observed with 
          the Indian peoples in whose favor all common law, 
          indeed all laws natural divine and human, 
          make. 
          Since however none of these things has been observed with them: 
          but in the manner of thieves, 
          plunderers, 
          robbers: 
          invading that world and any part of it, 
          our Spaniards have thus far violently and terribly entered: 
          laying waste all things, 
          usurping, 
          slaughtering, 
          depopulating as if fire sent down from heaven devoured all things: 
          it follows that the apprehension or taking of such possession by the Spaniards: 
          was not done rightly: 
          not correctly: 
          not with the order of law observed: 
          but with all law violated, 
          was done usurped tyrannical and condemned by all law: 
          and therefore our kings have no juridical possession today: 
          whence they are now in the aforesaid primordial state etc.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e789">
          ¶ All things which we have deduced concerning this are confirmed and this can also 
          be a third proof through the example which we read in divine scripture concerning 
          Abraham and his posterity. 
          For as is found in Genesis 12 although God had promised to Abraham and to his seed 
          after him to give the land of Canaan and thus Abraham had a most just title and 
          right to that land, 
          nevertheless he did not decree that Abraham should take possession of that land nor 
          Isaac nor Jacob until the party should be cited and heard, 
          that is the sins of those peoples should be completed which appealed to the judge 
          God as it were as plaintiff against them and by sentence the judge should decree 
          that actually the children of Israel should be sent into possession. 
          Which was then done and the sentence pronounced: 
          when their crimes were completed: 
          in the time namely of Joshua as is clear in Joshua throughout whence in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e827">
            chapter 11 of the same book
          </ref> 
          it is said 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Qd1e833">
            for it was the sentence of the Lord that their hearts should be hardened and they 
            should fight against Israel and fall and deserve no mercy and perish
          </quote> 
          etc. 
          Whence in all that running time namely before God had decreed to take that land 
          from such peoples and transfer it to the Israelites nothing of right was acquired 
          to Abraham nor to his successors nor did they have any dominion in all that land: 
          except the title and right to it: 
          but they were always strangers and pilgrims in a foreign land namely of their 
          natural possessors and lords and therefore those peoples justly held it as to 
          property and possession.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e870">
          Unless perhaps it might be objected that some saints hold that land was namely of Sem 
          the firstborn of 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Nd1e874">Noah</name>: 
          who indeed when he divided the world among his three sons gave that land to 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Nd1e878">Sem</name> 
          for himself and his posterity. 
          Which afterward the sons of Cham tyrannically and violently with the sons of 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Nd1e885">Sem</name> 
          expelled possessed for many years in barbaric fashion. 
          The Lord however because he is just to restore the land to the children of Israel 
          who from Abraham: 
          Abraham indeed who from the sons of Noah proceeded, 
          after so many thousands of years decreed and yet concerning this injustice of the 
          sons of Canaan perhaps it was not established to Abraham nor to the children of 
          Israel: 
          since they could not know except by revelation which is not made to all. 
          And although they knew since nevertheless it was not established to all: 
          therefore men could judge that land as to property and legitimate possession to 
          have been of the Canaanites. 
          Abraham following human judgment and his sons and their posterity: 
          although they knew otherwise by revelation and reckoning as if that land had not 
          been usurped from their predecessors but the Canaanites were true and legitimate 
          lords: 
          they did not build firm houses for themselves: 
          but they remained in huts and tabernacles which are mobile and portable houses as 
          these things appear 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Rd1e923">
            ad Hebreos 11
          </ref> 
          where the Apostle says concerning Abraham and his sons. 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Qd1e927" source="http://scta.info/resource/hebr11_9@2-19">
            He dwelt in the land of promise of the same
          </quote> 
          these things there. 
          And in Acts 7 it is said of Abraham 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Qd1e934" source="http://scta.info/resource/act7_4@11-26 http://scta.info/resource/act7_5@1-22">
            after his father died God transferred him (namely) 
            Abraham into this land in which you now dwell. 
            And he did not give him an inheritance in it not even the step of a foot but he 
            promised to give it to him in possession and to his seed after him
          </quote> 
          these things there.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e950">
          Moreover the promise of some grace: 
          does not confer any right on him to whom it is promised as is clear in Abraham and 
          for that reason Abraham was never bold to usurp anything as his own in that land 
          until that promise should be decreed to be fulfilled with effect by the judge God 
          himself. 
          This is clear: 
          when needing a place for burying Sarah his wife he bought from the inhabitants of 
          that land namely from Ephron son of Seor a field in which was the double cave: 
          nor did he wish to accept it freely: 
          but gave four hundred shekels of silver of approved public money as appears in 
          Genesis 23 and there he said 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-Qd1e976" source="http://scta.info/resource/gen23_4@1-15">
            I am a stranger and pilgrim among you give me the right of burial with you that 
            I may bury my dead
          </quote> 
          etc.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e985">
          If therefore the land promised by God to the children of Israel in which those 
          sinful peoples dwelt: 
          and who were to be deprived entirely of dominion and possession and every right by 
          divine decree: 
          indeed by the sentence of the Lord they were to be destroyed: 
          he did not wish that the Israelites who were to be the future lords by divine 
          concession should take possession until by the sentence of the judge it should be 
          established to them namely to the Hebrews that this was done according to the will 
          and command of God: 
          because for all that time those peoples justly possessed at least as to human 
          judgment: 
          how much more in these cases these things were to be observed namely not to 
          despoil them: 
          but with the order of law observed and due circumstances to attract sweetly and 
          persuade gently that of their own accord they themselves might deliver the 
          possession itself. 
          Who indeed are not only not to be destroyed or despoiled by the sentence of the 
          Lord but rather to be vivified by knowledge of the true God: 
          and to be clothed and informed with faith and the doctrine of salvation by strict 
          precept of divine law.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e1042">
          Therefore the apprehension of the possession of that world and of any part of it 
          on the part of our kings was never rightly or correctly held by the Spaniards thus 
          far but such possession was always unjustly apprehended.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e492-d1e1053">
          ¶ And since our kings have no juridical possession of that world: 
          it is manifest that they are in that state with regard to dominion and actual 
          jurisdiction and exercise of royal power: 
          in which they were when their institution concerning that world was made in Rome by 
          the Roman pontiff.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>