<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 45</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 45</title>
          <date when="2025-11-10">November 10, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-10" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="131-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Hd1e97">Section 45</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e99">
          § 45
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e108">
          But the second member of the aforesaid distinction,
          placed in the preceding §,
          was whether those who find and take away treasures are Spaniards,
          and then what should be said?
          For the decision of this doubt the following conclusion is placed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e119">
          Conclusion:
          The Spaniards are most unworthy to have any temporal good of that world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e128">
          The conclusion is proven first because,
          although by assisting the preachers of the faith and helping them,
          especially by living as they were bound to live,
          as true Christians,
          by whose example those nations would be more easily allured to embracing the faith,
          they would deservedly have been worthy to become participants in the most wealthy riches 
          and innumerable other goods with which that world abounds,
          so that by the will of the natural inhabitants and their lords all goods would be common to them 
          with these and thus they would become wealthy;
          nevertheless,
          because they have abused this privilege so wrongly,
          so ignominiously,
          so impiously,
          so cruelly and inhumanly,
          they have most deservedly rendered themselves unworthy of such a privilege 
          and have justly lost it by the very fact.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e173">
          Therefore the Spaniards are most unworthy to participate in any temporal good of that world.
          The consequence is clear.
          The antecedent is proven:
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e177">11, q. 3, c. priuilegium</ref>.
          Where it is said that one who abuses the power permitted to him altogether deserves to lose 
          the privilege,
          <pb ed="#B" n="131-v"/>
          for it is lost on account of the enormous damage supervening,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e189" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t30-Dd1e229">
            extra de decimis. c. suggestum
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e194" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t30-Dd1e214">
            c. dilecti fili
          </ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e196">
            de verborum significatione c. Quid per nouale
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e201">
            de vita et honestate clericorum c. fi.
          </ref>
          and there a good 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e203">
            gloss and de sententia excommunicationis c. contingit
          </ref>
          and de statu monachorum, c. recolentes.
          But what crimes have they committed?
          Rather what evil deeds?
          Rather what unheard-of crimes?
          And what and how enormous damages have supervened from their detestable works of this kind 
          to these peoples?
          Indeed,
          from the very many things deduced above and shown more clearly than light itself,
          and also most amply proven,
          it is easy to see.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e224">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second,
          the conclusion is proven because those things which ought rather to be turned to their punishment 
          should not lead to their advantage,
          as in c. et si necesse de donationibus inter virum et uxorem and 16, q. 1, c. legi 
          and ff. de negotiis gestis l. siue,
          and from wickedness no one obtains an action,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e238" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e4246-Dd1e252">
            ff. de furtis, l. Itaque fullo
          </ref>.
          And in the rule:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Qd1e242">
            From this no one ought to obtain fruit from which he has striven to attack
          </quote>:
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e247">
            de regulis iuris lib. 6 with its concordances
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e250">
          From this conclusion the following corollary follows:
          And therefore the Spaniards are excluded by natural reason from communication with the inhabitants 
          in seeking treasures,
          gold,
          silver,
          other metals,
          or other precious things and other temporal goods,
          even those which are in no one's goods,
          throughout that world of the Indies.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e273">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The corollary is proven in many ways.
          First,
          it is clear through the conclusion,
          because if on account of their crimes they have rendered themselves unworthy 
          to participate in any temporal good of that world,
          therefore in seeking,
          digging out,
          or carrying away treasures,
          gold,
          silver,
          and other goods,
          they are not worthy by natural reason to communicate with the inhabitants.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e296">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second,
          it is proven through the second and third corollaries 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e302">above § 31</ref>,
          situated in which it was proven that all gold,
          silver,
          and other precious things,
          lands,
          fields,
          farms,
          and other goods which the Spaniards have had and now hold have been seized,
          usurped,
          and wrongly taken away,
          and also unjustly possessed,
          nor can they be saved unless they restore them to their proper lords or their heirs.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e326">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Third,
          the corollary is proven because,
          since without the license of King Inca or his descendants or other kings and lords of the lands,
          no one can justly seek,
          scrutinize,
          dig,
          or extract those things,
          it is manifest that they will never grant this license voluntarily,
          <pb ed="#B" n="132-r"/>
          since they know they have a just cause for waging war against the Spaniards as public enemies.
          Again,
          they will scarcely cease from tyrannical and continuous oppression,
          nor do they hold any hope that they will satisfy for the evil damages and injuries received from them,
          as was proven 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e357">above § 29 in a certain corollary</ref>.
          Therefore the Spaniards are excluded from the communication of seeking treasures, etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e366">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Fourth,
          it is proven that,
          as was openly proven above §§ 31, 32, 34 and 35,
          it remains that the Spaniards from the first entry by which they entered into those lands and kingdoms 
          were tyrants in two ways,
          namely by entry and by actual exercise,
          that is,
          first through the invasions which they called <mentioned>conquests</mentioned>,
          and through servitude,
          namely the <mentioned>repartimiento</mentioned> or <mentioned>encomienda</mentioned>,
          by which they condemned all those nations,
          great and small,
          in perpetuity.
          Therefore by natural reason they have deserved ill that any way be opened to them 
          for communicating the goods of that world,
          when rather they would deserve to be slaughtered in vain.
          For there is no society or communication with tyrants,
          but rather supreme destruction,
          according to Cicero in the third book On Duties.
          Nor indeed is it against nature to despoil them if you can,
          since it is honorable to kill and exterminate this pestiferous and impious kind of men.
          For just as certain members are amputated if they themselves have begun to lack blood 
          and spirit as it were,
          and harm the remaining parts of the body,
          so this ferocity and beastly savagery in the figure of a man is to be segregated from the common body,
          as it were from humanity.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e417">
          It is proper to tyrants to desolate cities,
          to plunder sacred things,
          to enervate faith,
          to destroy religions,
          and to be more pernicious and impious and unjust (as is said in Ethics 4) 
          than the unjust,
          to oppress the people with unjust laws,
          to burden with illicit collections and tributes,
          to constitute iniquitous magistrates for fleecing the peoples like some of the plagues of Egypt,
          not to defend from invading enemies,
          and to do things similar to these.
          Hence 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Qd1e446" source="http://scta.info/resource/prov29_3@6-11">
            in the time when tyrants assume the principate the people will groan
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e451">Proverbs 29</ref>,
          and 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Qd1e453" source="http://scta.info/resource/prov28_28@1-10">
            When the impious have risen up,
            men will hide themselves;
            when those have perished,
            the just will be multiplied
          </quote>.
          And therefore under tyrants there is no republic,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e462">the same Cicero in book 1 On Duties</ref>.
          Therefore the tyrant is justly killed.
          Hence 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e467">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Nd1e468">Titus Livy</name>
            book 8 on the Macedonian war
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Qd1e471">
            Against him who cannot endure just and equal law,
            this unjust force is not unjust
          </quote>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e477">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore after the hostile entry of the Spaniards into that world,
          <pb ed="#B" n="132-v"/>
          a most wicked plague,
          crueler and more devastating than any Egyptian plague,
          invaded all those miserable nations,
          at which infinite mortals of both sexes groaned,
          indeed perished groaning,
          but innumerable peoples,
          and the residue hid themselves as if from the face of tigers,
          lions,
          and dragons,
          whom the sword and cruelty of servitude had not seen,
          and now surely those who can hide themselves,
          attaining the hiding places of mountains as quickly as possible,
          so that made companions of wild beasts,
          they may lead or live their lives in groaning and bitterness.
          And therefore not undeservedly the Spaniards are excluded by natural reason 
          from all communication of temporal goods with the natives,
          seeking treasures or any other temporal good of that world,
          since they have made themselves unworthy even of the least of such things.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e519">
          From which also a second corollary follows:
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The Spaniards who have deserved ill of the Indian nations,
          both by invasions,
          that is,
          <mentioned>conquests</mentioned>,
          and by general servitude,
          that is,
          <mentioned>repartimiento</mentioned> or <mentioned>encomienda</mentioned>,
          are bound by necessity of salvation,
          after complete or possible restitution of things wrongly taken away 
          and satisfaction for damages,
          to choose perpetual residence in that world and to dwell there perpetually at their own expense,
          especially in those provinces whose inhabitants they killed or otherwise oppressed and harmed,
          for the sake of the favor of the faith which they notably impeded and defamed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e550">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The corollary is proven as to this,
          that they are obligated to restitution.
          It can be seen through many things treated and elucidated above,
          especially through those things which were determined in § 42 concerning the obligation 
          of our kings to restitution.
          Since if our Catholic kings,
          against whose royal will and mandates those plunderers shook that world with their tyranny,
          are obligated to restitution from this alone,
          that it is imputed to them that they sent such messengers and evil men by carelessness,
          not by malice,
          or because after the rumor of evil deeds reached them they did not sharply correct and punish them,
          or because they did not apply due circumspection and diligence as so grave a matter required,
          how much more the tyrants themselves,
          the evildoers,
          the delinquents,
          who did so many evils through themselves and unjustly seized so many goods,
          <pb ed="#B" n="133-r"/>
          are principally bound to restore and satisfy.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e584">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But that they are bound to choose perpetual residence and to remain perpetually there at their own cost,
          in favor of the faith which they greatly harmed and defamed,
          is proven.
          First,
          because just as they were the cause that Christ and his holy Church lacked so many thousands of men 
          and nations who,
          unless they had killed them,
          taking from them the space of conversion and penance,
          would have known God,
          would have praised God and served him,
          and consequently holy houses or churches would have been constructed in which divine mysteries 
          would be celebrated,
          so these (although they were very great sinners) at least satisfy through what is possible to them,
          in this that they assist other faithful ones and constantly accompany the ministers of divine worship,
          so that churches may be constructed and those already constructed may not be deserted,
          lest divine honor be diminished with these Spaniards departing.
          For it is manifest that although it is impossible for them to repair equally the damages 
          which they inflicted on the faith and the Church of God,
          and also on so many peoples killed by them and who are now in hell,
          as for instance because they died in infidelity,
          nevertheless they remain obligated to satisfy in the manner possible to them.
          Thus 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e628">
            Saint Thomas teaches 2-2 q. 62, article 2 ad 1
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Qd1e633" source="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1592-d1e491@6-69">
            In those things in which an equivalent cannot be recompensed,
            compensation ought to be made in what is possible,
            as is clear concerning the honors which are due to God and to parents,
            as 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e639">the Philosopher says in Ethics 8</ref>.
            And therefore when that which has been taken away is not restorable through something equal,
            recompense must be made as is possible.
            For instance,
            when someone has taken away a member from someone,
            he ought to recompense him either in money or in some honor
          </quote>.
          These things Saint Thomas.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e653">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second,
          it is proven because just as through the nefarious and cruel works of the Spaniards 
          the Catholic faith was made infamous among those nations,
          and they rendered the name of Christ horrible and blasphemable,
          and they were an efficacious impediment lest it be spread throughout that whole world 
          in a brief time,
          but rather they restricted it under very few limits,
          on account of which,
          would that the promulgation of that sentence not be understood concerning them,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Rd1e678">Romans 1</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-Qd1e680" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom1_18@1-18">
            The wrath of God is revealed from heaven upon all impiety and injustice of men,
            of those who hold the truth of God in injustice
          </quote>,
          so such sinful men are bound by the force of necessary satisfaction to reside perpetually 
          at their own cost,
          without this that they receive a single penny from the Indians or from our kings,
          in the same provinces which they have devastated or in those neighboring or adjoining them,
          or at least in that world of the Indies,
          <pb ed="#B" n="133-v"/>
          and to give their full strength to this work,
          so that by their good examples,
          aids,
          exhortations,
          labors,
          and even monies if they abound,
          the faith of Christ may be received by the inhabitants,
          as the first and great gift of God,
          and they may reverence the divine name,
          and through all those most ample regions the knowledge of the true God 
          and the Christian religion may be extended and efficaciously spread through the publication 
          of the gospel.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e730">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Third,
          because on account of the faith long ago made ancient in Spain 
          and the firmness of faith by which the Spaniards through the grace of God have been made robust in faith,
          and until Christ be formed in such peoples who are now like new little plants (that is),
          while they grow together and become strong in the faith itself,
          there is need for those to be present who firmly hold and defend the faith.
          Therefore the Spaniards who have burdened those peoples are bound by the force of necessary 
          and possible satisfaction,
          beyond the common obligation by which they are Christians,
          to be present in the aforesaid provinces for the sake of the favor of the faith 
          which they most enormously harmed,
          as has been most fully proven.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e672-d1e762">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And we place an end to these things with the doubt premised which was placed at the beginning,
          to which we have responded according to our small measure as has been premised.
          All and singular the said determinations of which response we submit to the determination 
          and correction of the most holy lord our pope and of the most holy Roman Church,
          along with ourselves.
          We profess that we hold its faith and obedience unshakably,
          even unto the shedding of blood if it be necessary.
          Amen.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>