<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 31</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 31</title>
          <date when="2025-10-08">October 08, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-10-08" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="80-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Hd1e97">Section 31</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e99">
          § 31
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e104">
          Conclusion 4
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e109">
          No King or lord or people,
          nor even any private or particular person of that entire Indian world:
          from the beginning of its discovery,
          namely in the year of salvation 1493,
          up to this day of the month of August thirtieth of the year 1561,
          has known or accepted truly freely,
          rightly or juridically,
          nor correctly,
          the illustrious kings of Spain as our lords or superiors:
          nor the messengers,
          leaders,
          captains or magistrates sent by them in the name of the kings:
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e149">
          But the obedience which up to now 
          <pb ed="#B" n="81-r"/>
          they have rendered and now render is and always has been violently extorted,
          involuntary,
          and with all forced to it,
          since they do not have the forces to resist.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e164">
          And this in truth not by the fault of our Catholic kings,
          but only of the Spaniards.
          Whence all those peoples,
          kings and free peoples,
          just as they were free before the aforesaid institution,
          have always remained free by right.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e175">
          One quite small province is excepted,
          by the name of Verapaz,
          concerning whose history I will touch on something below.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e182">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The conclusion is proved as regards its first part.
          First by this reason.
          So that they might rightly,
          that is with the order of law observed,
          and correctly,
          that is with due circumstances observed:
          receive our Kings or recognize them as universal princes and superiors et Lords,
          one of two things or rather both were necessarily required.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e200">
          First that it be shown to them or proved that they were by some law bound to admit 
          our kings as universal princes and lords.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e207">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second that induced and provoked by the Spaniards through some gifts,
          good examples and sweet conduct:
          they should receive them of their own accord,
          without other reason being rendered or demonstration of right.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e228">
          Not indeed the first:
          because they never showed any right by which they would be clearly convinced 
          that they were obligated to receive some foreign prince as superior.
          Except that our people said and asserted to them that the true God in heaven 
          had instituted on earth a certain man in his place,
          by the name Pope:
          who indeed had granted all those kingdoms to the kings of Spain.
          You the reader judge whether from the said notification or proof they would be bound 
          immediately or with any delay to admit our kings as universal Lords,
          or rather would they take those words as mockery or laughter:
          or certainly that such a legation was worthy to be prosecuted with anger 
          and implacable hatred.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e268">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          You will note also what kind of beginning those legates of the faith took 
          for sowing through that world knowledge of the true God and notifying the Gospel of Christ 
          through peaceful and loving preaching.
          Although truly they did not even fully understand the words themselves,
          since they were uttered in the Spanish language.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e287">
          Add that most often our people did not begin their legation from words but from blows.
          And truly it is quite foolish to think that those peoples would believe or have faith,
          even if they understood the words,
          in such hard,
          scandalous,
          and disturbing words from men whom they saw armed with horrible arms 
          and with terrible bearing:
          whom also experience had taught them,
          either in themselves or in their neighbors,
          to be impious,
          cruel,
          inhuman and full of every kind of vice and filled with all iniquity and injustice.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e329">
          And although the Spaniards should wish to prove that peacefully through some law:
          nevertheless they would not find it.
          Because it cannot be shown to them by natural law,
          that is of nations,
          nor by divine law that they are obligated to do it.
          But rather all laws support and save these people and condemn the Spaniards.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e349">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Concerning natural law it is evident:
          because provinces which have been accustomed to be ruled by their kings and princes,
          as those peoples are and are ruled:
          are said to be under their natural dominion,
          that is by the law of nations 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e364">l. ex hoc iure ff. de iustitia et iure</ref> 
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e369">above § 6</ref> 
          appeared sufficiently proved.
          Whence rather those peoples and nations can prove by the authority of natural law 
          and the law of nations:
          that the Spaniards are tyrants who invaded their kingdoms contrary to natural law:
          concerning which there is no doubt to anyone who has been of sound mind 
          that we have been tyrants in those lands and today are:
          since we have despoiled the natural kings under whose natural dominion all were:
          and all inhabitants of their natural liberty for no other cause 
          except that we were stronger,
          indeed more unfortunate than they,
          and therefore now we are unjust possessors and very violent.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e401">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Nor can it be proved to them by divine law.
          Indeed they can in defense 
          <pb ed="#B" n="82-r"/>
          of their right:
          allege against us and our wicked invasion and detention of foreign kingdoms 
          that very divine law itself.
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For divine law of the new law,
          just as it is not found to have derogated from natural law or the law of nations,
          but rather to have established them according to that passage in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e424">Matthew 5</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Qd1e426" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt5_17@9-13">
            I came not to destroy the law but to fulfill it
          </quote>:
          so it did not establish anew that those peoples should be subjected to some foreign prince,
          with the prior and natural ones dismissed without fault.
          Indeed in their dominions,
          jurisdictions,
          estates,
          and dignities they were by that law confirmed and established as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e449">
            § 6 was most extensively proved in the 1st consideration
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e444">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But you expect,
          as I presume,
          what I should say concerning human law.
          For nothing to the point concerning civil law,
          since it does not bind them,
          for it binds those who exist in the same city or kingdom where it was established as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e455" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e5493-d1e110">
            C. de emancipationibus l. 1.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e462">
          But it remains to speak concerning canon and ecclesiastical Law.
          For nothing to us concerning 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Qd1e466" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor5_12@4-9">
            judging those who are outside
          </quote> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e469">1 Corinthians 5</ref> 
          Whence they are not bound by canonical constitutions 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e482">c. gaudemus de diuor.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e474">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But whether the Supreme Vicar of Christ who is above all laws could deprive the kings 
          of those peoples of their kingdoms,
          dignities and jurisdictions and dominions without cause 
          (certainly saving his reverence,
          obedience and final definition) 
          he neither does nor ever did,
          nor will do,
          unless for clear and manifest and most urgent and necessary cause,
          which here is entirely lacking,
          as above 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e510">
            § 8 in the 4th consideration you have had determined by most extensive disputation
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e500">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore by no law has it hitherto been proved or shown to the kings or peoples of the Indies:
          nor could we even if we wished and strove with all our might prove:
          that they would be obligated to recognize our kings as universal princes:
          but with frivolous and ridiculous words:
          indeed most scandalous and efficacious for moving,
          exasperating and inciting their spirits:
          to anger and implacable hatred against the Christian religion 
          and for disturbing that entire world with unheard of confusion (namely) 
          that those kingdoms had been transferred to our nation,
          to them at first sight 
          <pb ed="#B" n="82-v"/>
          horrible and insolent in appearance,
          they took care to extort obedience from them,
          not omitting terrible threats.
          Therefore by this reason,
          namely:
          that it has been proved to the kings or inhabitants or dwellers of that world 
          that they are obligated to recognize our kings as universal lords:
          it cannot be understood that any of them,
          either King or peoples,
          voluntarily received or recognized the same kings of Spain as superiors,
          or rendered obedience to them or to any of theirs sent hither and thither,
          but rather the contrary.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e556">
          Therefore the kings and peoples and all other inhabitants of the Indies remain by right 
          in that state of liberty and integrally of their right in which they were before,
          notwithstanding the institution of our kings as supreme princes by the Pope.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e565">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second thing which was required so that the peoples of the Indies might rightly 
          and correctly recognize our Kings as lords and universal princes was:
          that of their own accord and by free consent they should receive them,
          without reason being rendered or demonstration of right,
          but persuaded by good reasons or induced by gifts.
          But nor by this will it be proved that they received them or held the said papal institution as valid.
          The reason for which is that the Spaniards always began their legation (as was done) 
          from sudden,
          wicked and unexpected violence and invasion.
          For at the beginning of the discovery of that world and of any part of it,
          they never entered those kingdoms and lands except as enemies,
          invading hostilely and occupying the boundaries of the lands and kingdoms of such peoples:
          killing,
          slaughtering,
          capturing,
          plundering,
          devastating all things with slaughters,
          fires,
          rapines such as were never before seen or heard of in the entire world:
          sparing no sex,
          no age,
          no dignity,
          estate or even order.
          And after the greatest and most cruel slaughters,
          of which they perpetrated more and very many intentionally and deliberately.
          Savagely so that they might cast their fear into the hearts of the inhabitants 
          (besides the fact that by their very nature such peoples are wonderfully timid,
          being naked and unarmed and inexperienced in the terrible fury and terror of our arms 
          and horses) 
          namely lest it should be permitted to them further even to think or aspire to thinking 
          <pb ed="#B" n="83-r"/>
          about their miserable and unhappy state and about their liberation at some time.
          They led moreover those of them who in any way escaped their cruel sword,
          innumerable,
          great and small,
          kings and subjects,
          lords and subordinates,
          into horrible,
          most foul and perpetual servitude in which it was not permitted even to lift their eyes to heaven.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e666">
          Behold what beginning our people held.
          Behold what kind of entry theirs was when they arrived at those Indian regions.
          Thus they began,
          thus they continued,
          and thus even to the present day they have continued what was impiously perpetrated by them.
          And in this state all peoples of this kind always have been and now are:
          nor has the exactor,
          indeed the cruel killer,
          prodigal shedder of human blood,
          ceased for one day:
          nor has the tribute been quiet,
          the rod of the impious slept:
          nor has the rod of those unjustly dominating been taken away,
          striking the peoples,
          indeed extirpating and destroying the peoples with an incurable wound:
          subjecting the nations in fury,
          persecuting cruelly as was foretold in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-Rd1e712">Isaiah 14</ref>.
          Which indeed they have suffered and continuously and incessantly now in many places 
          of the Indies from us,
          whom they had never offended or harmed,
          those peoples to be lamented suffer,
          as this egregious and never heard of crime has now been spread throughout the entire world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e712">
          Whence because of such crimes of our people,
          cruel insults,
          violences and iniquities in which they have always been involved:
          they did not take care to fulfill what especially they carried in the commands from our kings 
          (namely) 
          that sweetly,
          peacefully,
          amicably and by good works,
          with humble,
          gentle and gracious conduct they should induce and attract those nations 
          to the Christian religion and to devotion and love of our kings,
          prohibiting wars,
          oppressions,
          injustices and other grievances to be done to them.
          And therefore the inhabitants hearing nothing of this kind,
          but feeling the cruel swords of the Spaniards in their own bodies:
          enough care to them was to be occupied concerning their defense,
          which principally consisted in taking flight toward mountains and hiding places.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e769">
          Therefore they did not recognize nor do they recognize today voluntarily our kings as lords or superiors:
          <pb ed="#B" n="83-v"/>
          but rather as enemies and inhuman destroyers or extirpators of the entire human race.
          The consequence is evident:
          because the deeds done by our people,
          the messengers of our kings,
          against them (which are not the works of a just or legitimate king:
          but of a dire tyrant and diabolical man:
          or rather of irrational beasts,
          indeed of demons) 
          they think and rightly indeed that they are done with the consent,
          command and will of our kings:
          when however in truth our kings never thought to command or permit such things,
          but always strenuously prohibited them by very many letters and actual mandates,
          of some of which we are eyewitnesses.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e466-d1e803">
          Therefore how could those peoples,
          placed in such estimation,
          voluntarily consent to the said papal institution or accept our kings as supreme lords,
          with such savagely oppressing tyrants?
          Behold the great service (concerning which they themselves boast much everywhere) 
          which they offered to their kings of Spain (namely) 
          to defame them wickedly among all those nations:
          which without doubt (as I said) judge that all those evils are perpetrated 
          with the consent and command of the kings of Spain.
          And what is more lamentable:
          they have made the name of our Savior to stink through all those parts of so vast a world:
          and also have always provided matter so that they may hold the Catholic faith 
          in perpetual hatred and blaspheme and abhor the religion of Christians.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>