<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 40</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 40</title>
          <date when="2025-12-18">December 18, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
          John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
      url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-18" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="111-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Hd1e97">Section 40</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e99">
          § <sic>39<!-- but actual 40 --></sic>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e108">
          Indeed concerning the things predetermined above,
          we still must consider that while our kings are and will be in the state of which 
          the fifth conclusion with its proofs treats:
          in two ways they can conduct themselves by right (whatever today is done in fact) 
          concerning the condition of power and jurisdiction which (as we said) they have. 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e126">
          In one way with respect to the inhabitants of the aforesaid world 
          who now are already initiated in the sacred mysteries,
          and in another way with respect to those who have not yet become Christians. 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e135">
          And indeed with respect to the inhabitants who have already received the faith 
          and are baptized,
          who are now within the Church and subject to the Roman Pontiff as regards spiritual matters:
          so that he has over them jurisdiction fully in habit:
          and consequently it seems that Christ's vicar through that condition 
          transferred it through the said institution insofar as of this kind into our kings,
          as he constituted them his delegates,
          because he could concede to them what he had of which they are capable,
          and all things that were necessary for the expedition 
          or explanation of the preaching of the Gospel 
          and the conversion and maintenance in the faith received of the inhabitants:
          as is proved through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e172">
          c. preterea de officio delegati cum sua materia</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e174">
          l. 2 ff. de iurisdictione omnium</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e179">
          l. qui procuratorem dat ff. de procuratoribus</ref>.
          Therefore our kings have that condition fully purified at present 
          as regards the aforesaid explanation.
          Hence care befalls our kings through the provision,
          presentation and sending of prelates,
          preachers and other ministers of the Church to preserve those in the faith received 
          and to do other things which are of voluntary jurisdiction,
          that is of the voluntary forum without any coercion. 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e192">
          And since they already have subjects there in habit by reason of the aforesaid:
          they can subdelegate,
          and our kings can have in habit over some of those who are newly made Christians,
          namely that they of their own kind exhort others 
          who have not yet put on Christ through faith and baptism to receive the Christian faith.
          While others may persevere in the good begun 
          and similar other things which are of voluntary jurisdiction.
          For our Kings can subdelegate them as delegates of the prince,
          that is of the supreme vicar of Christ,
          because simply they have from law that they can delegate,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e218">
          c. Pastoralis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e220">
          c. fi. de officio delegati</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e222">
          c. cum causam que de appellationibus</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e227">
          C. de indiciis l. a iudice</ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e229">
          C. qui pro sua iurisdictione l. unica.</ref> 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e235">
          ¶ But if the kings or natural lords should permit by their own good pleasure 
          some or any of the Spanish to remain in the territory of their jurisdiction and dominion:
          our Catholic kings will be able to commit or delegate the same to them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e249">
          But concerning sins of those already converted to the faith which are to be punished,
          whatever and however grave they may be,
          or committed against their republics or against particular or private persons,
          it does not pertain to our kings to care for,
          nor can they commit or delegate from defect of coercive or contentious jurisdiction,
          that is of the contentious forum:
          since they do not have the exercise of royal power:
          until those peoples and nations submit themselves to their rule 
          by their own and free consent,
          approving and accepting the aforesaid papal institution,
          as has been abundantly proved in the above.
          For those nations have their own and proper judges,
          kings and magistrates,
          with full jurisdiction and royal power:
          with whom they stand or fall. 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Qd1e275" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom14_4@1-12">
          You (says the Apostle) who are you who judge another's servant.
          To his own lord he stands or falls</quote> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e282">
          to the Romans 14</ref>.
          For they must judge concerning them,
          unless they are prevented in fact by the Spanish.
          But because the supreme vicar of Christ by the authority of his apostleship 
          can correct and punish any mortal sin of any Christian,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e295">
          c. nouit de iudiciis</ref> 
          cum sua materia.
          Therefore I would think it could be said not absurdly that in the case 
          where the kings and magistrates of the Indians should neglect 
          the punishment of public crimes in their communities:
          our kings could reduce that condition to act,
          not by their own but by apostolic authority,
          punishing those crimes with reasonable and pious exhortation first to their Kings 
          that they punish them.
          However because we suppose our kings to be by right through their ambassadors 
          outside their own territory,
          indeed to exist in another's namely of those peoples (as has been shown many times),
          therefore they can delegate that temporal condition 
          pertaining to the pope in such a case to some of the already converted 
          or of the Spanish in the manner and reason said according to those things which in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e325">
          § 30</ref> 
          were determined,
          but in this article it must be especially guarded against scandal 
          which can easily arise from this license 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e332">
          1 to Corinthians 8</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e334">
          to Romans 14</ref>,
          but all things should be weighed according to what will be said immediately.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e339">
          ¶ But voluntary jurisdiction is that which is rendered only among the willing,
          because through it they cannot be coerced unless they wish,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e349">
          l. omnes, ff. de officio proconsulis</ref> 
          and noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e351">
          c. per venerabilem extra qui filii sint legitimi</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e357">
          c. sicut extra ne clerici vel monachi</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e362">
          c. nouit. de officio legati</ref> 
          and it extends to foreigners provided that they consent,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e368">
          C. De emancipationibus liberorum l. 1</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e373">
          c. fi. de feriis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e376">
          bartholus and baldus and others super d. l. omnes</ref>,
          Whose acts are to adopt,
          to emancipate,
          to enter into contracts etc. in which cognition of the cause is not required,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e385">
          C. de feriis l. actus</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e388">
          ¶ But if it should happen that these sometimes decline from the faith received (which may it not be),
          when ecclesiastical judges request the aid of the secular arm:
          our Kings can and should lead that condition in a certain way to act,
          indeed they are bound to bring help:
          not indeed as judges having jurisdiction in act,
          but as ministers of the Catholic Church in favor of the faith.
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e409">
          c. excommunicamus el. 2o § <sic>moneam<!--moneantur,--></sic> de hereticis</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e416">
          c. presidentes eo titulo lib. 6</ref> 
          with those noted there,
          where it is evident that secular power,
          even if it does not have jurisdiction except in fact:
          is bound at the requisition of ecclesiastical judges against heretics 
          to furnish its power. 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e429">
          ¶ Moreover with respect to those inhabitants of that world 
          who have not yet professed the name of Christ,
          from this kind of condition,
          since our kings do not have it at present purified,
          that is perfected:
          nothing at all befalls the royal highness to act concerning their sins,
          however grave,
          whether of idolatry or unnatural acts which within the boundaries 
          of their infidelity they commit or are found to have committed:
          except to provide as diligently as possible that through the teaching 
          and examples of good men who first do what they teach:
          they may be illuminated so that with divine grace assisting they may be led to Christ:
          if however they wish to hear the word of life voluntarily.
          But if they are unwilling they cannot be compelled to hear:
          but the dust should be shaken from the feet over them 
          according to the form which Christ ordained and commanded in his Gospel in preaching.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e470">
          ¶ For by this way which Christ followed and the form which he used 
          and whoever were his true disciples,
          the whole world which was in darkness and in the filth of all evils 
          and indeed the worst:
          saw a great light and left its crimes.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e484">
          ¶ But if perhaps meanwhile it should come to the notice of our kings 
          that some of these infidels kill the innocent either for sacrificing to their gods 
          or that they kill them for eating as Anthropophagi (that is) feeding on human corpses 
          (for if they eat those already dead or by plague or captured in war or otherwise:
          nothing pertains to the royal highness concerning those who are outside),
          certainly in this kind of case:
          Our Kings should strive by all possible peaceful ways to show them 
          what a grave evil they commit,
          and to persuade them with gracious words and examples many times and again 
          that they leave off such things at least gradually.
          But if they should pertinaciously refuse to cease from such things,
          moderate force can be brought against them.
          Not indeed that they punish them for those crimes 
          nor subject them to themselves as slaves:
          since this is not properly war but a certain defense:
          just as private persons can against those oppressing themselves and bringing them aid.
          Since from the defect of power and jurisdiction which our kings do not have 
          except in habit,
          not yet fully with respect to those infidels who have not received the faith,
          as has been proved often:
          they cannot punish them:
          because again nothing to us concerning the crimes of infidels 
          committed within their infidelity and district: 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e536">
          1 To Corinthians 5</ref>.
          But insofar as they bring aid to the oppressed 
          and only liberate those who suffer injury.
          As we have proved most extensively in book 2 concerning the one way of calling 
          all peoples to the true religion and in the first part of the apology 
          both in the Spanish idiom and in Latin we have written.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e550">
          ¶ However concerning this case two things must be much observed by our kings:
          One that namely under the pretext of such crimes 
          or of freeing the innocent from unjust death:
          the inexplicable cupidity of having of wicked men (who always seek occasions) 
          may not falsely feign what is not true in the reality of the matter:
          so that they seek opportunity for seizing the goods of the Indians 
          and subjecting their persons to themselves.
          Which tyrants and robbers strive with all effort;
          and has been most frequent hitherto in those western lands.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e577">
          ¶ The other is that before that force is brought,
          it should be most exactly weighed:
          whether more innocents who have committed no such thing will be killed in war 
          if it is moved against them:
          than those whom they strive to liberate from destruction.
          Or even if the scandal which it is necessary to arise from such a fight preponderates,
          so that the faith is rendered hateful to the peoples 
          and an obstacle is made to preaching by the liberation of the few 
          who may at length be liberated from the hand of the cruel.
          Then indeed from such a way of liberating the innocents 
          one should certainly cease by divine precept and dissemble with them:
          since such an act would be vicious,
          existing against the rule of reason which says that the lesser evil 
          should be chosen both in one and the same person and in many and diverse:
          both in evils of fault and of punishment,
          as is evident through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e608">
          the philosopher 2 Ethics c. 9</ref> 
          from 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e610">
          3o ethics c. 5</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e615">
          5o c. 6</ref> 
          and elsewhere it is evident also through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e617">
          c. duo mala</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e622">
          c. sequenti nota. 13 dist.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e624">
          14 dist. c. 1o</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e626">
          22, q. 4, c. non solum</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e631">
          l. 1 § penultimo ff. de periculo et commodo rei uendite</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e634">
          ¶ For it is a lesser evil truly without comparison to permit 
          some to suffer innocently and to be unjustly killed by idolaters and Anthropophagi,
          than that we for rescuing them from unjust death should accomplish 
          through cruel wars (which are called and are a calamity of the human race) 
          the greatest slaughters of men,
          among whom indeed thousands of thousands of innocents it is necessary also to be slain.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e657">
          ¶ For not all are those who feed on human flesh:
          even where men are infected with this vice,
          nor did all or always immolate human victims to idols:
          but very few with respect to those who did not do such things or do them.
          From which would undoubtedly follow another maximum evil,
          namely that the name of Christ would be horrible and most hateful 
          to hear for that whole world:
          and also the Christian religion will be deemed cruel and unjust,
          therefore it will be better and holier and thus more eligible 
          to permit the few innocent to perish,
          dissembling the crimes of the killers,
          than that for liberating them we kill thousands of thousands of innocents. 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e686">
          ¶ This consequence is proved from the rule which the redeemer of the world 
          himself established for us:
          Matthew 13 in the parable concerning the weeds growing amid the wheat.
          Hence Saint Thomas speaking of this kind in diverse places says:
          that: the Lord commanded that one should abstain from rooting out the weeds 
          lest the wheat be spared,
          that is the good.
          Which indeed is done when the evil cannot be killed 
          unless at the same time the good are killed,
          either because they are hidden among the good:
          or because they have many followers:
          so that without danger of the good they cannot be killed,
          as Augustine says against Permenian.
          Hence the Lord teaches that it is better to allow the evil to live 
          and vengeance to be reserved until the final judgment:
          than that the good be killed at the same time etc.
          these things Saint Thomas upon the said parable and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e745">
          2. 2o q. 1o article 8, ad 1m</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e747">
          22. q. 64. article 2 ad primum</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e749">
          4 distinction 13 question 2 article 3o ad 3</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e754">
          3 contra gen c. 146</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e757">
          quodlibet 10 article 15 ad 1m</ref> 
          and in many other places.
          Very many laws reason similarly to the aforesaid 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e762">
          c. denique, 14, q. 5</ref>, 
          where 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e764">
          Ambrose</ref> 
          says: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Qd1e723">
          if one cannot be helped unless the other is harmed,
          it is better that neither be helped than that one be burdened etc</quote>. 
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e735">
          And for this makes that which very many laws have.
          For they prohibit exercising rigor or vengeance 
          when the delinquents cannot be precisely distinguished from those who are not culpable,
          lest the innocent unjustly suffer.
          And as often as they are reasonably believed to be likely to perish more than are those 
          to whom we strive to bring help.
          Which in war is always not doubted to happen.
          these are evident. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e796">
          23, q. 4, c. non potest</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e798">
          1. q. 7. c. Quotiens, el. 2o</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e803">
          de temporibus ordinatio c. 2, and 23, q. 5, c. ipsa pietas</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e808">
          9, q. 1 c. ordinationes</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e811">
          50 dist. c. ut constituerentur</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e816">
          44 dist. c. comensationes</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e818">
          4 dist. c. denique</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e760">
          ¶ Outside this kind of case nothing befalls our kings (as we said) 
          except to occupy themselves concerning those things which in the 2nd conclusion are included:
          and are preparatory for their principality or for having the principality in act,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e771">
          above § 30</ref> 
          it was proved.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e774">
          ¶ And although it is said in the above that one having power or jurisdiction 
          in habit can subdelegate it:
          however with those infidels who never received the faith nor heard 
          or committed any fault against the Church,
          our kings cannot subdelegate by the things said above,
          namely because neither the Church nor the supreme pontiff have power 
          or jurisdiction in habit at present purified,
          that is perfected,
          as long as they do not come to the faith voluntarily:
          and consequently they do not have there subjects to whom they can commit a cause 
          or delegate.
          According to those things which are read and noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e799">
          c. pastoralis, § quoniam autem de rescriptis</ref> 
          and many laws in the preceding alleged,
          therefore neither can our kings do or delegate these things.
          For what the first cause which has to influence into the second cannot,
          much less can the second,
          taking the argument from the greater power of the efficient cause.
          And taking the argument from the effect of the efficient cause,
          as baldus argues in a similar way in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e819">
          l. cunctos populos C. de summa trinitate</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e825">
          ¶ Furthermore concerning this kind of infidels only does the supreme vicar 
          of Christ obtain power or jurisdiction which jurists call voluntary 
          or similar to voluntary.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e837">
          Which is evident first thus.
          Because since principally the power of the Church and of its head 
          and the chief act of power through which the building or construction 
          of the Church began consists in the preaching of the faith 
          and the gathering of the faithful from infidels. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e847">
          To Ephesians 2</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e850">
          to Romans 10</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e852">
          c. cum ex iniuncto de hereticis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e857">
          de statu monachorum c. quod dei timorem</ref>.
          And this ought to be sweet and persuasive to the intellect 
          and alluring to the will:
          showing charity and benevolence so that men may be moved voluntarily 
          and incited to hear and receive the word of God and thus the Catholic faith itself,
          because to believe is an act of the will which it is impossible to coerce:
          it follows that this kind of ecclesiastical power of preaching the Gospel 
          can be called voluntary jurisdiction or to be similar to voluntary jurisdiction.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e876">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          2nd it is evident and better because since to adopt someone as a son who is not a son 
          but a stranger or foreigner is an act of voluntary jurisdiction,
          as it were art imitates nature (For adoption or adoptio is of a foreign person 
          as a son or grandson or thereafter a gratuitous and legitimate assumption:
          or as we may say more fully for the purpose abrogation which is a species of adoption 
          and perfectly imitates natural filiation through which the adoptee is reduced 
          into the power of the adopter voluntarily however:
          because unless the adoptee voluntarily receives,
          the adoption is not valid,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e908">l. necque ff. De adoptionibus</ref>.
          And therefore the adoptee succeeds the adopting father intestate etc. 
          in the end de adoptionibus § femine in the gloss. 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e919">
            S. Thomas, in 4 sententiarum dist. 42 q. 2, articulo 1o</ref>.
          And infidels of this kind are foreign persons and foreigners:
          because they are totally outside the Church and its forum,
          nor subjects as regards coercive or contentious jurisdiction which is exercised 
          against the unwilling,
          as something was touched upon above near the end of § 30 and in our apology 
          and in our other treatises most extensively proved it is evident:
          it follows that if they are to be adopted as sons of God,
          this is to be done through faith of Jesus Christ by receiving the most holy 
          sacrament of baptism according to that 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e945">ad Romanos 8</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Qd1e950" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom8_15@10-18">
            you have received the spirit of adoption of sons of God: in which we cry abba father</quote>:
          and therefore voluntarily:
          so that they themselves freely without any coercion or violence wish to be adopted 
          as sons of God (that is) wish to be Christians according to that 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e960">ioannis 1.</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Qd1e963" source="http://scta.info/resource/io1_12@5-16">
            he gave them the power to become sons of God: to those who believe in his name</quote> 
          (that is) he left them in the power of free will so that if they wish they may become 
          sons of God by believing in him etc.
          For if they were unwilling and forced to believe the adoption would not be valid.
          And this is what Ambrose says: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Qd1e979">Christ chose a voluntary soldier</quote>: 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e981">15, q. 1, c. non est</ref>. 
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e984">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore this power of the Church or of the supreme pontiff of drawing 
          and inviting and persuading the infidels that they wish to be adopted 
          and to be sons of God through faith and reception of the sacrament of faith 
          namely baptism:
          and thus to enter the Church or to be numbered among the faithful who are 
          the inheritance of God has its foundation in the liberty and voluntary acceptance 
          of the free will of the infidels themselves supposing the grace of God as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Rd1e1005">
            s. Thomas docet: 3 par. q. 8, articulo 3o ad primum</ref> 
          saying that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-Qd1e1010">
            those who are infidels even if in act they are not of the Church are nevertheless 
            of the ecclesiastical power.
            Which power indeed is founded in two things.
            First indeed and principally in the virtue of Christ which is sufficient for 
            the salvation of the whole human race.
            Second in the liberty of free will</quote> 
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e585-d1e1033">
          It follows that this kind of power or jurisdiction of the Church which can regularly 
          extend itself to infidels who never either received or heard the faith is a power 
          or voluntary jurisdiction or similar to that which jurists call voluntary.
          And this very thing could be delegated and committed by the pope to the kings 
          and by the kings to other suitable ministers of the Church:
          since it is nothing other than to move,
          to command,
          to order or to exhort that peacefully,
          gently,
          benevolently,
          charitably and by example those peoples may be led and drawn to the faith.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>