<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 17</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 17</title>
          <date when="2025-11-14">November 14, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-14" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="46-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Hd1e97">Section 17</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e99">
          § 17
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e104">
          Thirdly the same first consequence is proved:
          whenever a free man and more forcefully a free people or community must be obligated 
          to undertake some burden or to pay some debt,
          and generally when there is a question of prejudice especially of many:
          it is necessary that all whom the matter touches be summoned 
          and free consent be obtained from them,
          otherwise nothing that is done will be valid.
          As will be evident below.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e117">
          But if our King of Spain were imposed upon those nations and their princes as king 
          and universal lord either by right or in fact:
          they would be obligated,
          at least civilly as regards the judicial forum or human judgment,
          to a most grave burden and to paying an intolerable debt:
          namely to recognize as king and lord:
          a man indeed unknown to them,
          a king of another foreign nation and therefore very much suspect,
          to render subjection,
          obedience,
          reverence,
          tributes,
          services,
          new taxes and other royal rights which would that they did not grow day by day,
          like sea foam,
          indeed not like a flame rising from earth to heaven burning 
          and devouring all things.
          Whence it is a question of incomparable and perhaps irreparable damage.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e152">
          Therefore it is necessary that all kings and all peoples of those nations be summoned 
          and their free consent be awaited and obtained from them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e160">
          But they will never give this consent,
          at least not freely (which quality is necessarily required).
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e167">
          Therefore so that it may be obtained from them,
          it is necessary that they be persuaded and induced by good reasons:
          and by pleasing,
          sweet and honeyed inducements.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e174">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The Minor is plain.
          The consequence with the Major is proved:
          first because it is known in law that those who are to be summoned or called are all 
          whom the business 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e183" source="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1612-d1e309@3-7">
            touches,
            it must be approved by all
          </quote>.
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e187">De regulis iuris libro 6.</ref> 
          Namely all those who are harmed or whose right is diminished:
          or to whom prejudice is done. 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e192">
            To whom power has been given by natural and divine and human law 
            of consenting or contradicting
          </quote> 
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e199">Baldus says in l. nam ita divus, ff. de adoptione</ref>.
          Which is understood according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e203">Innocent and all in c. cum omnes de constitutionibus</ref> 
          when something is common to many as to members of a college or as to one body.
          But as to individuals or concerning a singular right.
          For then it is necessary that individuals know and consent,
          otherwise what is done by many is not valid unless all consent,
          whether together or separately according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e214">
            Innocent ff. de seruitutibus rusticorum prediorum l. per fundum
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e220">
          And according to 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Nd1e222">Baldus</name> 
          this distinction is proved in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e224" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t2-Dd1e184">
            d. c. cum omnes
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e229" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e137-d1e176">
            l. in tantum, § uniuersitatis ff de rerum diuisione
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e232" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e5159-d1e1870">
            ff. de regulis iuris l. aliud § refertur
          </ref> 
          where fully concerning this,
          as behold if many persons have a common estate and wish to establish a servitude 
          on the estate,
          the consent of all must intervene:
          otherwise the defect of one renders the constitution useless as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e247">
            ff. de seruitute rusticorum prediorum l receptum
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e250" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e3844-Dd1e270">
            d. l. si per fundum
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e253" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e3195-Dd1e330">
            ff de aqua pluvia arcende l. in concedendo
          </ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e257" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e3242-Dd1e147">
            C de autoritate prestanda l. ultima
          </ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e262">ff. de adoptione l. ita divus</ref> 
          where it is said that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e264" source="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e126-Dd1e545@28-31">
            those who are harmed,
            must be called in the confirmation of adoption.
          </quote> 
          If many have a servitude of drawing water from that fountain 
          and the lord wishes to grant to others with diminution of the right of the first:
          he will not be able unless with the consent of the first.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e274">
          Concerning these matters 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e286">Dynus in d. regula</ref>; 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e279">What touches all</quote> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e293">the gloss there</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e296">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Nd1e283">Innocent</name> 
            in d. c. cum omnes
          </ref> 
          de constitutionibus 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e301">Panormitanus and Felinus there</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e288">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And especially the summoning or citation and consent of all those 
          who claim to have some interest or fear future prejudice is required
          <pb ed="#B" n="47-r"/>
          whenever obedience or subjection and other royal rights are sought from any people or nation.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e303">
          For it is manifest that for this cause all,
          both the great,
          that is kings and lords,
          princes,
          nobles and magistrates or heads of cities and peoples:
          as well as the small and individuals must be summoned:
          and all and each must consent,
          otherwise nothing will be valid:
          whatever is done to the contrary.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e312">
          For if in granting the drawing of water all who have a right must be summoned 
          and in the confirmation of adoption because the right of each one 
          or of individuals is diminished and it is a question of the prejudice of individuals,
          as in the laws previously alleged:
          by how much stronger reason must they be summoned and from them,
          great and small,
          voluntary consent be sought,
          of all whose right is so diminished that peoples and princes existing free 
          and recognizing no superior,
          kings,
          princes and subjects,
          great and small,
          lose their beloved freedom,
          are obligated to obedience,
          to perpetual subjection,
          to reverence,
          tributes and other royal rights to be paid.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e335">
          For all,
          great and small,
          that is princes and lords:
          and their peoples and subjects claim maximum interest.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e342">
          And as regards princes it is evident:
          because a temporal lord existing free,
          subject to no one:
          becomes in a certain way a servant.
          Likewise if his subjects are subjected to another lord's authority,
          his authority,
          dominion and power are diminished together with his advantage.
          Likewise his subjects are burdened with a double burden,
          indeed multiple.
          Which is contrary to natural reason.
          Whence he can and ought to oppose for the sake of preserving the right of his subjects.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e358">
          An excellent argument for this 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e360" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e578-Dd1e522">
            ff. de dolo l. cum quis
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e363" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t10-Dd1e123">
            extra de ordine cognitionum C. 2
          </ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e368" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t13-Dd1e108">
            de restitutione spoliatorum c. 1
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e371" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t28-Dd1e927">
            de appellationibus, c. dilectis
          </ref> 
          so much so that the lord himself can wage war against a temporal lord 
          oppressing the rights of his subject,
          if when requested he neglects or refuses to render justice concerning him,
          by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e400">capitulum dominus noster 23, q. 2</ref> 
          thus 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e402">Innocent and Hostiensis note in d. c. dilectis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e383">Hostiensis de treuga et pace c. 1</ref>.
          And this because it is to his interest that his subjects not be harassed 
          and that his jurisdiction not be violated nor his advantage diminished.
          Thus the Supreme Pontiff in the extravagant of John the First asserts 
          that he cannot ignore the losses of the Roman Church and his faithful:
          but that after they have been made known to him,
          he will take suitable remedies against them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e400">
          Whence a lord can reclaim his subject held by another 
          so that he may undertake personal services 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e429">l. de iure ff. ad municipia</ref> 
          concerning which the 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e434">
            gloss in l. 1 § per hanc ff. de rei uendicatione
          </ref>
          <pb ed="#B" n="47-v"/>
          and the lord will reclaim his ascripticius 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e443">c. 2 de iudiciis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e445">gloss in cap. autoritate de priuilegiis lib. 6</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e415">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Nd1e416">Panormitanus</name> 
            in c. dilecti de appellationibus circa prin.
          </ref>.
          Likewise anyone can act for the diminution of his patrimony.
          And more easily someone receives his rights in a free and vacant thing 
          than from one possessed by another.
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e425" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t13-d1e392">
            c. fine de restitutione spoliatorum
          </ref>.
          The things noted by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e431">Innocent in c. veniens de testibus</ref>, 
          and by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e433">Bartholus in l. a Diuo pio ff. de re iudicata</ref> 
          apply.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e440">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But it is in the interest of subjects that their lord be free and not subject himself to another:
          lest they be compelled to have multiple lords.
          Likewise just as it is in the interest of the lord not to change his subject:
          so it is in the interest of the subject not to change his lord and to be subjected to a foreigner.
          And especially if it happens that he is of another language or nation:
          because such are wont to be little affectionate toward subjects 
          nor do they care much about them.
          As will be evident below.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e462">
          Concerning these matters 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e501">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Nd1e464">Hostiensis</name> 
            in c. dilecti de maioritate et obedientia
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e508">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Nd1e468">Panormitanus</name> 
            there
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e513">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Nd1e470">Felinus</name>
          </ref> 
          and all,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e517">c. fine eo titulo</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e475">Innocent in c. auditis de prescriptionibus</ref> 
          It seems that if the lord of some place wishes to subject that place to a foreign lord:
          the men of that place can object according to all in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e481" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t33-d1e362">
            D. c. fine de maioritate et obedentia
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e486">d. l. in tantum C, de appellationibus</ref> 
          the text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e489">
            d. l. imperialem, 
            in § preterea ducatus de probibita feudi alienatione per fredericum collatio 10
          </ref> 
          applies,
          where it is particularly stated that the lord of a fief cannot transfer dominion to another 
          with the vassal unwilling:
          lest that vassal be compelled to have a foreign lord.
          And if the lord dies leaving many sons:
          the vassal is not bound to render the oath of fidelity to all but it suffices to one.
          Which is to be kept in mind according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e502">
            Panormitanus in d. c. dilecti de maioritate et obedientia
          </ref> 
          and according to him that saying of Hostiensis with the aforesaid allegations applies:
          so that the king cannot subject a castle or city subject to him to some inferior 
          with the men unwilling.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e511">Innocent in d. cap. auditis</ref>, 
          says that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e513">
            just as it is in the interest of the lord not to lose his vassal:
            so equally it is in the interest of subjects not to lose their lord
          </quote> 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e518">Which you should note well</quote>
          says 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e573">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Nd1e521">Panormitanus</name>
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e578">on the gloss together with the text in d. c. fine</ref> 
          that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e523">
            the lord cannot settle concerning the right of superiority to the prejudice of subjects:
            unless the subjects consent,
            for that reason,
            namely because it is in the interest of subjects not to have multiple lords 
            or not to change their lord as 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e593">d. l. imperialem</ref>
          </quote>.
          And from the reasoning of the gloss according to him
          <pb ed="#B" n="48-r"/>
          it can generally be gathered that wherever subjects can claim some interest,
          a settlement made by the lord alone will not be valid with the subjects not consenting 
          (and it can be added) or coerced into consent.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e545">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Behold how it is in the interest both of all subjects and of lords 
          that in the question or cause of rendering subjection:
          and of admitting someone as lord as superior,
          of obligating themselves to undertaking the burden and most grave burdens 
          which follow thereupon:
          it is necessarily required that all be summoned and from all be required 
          and obtained free consent,
          since this matter or cause touches all and each,
          and consequently by all and each it ought to be approved.
          Otherwise without doubt what is done will have no validity.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e581">
          This is evident beyond the laws introduced above by the chapter inter quatuor 
          de maioritate et obedentia:
          where the Pope rejects the petition of a certain patriarch of Constantinople 
          seeking to have certain churches of the regions subjected to him,
          those concerned not having been cited,
          because where obedience and subjection are at issue:
          nothing ought to be attempted to the prejudice of the matter or of the possessor 
          not cited.
          Where the text says 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e594">
            for the reason of law demands that to the prejudice of those to whom they are subject 
            of the same church,
            we ordain nothing concerning it since neither have they been cited nor convicted
          </quote> 
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e605">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          In which chapter Innocent and other doctors after him also say that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Qd1e612">
            we would sin if we should seek obedience or subjection from some people 
            while they are subjected to others,
            and we are to be punished even if they should spontaneously subject themselves to us
          </quote>.
          He alleges capitulum placuit 16 q 13
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e622">
          And the reason for this is because meanwhile we commit theft and violence 
          and injury to another possessor:
          until the cause is known judicially and the authority of law properly interposed:
          and also those same subjects sin by withdrawing obedience from the possessor 
          unless they are first absolved from his obedience.
          Which cannot be done if that one to whom they now obey is not present:
          and because action has not been taken against him in a just judgment according to Innocent 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e696">
            Baldus in d. c. inter quatuor argumentum 8 q. ultima c. nonne
          </ref> 
          and it is noted by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e700">the same Innocent and others in d. c. auditis</ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e702">
            Baldus alleges to the aforesaid ff. de adquirenda hereditate l. Iuste
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e643">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore this matter of receiving our King of Spain as universal lord 
          touches all those nations of the Indies,
          not only kings and princes,
          peoples,
          provinces,
          cities,
          municipalities,
          and places:
          but truly also each individual person of any province,
          city,
          municipality and place:
          namely it is necessary
          <pb ed="#B" n="48-v"/>
          that all and each be obligated to undertaking the greatest burden 
          and paying great debts,
          to lose or at least greatly diminish,
          even if matters,
          the government with them,
          are conducted rightly and prosperously,
          their own freedom,
          both of kings and princes as well as of peoples and individual inhabitants:
          which indeed it is more probable they will totally lose 
          than that they should enjoy the smallest part of freedom 
          (which indeed most certainly is,
          indeed has been and now is as the outcome of the matter has proved and proves),
          rendering subjection,
          obedience,
          reverence and multiple royal rights:
          and consequently it is a question of their maximum prejudice because all will be harmed 
          and the right of all of them is diminished.
          And since they exist free,
          the power and faculty of consenting and contradicting is given to them 
          by natural law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e695">
          Therefore all,
          both great and small,
          all peoples and individual persons are to be summoned 
          and from all of them free consent is to be sought and obtained.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e704">
          But this consent,
          at least free,
          which quality,
          that is freedom,
          is necessarily required,
          they will never give,
          as is evident.
          Therefore so that free consent may be obtained from them,
          it is necessary that they be persuaded by good reasons,
          pleasing,
          sweet and honeyed inducements.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e714">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          That freedom in rendering consent is necessarily required as a necessary quality is proved 
          by a very notable text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e789">c. ubi periculum § coeterum de electione lib. 6</ref> 
          where it is said that election ceases where freedom of electing is admitted.
          Where the word freedom is to be weighed,
          therefore in the election or acceptance of any future superior or ruler 
          by free persons,
          the free consent of electing or accepting is required.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e735">
          If therefore consent is present without the quality of freedom,
          that is not election,
          like carnal marriage as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e808">c. cum locum</ref> 
          and what is noted there de sponsalibus and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e812">gloss in c. quisquis. de electionibus</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e742">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e822">Bartholus in tractatu de tyrano</ref> 
          agrees:
          where he says that if a city having the election of a rector 
          and compelled by a tyrant should elect a Rector:
          the election would not be valid.
          Whence sentences issued by that rector would be null.
          For which 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e756" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e662-Dd1e114">
            l. 2 ff. de iudiciis
          </ref> 
          applies well.
          Where free consent is required in transferring and subrogating jurisdiction.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-d1e765">
          From which it is also inferred that if a tyrant should go to a free city with an army:
          and the city elects the tyrant as lord,
          transferring to him all jurisdiction:
          it is not valid
          <pb ed="#B" n="49-r"/>
          because it is done under such fear.
          And consequently the acts of such a tyrant will not be valid,
          which 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e853">Bartholus confirms in d. tractatu de tyrano</ref>.
          Add here what is noted by all in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e857">l. decernimus C. de sacrosanctis ecclesiis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e862">Calderini consilio primo</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e864">Ancharanus in consilio 300</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e282-Rd1e869">
            Panormitanus in c. licet de euitanda 10 columna de electione
          </ref>
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>