<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 36</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 36</title>
          <date when="2025-12-13">December 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
          </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
          John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
      url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="98-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Hd1e97">Section 36</head>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e99">
          § 36
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Concerning the first impediment (namely) war,
          something should be considered, 
          and indeed not with a slight consideration 
          (namely) that since the indigenous peoples of that Indian world,
          and indeed all of them,
          on account of our iniquities (as I have said) 
          and the evils that they have innocently suffered from us,
          have the right to wage war against us,
          not only defensive, 
          and for the recovery of their liberty and their dominions and possessions:
          but also for vengeance,
          even to the point of destroying their name from the earth inclusively:
          I say perpetual war) as was touched upon in the preceding §,
          and most extensively in a certain treatise of ours whose title is 
          "On the War of Jalisco."
          But we truly lack any right whatsoever to harm them in any way
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e137">
          from this follows a necessary consequence,
          that absolutely speaking,
          the Spanish who wish to kill those peoples through war,
          or to expel them from their lands,
          cannot defend themselves by war against them.
          Yet they could flee, 
          and in the best way they can,
          without harm or injury to the Indians pursuing them,
          withdraw themselves,
          and exit and leave the foreign land.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e153">
          The first point (namely) that they could not defend themselves is clear:
          first because by natural law those peoples waging just war against us Spaniards were:
          indeed they are our legitimate judges on account of our crimes,
          since the kings and natural lords and they themselves have complete jurisdiction,
          not recognizing a superior,
          as was proven above in § 5 and 6.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e173">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Against one's proper judge,
          however,
          it is not permitted to defend oneself when one is guilty:
          just as a thief or malefactor,
          although he can flee,
          yet without injury or harm to another.
          For Saint Thomas said, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1ex7a">2a 2e question 69 article 4</ref>
          that divine, natural, and human law 
          obliges anyone not to resist a judge proceeding justly.
          Hence one sins mortally by resisting legitimate authority,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e197">Romans 13</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Qd1e199" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_2@2-14">
          whoever resists authority resists the ordinance of God,
          and acquires damnation for himself
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e205">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly, it is proved,
          since the common rule of the jurists is in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e214">l. ut vim ff. de iustitia et iure</ref>
          that wherever an offense is permitted and lawful by law:
          there defense is denied.
          Just as, on the contrary,
          where offense is prohibited,
          defense is permitted and lawful,
          by argument from opposites.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e224">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore a criminal offends someone,
          and the judge, by natural law,
          and the law of nations,
          indeed by divine law is the avenger of that crime, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e233" target="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_2 http://scta.info/resource/rom13_3">
          Romans 13
          </ref>
          it follows that he cannot defend himself from the judge who wishes to punish him.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e239">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second point (namely) that such a delinquent can flee is proved,
          because according to St. Thomas,
          it is lawful for anyone to act for the protection of his own body:
          whatever he reasonably can,
          provided it is without prejudice to another.
          But when a malefactor is sought unto death,
          if he flees so as not to be found,
          or hides himself:
          he does not prejudice the judge,
          because he takes nothing away from his right,
          nor does he even offend when he is held by him and flees without striking him,
          he does not sin:
          because he does not offend him,
          because he acts with the intention of using that defense which is naturally permitted,
          since a natural desire is innate in man to preserve his life.
          For whoever acts through nature's inclination:
          if he does not act against any law,
          he does not sin.
          Hence defense is always lawful when it is done or exercised without prejudice to or 
          offense of anyone:
          and by so acting he does not resist authority,
          as appears from what has been said,
          therefore such a criminal can flee without sin.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e285">
          So it is with all the Spaniards who are in those regions of the Indians,
          because since they are truly aggressors or unjust invaders of foreign kingdoms,
          and properly tyrants,
          and the Indians wage just war against them in natural defense,
          and therefore carry the person of a judge proceeding criminally,
          it is not lawful for the Spaniards to defend themselves from them,
          by fighting, striking back,
          or killing,
          or harming them in any way:
          but they are bound in the best way they can to flee or hide themselves,
          so that they may save their own lives,
          indeed to depart entirely from the lands of the Indians:
          unless something else should stand in the way,
          about which I will speak immediately.
          And this is so lest they add sins to sins,
          by which their state has always been worse in malice:
          by attacking, subjugating,
          and utterly destroying innocent people,
          and very often those who deserved well of them.
          Therefore they sinned most gravely as often as they defended themselves 
          with injury or prejudice to the Indians.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e325">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          I said, unless something else should stand in the way:
          namely as regards departing from the land,
          because in some case they would not be bound to do so (namely) 
          on account of favor to the faith.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e336">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Indeed, if in some region some of the indigenous people have already been converted to God,
          they would not be bound to abandon that land entirely:
          but they would be bound to remain even with danger to their own life,
          for the sake of preserving the faith in those people,
          defending themselves,
          yet with the moderation of blameless defense.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e358">
          This is clear,
          because any Christian is bound by the necessity of salvation to defend and preserve 
          the faith of Christ,
          insofar as it is in him,
          namely when divine honor or the utility of one's neighbor would be endangered,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e368">St. Thomas teaches 2a 2e q. 3, article 3</ref>
          and elsewhere.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e371" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d96-Dd1e134">
          decretis 96. distinctione c. nos ad fidem
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e376">c. vbi nam legisti</ref>.
          But if the Spaniards were to abandon such a region entirely:
          undoubtedly the faith and divine honor would be endangered,
          and thence the utility and salvation of the souls of those Indians would perish,
          because perhaps,
          and without perhaps,
          those nations would not be well founded in those things which are of the faith,
          and because of the extreme detestation and implacable hatred which they bear 
          against the Spaniards:
          thinking that the religious or preachers of the faith are accomplices of the same 
          in the evils which they have suffered from them,
          they would kill them.
          Whence it seems probable that they would despise and reject the received faith,
          or little by little the faith in them would totally fail,
          for lack of teaching and exercise of the sacraments
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e408">
          therefore it would be illicit for the Spaniards,
          and they would sin mortally,
          by deserting such a region:
          to which otherwise,
          the cause of faith ceasing,
          they were obliged even by necessity of salvation,
          as has been said.
          For the favor of faith is preferred to all utilities and favors,
          on account of which many singular things have been introduced:
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e423">c. in fidei. favorem de hereticis lib. 6</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e428">2, quaestione 7, c. si hereticus</ref>.
          And what is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e440">c. Magne de voto</ref>
          likewise the utility of the Church of God and the salvation of souls.
          For there is no greater reason, or more favorable,
          than that which acts for religion,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e437" type="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e1121-Dd1e686">
          l. sunt persone ff. de religiosis et sumptibus funerum.
          </ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e443">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Nevertheless, this favor of faith and religion does not extend so far 
          that for the sake of preserving the faith and its ministers,
          and lest the faith be endangered:
          Christians can invade or become aggressors through war of the kingdoms and lands of peoples,
          living in peace, 
          and who have never attacked us or inflicted any evil or even the slightest thing upon us:
          especially since they rather wage just war against us 
          (as has been proven) 
          and indeed a war strengthened by such multiple right and full justice.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e466">
          This is proved,
          because evil things are not to be done that whatever good things may result:
          of whom (namely) those who do the contrary,
          their damnation is just.
          As 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e472" target="http://scta.info/resource/rom3_8">
          the Apostle teaches in Romans 3
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e475" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c30q1-Dd1e146">
          3 quaestione 1, c. nosse
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e479" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-Dd1e270">
          23. q. 4 c. forte
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e486" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c33q5-Dd1e112">
          33, q. 5, c. si dicat
          </ref>
          For it never pleases God that anyone sin mortally,
          indeed not even venially,
          for the sake of whatever good that could proceed from it,
          however much it may redound to the glory of God.
          Nay rather it greatly displeases God,
          because God does not want such profit to be compensated with such loss. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e497" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c33q5-Dd1e112">
          d. c. si dicat
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e503" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d14-Dd1e115">
          14 dist., c. quod ait
          </ref>.
          And no one is to be led to salvation with the help of a venial lie:
          how much less with mortal sin,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e516" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c22q2-Dd1e248">
          22, q. 2, c. Primum est
          </ref>;
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e520" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c22q2-Dd1e352">
          c. faciat homo
          </ref>
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e525">23, q. 5, c. cum nemo.</ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e530">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore, only for the favor of faith is it lawful for such men 
          (that is) for Spaniards constituted in such an article of necessity,
          by divine and human law,
          to protect themselves against the Indians,
          not in any manner whatsoever:
          but with the strict moderation of blameless defense,
          and to do that only to this extent,
          that which is contained within the bounds of merely natural defense,
          for preserving themselves and the bishops and religious or preachers of the faith 
          and other ministers of the Church,
          without injury, wrong,
          or harm voluntarily inflicted on the Indians.
          Which otherwise outside this case would be utterly denied to them by both laws:
          since all the Indian nations of that entire world always have the right to wage war,
          and wage just war against us Spaniards,
          as sufficiently appears from what has been said.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e569">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          From all of which can be gathered the clarity of that truth 
          which some turn into doubt (namely) whether the kings of Spain are bound to abandon 
          that world and the Spaniards to depart from it entirely:
          since they have used it so badly:
          both in entrance and tyrannical invasions:
          and in progress (that is) iniquitous,
          indeed impious government,
          and several reasons can be adduced for the affirmative part.
          But it must be said that our kings are not bound to abandon entirely the aforesaid world,
          except in a certain manner,
          nor are the Spaniards to depart from it:
          but rather by divine precept our kings are bound to retain those kingdoms perpetually:
          the Spaniards also are obliged by the same precept to remain.
          Unless some are so criminal and harmful to the Indians that by public edict 
          they should deservedly be condemned to perpetual exile from those lands.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e611">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Concerning the kings,
          and generally concerning all Spaniards indeed,
          it is clear by the common reason assigned above (namely) 
          because every Christian is bound to help, defend,
          and preserve the faith.
          Also by a particular reason as regards those who have inflicted evils on those peoples,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e640">below § 38 will be proved in corollary 2</ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e631">
          But concerning our kings in particular,
          it is manifest that they are obliged.
          Both because the universal care of that world was imposed on them by the vicar of Christ,
          and by virtue of necessary restitution and satisfaction,
          from the fact that they permitted so many unheard-of unjust evils to be inflicted 
          on innocent nations living in peace in their own lands and homes.
          Or because they did not prevent them when they could,
          by which nevertheless that entire world lies devastated.
          Also on account of the infinite weights of gold and silver and precious things 
          which have come to our kings from that world for nearly seventy years,
          of indeed incomparable price.
          About this again I will say something below.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e674">
          I said "except in a certain manner" because in truth the King of Spain,
          perpetually remaining in Spain:
          can in no way usefully govern that world without it going into devastation,
          as we see by sufficient evidence of fact.
          Since between him and the peoples of those nations,
          and on account of the magnitude of the regions, kingdoms,
          and provinces,
          there is known to be so great a distance of seas and lands,
          as we have proven by very many and urgent reasons in a certain work of ours,
          on not alienating wealth from the royal crown,
          nor selling public offices.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e698">
          And therefore our King is bound,
          and indeed by necessity of salvation,
          to leave that world in this manner (namely) 
          by establishing in each province or kingdom someone as king of royal blood:
          who being present may rightly provide for the government and utility of those kingdoms 
          and peoples,
          and may preserve, defend,
          and as far as possible exalt and extend the faith,
          as befits and is binding upon a truly Christian King.
          Having therefore from what has been predetermined that it is lawful for some Spaniards 
          to inhabit,
          indeed they are bound to inhabit and to choose a perpetual settlement in the Indian regions,
          in which (namely) some of the indigenous people have already been converted to the faith,
          yet without prejudice or injury to them voluntarily procured:
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e729">
          it follows that it is also lawful for them to gather themselves all together in some part 
          of the land or of such a province,
          in which the indigenous people are known to be less burdened,
          and first of all to build a tower with some concealment for their protection,
          and a colony or settlements.
          And there they should seek food for themselves,
          either by laboring with their own hands,
          or by exchange with the indigenous people themselves:
          which will be very easy if,
          with peace offered and kept inviolably,
          by good works and Christian examples and by some small gifts from Spain with all diligence,
          they should strive to placate them and to conciliate their minds to themselves.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e754">
          With these things indeed fully observed,
          the indigenous people of such a province will little by little begin to consign 
          to oblivion the multitude of injuries which they have received from them,
          and to be of good and placated mind:
          and therefore,
          although tacitly,
          to give to them that part of the land in which they have received themselves:
          and also to approve even their perpetual settlement.
          And these things indeed we ought reasonably to presume from the fact that those peoples 
          are naturally peaceful as a whole race,
          and gentle and of good will,
          inflicting evil on no one (unless they first received it).
          Whence, when they shall have known by experience that the Spaniards converse with them 
          peacefully and humbly,
          without doubt they will love them no less than if they were their own brothers and fathers,
          and for the Spaniards afterwards there is acquired the right of communicating 
          and acquiring and enjoying acquired things:
          whatever temporal goods are found in the land.
          Which right has in no way been acquired by them hitherto in that entire world,
          as is clear from what has been said and will be said.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-d1e799">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But our King from that time can be considered to have subjects in such a province,
          and not before,
          to whom he can delegate those things which he has in habit,
          according to what will be said 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e532-Rd1e810">below § 40</ref>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>