<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 14</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 14</title>
          <date when="2025-08-20">August 20, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-08-20" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="39-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Hd1e97">Section 14</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e99">
          § 14
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e104">
          In the conclusion follows Part 7
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e111">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          A timely,
          quiet notification,
          etc.,
          concerning the cause of their advent and legation,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e126">
          Timely,
          namely,
          with place and time,
          persons and other circumstances observed according to those things which the Philosopher teaches 
          in Ethics 3,
          that the virtuous one works what is fitting and according to what is fitting,
          and when and how and concerning what he works.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e136">
          And especially it must be awaited and observed in this article that first the Spaniards 
          or the aforesaid messengers learn and know the idiom of each province or place,
          so that those peoples may fully understand whatever will be proposed to them.
          Otherwise nothing will be done by law,
          in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e150">
            l. 1 § fi. in 5th column ff. de verborum obligatione
          </ref>,
          and there notes 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e154">Ludovicus Romanus and Instit. eo titulo § in hac re</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e156">
            Antonius de Butrio in c. fi. de eo qui mittitur in possessionem causa rei servande 2nd column
          </ref>,
          there in open and clear words so that they may be understood,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e163">ff. de institutionum l. sed et si § 1.</ref>
          Felinus notes in the rubric de constitutionibus penultimate column.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e158">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But that this notification ought to be quiet,
          that is,
          as regards the intellect and reason,
          free from the darkness of disturbances which are caused by the passions of the soul,
          is clear,
          because just as the stars accustomed to shine on us and the earth to germinate cease to do this 
          on account of the interposition of obscure clouds,
          so the intellect and reason which shine and illuminate man in the knowledge of truth 
          are impeded by the darkness of disturbances.
          And just as when the water of the sea remains clear like glass,
          our sight can penetrate it and see 
          <pb ed="#B" n="39-v"/>
          those things which are under the water,
          but if it is disturbed by wind,
          then it will obstruct vision,
          so the quiet mind of a man does not impede the discourses of reason 
          nor the judgment of the intellect for understanding what is proposed.
          But if it be moved and disturbed by some molestation or anguish,
          fear,
          sadness,
          pain,
          or even anger,
          or other things which give cause for disturbances,
          immediately it obstructs the discourse of reason and the judgment of the intellect.
          Similarly,
          just as water running from high mountains proceeds freely and by a straight path,
          and is impeded by the obstacle of a stone which rolls down from the mountain,
          so that it cannot proceed rightly,
          so reason,
          free and unimpeded,
          discourses rightly and the intellect judges rightly.
          But if it is affected by motions of some disturbance,
          reason is impeded in the discourse of liberty,
          and the intellect in the knowledge of liberty.
          Thus says 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e218" corresp="#cy8th8-d1e242-Qd1e223">
            Boethius book 1 meter 7, On the Consolation
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Qd1e223" source="http://scta.info/resource/hy7y6y-d1e51-d1e419@1-55">
            Hidden by black clouds,
            the stars can pour forth no light,
            etc.
            You too,
            if you wish to discern the truth in clear light,
            to grasp heaven by a straight path,
            drive away joys,
            drive away fear
          </quote>,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e234">
          From which it appears that in order that those things which we wish to propose and persuade 
          to some persons may be heard and understood,
          it is necessary that the reason and intellect of the hearers be unquiet and in tranquility,
          and far from any molestation and other thing which is sufficient to cause disturbance in the mind.
          But if they were proposed with tumult or perhaps with the noise of arms,
          with terror breathing,
          with threats or scourges,
          or in an imperious manner,
          or harshly and with any other rigor or disturbance,
          it is manifest that the human mind is dismayed by terrors,
          disturbed by clamors,
          fear,
          and harder words,
          is saddened,
          afflicted,
          flees.
          Therefore to hear,
          the exterior sense and also the interior,
          such as fantasy or imagination,
          is disturbed and darkened.
          Consequently reason and intellect do not apprehend,
          nor can they take up the intelligible form as lovable or delightful,
          but rather as saddening and hateful.
          On account of which the will not only cannot be affected or love,
          but rather hate those things which are proposed,
          and be indignant on account of those terrible things which it unjustly,
          or a man through the intellect,
          judges himself to suffer.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e301">
          Therefore it is necessary that this notification be quiet 
          <pb ed="#B" n="40-v"/>
          and free from all darkness of disturbance,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e307">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          From these things can be elicited the proof of that which follows,
          namely that this notification ought to be sweet and friendly,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e317">
          All this is clear,
          first because the first of the rhetorical rules is that he who wishes to propose certain things 
          to some persons and to persuade them,
          needs first to have had their minds conciliated to himself,
          through which he may render them benevolent,
          attentive,
          and docile,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e331">Cicero in book 2 On the Orator</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e335">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But they are conciliated through gentleness of voice and the signification of modesty of countenance,
          the placid showing of gentleness,
          the courtesy of words,
          which things especially prepare benevolence,
          according to the same Cicero.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e347">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second,
          because the natural mode by which a rational creature is apt by nature to be moved,
          led,
          directed,
          persuaded,
          and drawn to any good is that it be moved,
          led,
          directed,
          persuaded,
          and drawn blandly,
          sweetly,
          gently,
          and suavely,
          on account of the liberty of will,
          namely so that that motion may be gentle,
          sweet,
          and suave to it and connatural,
          so that of its own accord it may listen,
          hear,
          consider,
          acquiesce,
          and whatever there is of virtue,
          accept and do.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e390">
          Hence it is said 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e392" corresp="#cy8th8-d1e242-Qd1e394">Ecclesiasticus 6</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Qd1e394" source="http://scta.info/resource/sir6_5@1-4">
            A sweet word multiplies friends
          </quote>
          (just as we read of the blessed Clement and Sylvester,
          that on account of the sweetness of eloquence and gracious gentleness in conversing,
          they were beloved not only by the faithful but also by gentiles and Jews).
          And it follows in the adduced authority from Ecclesiasticus:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Qd1e405" source="http://scta.info/resource/sir6_5@5-7">
            and mitigates enemies
          </quote>.
          This appeared in Gideon,
          who mitigated the men of Ephraim stirred up against him through a sweet word,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e411">Judges 8</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e429">Valerius Maximus book 5</ref>,
          speaking in praise of humanity,
          says:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Qd1e416">
            The sweetness of humanity penetrates even the savage minds of barbarians,
            and softens the harsh and fierce eyes of enemies,
            and bends the most insolent spirits of victory.
            Nor is it arduous and difficult for it to find a placid way among contrary arms,
            among swords drawn at close quarters.
            It conquers anger,
            prostrates hatred,
            and mingles hostile blood with the tears of enemies
          </quote>,
          etc.
          And the reason for this is the generosity of the human soul.
          For according to Seneca,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Qd1e437">
            the human soul is more led than drawn;
            for the human mind has something sublime and lofty and impatient of a superior,
            but by the delight of a certain reverence or levity it is subjected
          </quote>,
          <pb ed="#B" n="41-r"/>
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e449">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore that notification ought to be sweet and friendly,
          and most modest and conciliating of the minds of hearers.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e459">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Further we said it 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Qd1e464">
            ought to be slow and successive with an interval of several days
          </quote>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e470">
          This is clear,
          first,
          because since those things which they are going to signify concerning the end or final cause 
          of their advent,
          namely to teach them concerning the one and true God,
          Lord creator of all,
          and concerning things pertaining to God which the Catholic faith preaches,
          have never been heard by them nor even thought,
          being so new,
          so admirable,
          as transcending every faculty of nature,
          it is manifest that they need a tract or delay of time not minimal,
          indeed great and maximum,
          for thinking about those things which are proposed,
          whether they are thus in truth as they are asserted.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e497">
          For since those things which are to be proposed to those peoples concerning God 
          are not manifest to the intellect immediately to be true,
          but some ratiocination must precede for believing them to be true,
          so that the intellect does not concede them to be true unless it wills,
          and unless through the will and by design it will have reasoned concerning them sufficiently,
          but to reason,
          according to the great Dionysius in On Divine Names 7,
          is to proceed through a certain discourse from one thing understood to another,
          and thus reason or intellect,
          or a man through reason or intellect,
          thinks,
          inquires,
          and discourses from one to another of those things which he hears,
          before he assents or gives assent.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e525">
          Therefore those nations need an interval and process of no small time,
          so that they may hear,
          think about,
          inquire into,
          discourse,
          and understand those things which are proposed to them.
          Therefore the notification of the cause and end of the advent of the Spaniards 
          or of the legates of our kings to be made and announced to the peoples and inhabitants 
          of that world of the Indies must necessarily be slow and successive over several days,
          and not sudden.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e545">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Second,
          those things which concerning the end or final cause of the advent of the Spaniards 
          are to be proposed to such peoples at the beginning of their application to any place or province,
          are unusual and unaccustomed,
          and never heard nor even dreamed,
          as has been said.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e564">
          But we naturally judge unusual and unaccustomed things less worthy of hearing and reception,
          as less known and strange to reason,
          and thus less true,
          because they are unaccustomed,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-Rd1e570">the Philosopher in Metaphysics 2</ref>.
          For if certain things be said to us beyond those things which we are accustomed to hear,
          <pb ed="#B" n="41-v"/>
          they do not seem to us similar in truth to those things which we are accustomed to hear.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e581">
          Therefore,
          in order that they may seem worthy of hearing and similar in truth to those things 
          which we are accustomed to hear,
          they must be accustomed among us.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e588">
          For those things which are accustomed are more willingly heard and more easily received,
          for accustomed things are pleasing.
          For it seems worthy to us that it be said concerning anything as we are accustomed to hear.
          For that which is accustomed is more known and pleasing to us,
          the reason for which is that custom is turned into nature.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e600">
          But they cannot be accustomed,
          nor can custom be generated,
          except from frequent acts,
          and for the frequentation of acts an interval of time and of several days is necessarily required.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e609">
          Therefore,
          in order that those things which concerning the cause of the advent of the Spaniards,
          namely concerning God and the preambles to that and subsequents,
          are to be notified to the aforesaid peoples at the beginning,
          may be able to be accustomed and pleasing to them,
          and thus may seem to them worthy of hearing and similar to those things which are true 
          or which they have been accustomed to hear,
          and may be more willingly heard and more easily received,
          it is necessary that the aforementioned notification be slow and successive over several days,
          in which interval of time those things may frequently and most frequently be proposed,
          repeated,
          explained,
          distinguished,
          so that from such frequent acts,
          little by little in the hearts of the hearers,
          may be generated a certain force and disposition or pleasing custom or habit 
          which causes a quasi-natural inclination by which the human mind may be helped and disposed,
          so that the aforesaid things,
          since they have already become accustomed to be heard,
          are made pleasing to them,
          may seem consonant with truth,
          and consequently worthy to be heard,
          believed,
          and received.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e242-d1e655">
          Therefore it is clear how the aforesaid notification concerning the cause and end 
          of the advent of the Spaniards,
          to be made and announced to the peoples and inhabitants of that world of the Indies,
          ought to be timely,
          quiet (that is),
          free as regards the intellect and reason from any disturbance,
          sweet and friendly,
          most modest and conciliating of the minds of hearers,
          finally slow,
          successive with an interval of time,
          and not sudden.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>