<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 44</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 44</title>
          <date when="2025-11-09">November 09, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-09" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="123-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Hd1e97">Section 44</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e99">
          § <sic>43<!-- but actual 44 --></sic>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e108">
          Up to this point we have endeavored in a by no means avaricious course 
          to make evident in what manner or by what right it would not be lawful 
          for our kings of Spain without the license and gracious consent of the Inca king 
          or his descendants to whom it would belong according to their laws 
          to succeed in their goods or dignities: 
          to inquire into or investigate and much less to carry away 
          or command such things to be done regarding the treasures 
          and riches of the tombs with the intention of retaining them, etc., 
          as contained in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e135">
            a certain responsive conclusion to the principal question in § IV
          </ref>.
          Where, expanding the matter so that the truth might be made more lucid and robust, 
          we strive to exhaust thoroughly from the foundation of the principles of natural 
          and divine law in what state the royal right existed in that world from the beginning 
          of its discovery and how it now exists.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e157">
          ¶ But then indeed let the discourse return from where it has wandered at greater length 
          (namely) what will be the right concerning treasures found and to be found in tombs: 
          of which there exists no memory whose they are or to whom they belong 
          from the antiquity of time. 
          For previously through the first four §§§§ 
          matters are treated and understood concerning things found whose owners 
          or their heirs are known or can easily be known. 
          And therefore concerning those now it must be treated: 
          whether they belong to the finder. 
          Or to the one whose place or land in which they are found belonged 
          or to the prince himself, the Inca, or his treasury.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e189">
          ¶ For the clarification of this doubt it seems it must be said with this distinction: 
          that either those who now in those parts inquire, investigate, find, 
          and take away are Indians or natural inhabitants of that world 
          or they are Spaniards now in fact inhabitants there with the natives. 
          If indeed they are natural inhabitants and individual persons 
          who inquire into or find treasures, then we say thus: 
          that if such treasures are in some property or estate 
          or field or house or part of the land belonging to someone, 
          and by chance or industry he seeks whatever is precious, 
          the whole belongs to the finder by natural right according to all doctors 
          and likewise Saint Thomas in 2 2ae q. 66, article 5 ad 2 thinks 
          and the gloss on the Institutes de rerum divisione § Thesauros 
          because natural law itself gives him the faculty of seeking 
          and justly enjoying what he has found. 
          Whence from that point of time when he has found it he acquires ownership of them for himself. 
          This d. Thesauros gives to understand, where it is thus said: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e234">
            Treasures which anyone has found in his own place: 
            the divine Adrian following natural equity granted to him who found them
          </quote>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e240">l. unica C. de Thesauris lib. 10</ref>
          where it is said: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e241">
            we grant free faculty to use what has been found: 
            lest further the benefit of God be pursued by envious calumny
          </quote>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e250">
          ¶ But if he finds in the place of some private person, 
          or in the place of Caesar or a public place of the treasury or city, 
          either this happens by chance, as if perhaps plowing or otherwise cultivating 
          another's land or by any other chance, 
          because it seems by fortune or better by God's benefit 
          that good was conceded to him, it was owed to the finder by natural right. 
          But the civil laws (of which Saint Thomas makes mention in the above place) 
          have established for the sake of preserving peace among citizens 
          that half the part should belong to the owner of the soil 
          and the other half should fall to the finder, as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e273">d. l. unica</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e275">l. non intelligitur § si in locis ff. de iure fisci</ref>.
          Similarly half a part must be given to the treasury or city 
          if it is found in a public place as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e282">d. § thesauros</ref>.
          But if from intention and industry with deliberate effort, 
          or even against the will and objection of the owner, 
          all that he has found will belong to the owner of the soil as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e299">d. l. unica</ref>.
          Because such a one is considered a thief. 
          In Spain the aforementioned laws are observed to the letter, 
          as appears in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e305">l. 44 titulo 28 3e partite</ref>.
          But in the business of the natural inhabitants of that world it must be noted 
          what laws or customs prevailed among them concerning those things 
          which were found by chance or industry or deliberate effort, 
          and according to them judgment will have to be made by reason of 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e316">
            l. venditor § si constat ff. communia prediorum
          </ref>.
          But our laws do not bind them. 
          But if we cannot use their laws or customs for the decision of such doubts, 
          it must be had recourse to what should be done according to natural equity. 
          For if anyone finds treasures or any precious things deliberately and with effort 
          in another's property or field, especially if against the will 
          and prohibition of the owner, he is bound to restore the whole to him 
          whose property or field it is, to whom he does an injury worthy of punishment, 
          as is clear through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e339">l. 3 ff. de acquirendo rerum dominio</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e344">ff. de iniuriis l. iniuriarum § si quis me prohibeat</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e349">d. l. unica C. de thesauris lib. 10</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e351">l. quosdam C. de metallavus lib. 11o</ref>.
          And the reason for these laws is the injury which is inflicted upon the owner 
          of the property or little land or soil without his knowledge and license 
          by entering into his property, especially if violently when the owner objects.
          Thus says 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e370">d. l. uenditor § si constat</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e364">
          ¶ Nor can the Inca king grant license for inquiring into 
          or investigating treasure in the property of some private person against his will, 
          especially if some harm would result to him from it, by reason of 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e384">d. l. vnica de thesauris</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e390">d. l. quosdam</ref>.
          Unless there were a custom, or unless the Inca king when he granted 
          <add place="margin-left">
            <unclear>that land if indeed he granted it</unclear>
          </add>
          reserved to himself the treasures or any other precious things 
          which might sometime be found in that property or land. 
          And then something must be given to him whose land it is 
          for the damage perhaps which he received in the property, 
          and let the damage not be grave, as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e412">d. l. cuncti C. de metallariis</ref>.
          But if it were grave, the Inca king could not grant it against the owner's will 
          because it would be against natural law, 
          since no one is to be advantaged with another's injury or loss, 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e421">regula iuris locupletari lib. 6</ref>.
          And if such a custom prevailed in that place or kingdom it would be corruption 
          and diabolical, as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e409">
            Baldus says in l. sicut C. de servitutibus et aqua pluuie arcenda
          </ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e432">l. quosdam preallegata</ref>
          supports this, where it is prohibited to dig in another's place 
          for the sake of seeking stones or marbles where the owner of the place would have damage, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e418">ff. de damno infecto l. fluminum § fi</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e423">ff. d. l. venditor in fi</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e426">
          ¶ Hence it is apparent that marble quarries, chalk pits, silver mines, 
          or gold mines, or veins of another metal which are in the soil of any private person 
          cannot be inquired into nor taken from there without his license, 
          nor can the king take them from private persons or give license for taking 
          without injustice, because by natural right they belong to him, 
          unless a certain quota which at the beginning in election the people established for him. 
          And thus are understood those things which are regalia.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e464">
          ¶ Likewise the Inca king cannot give license for inquiring into these things to others 
          or for being dug or taken against the will of the owners for the same reason 
          by which reason the kings of Castile dispose that no one with harm to anyone 
          and without the license of the owner of the soil should inquire into 
          or dig up metals, as will be shown below. 
          Whence just as by common law I can find treasure by my labor in my own property 
          and take it as mine, as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e510">d. l. unica and instit. de rerum diuisione § Thesauros</ref>,
          by the same reason if in my property there are quarries, gold mines, 
          silver mines or metal, I can dig those things, because it is the same reason. 
          And therefore it is the same right because a reason for diversity cannot be given: 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e505">ff. de fonte l. 1</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e508">
            ff. de verborum obligationibus l. a titio according to 
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Nd1e510">Andreas de Isernia</name>
            in titulo Que sint regalia super verbo argentarie
          </ref>.
          Where he proves that that text "argentarie" is not understood absolutely 
          that mines or metals wherever they are found belong to the king, 
          but only those which are in the property of the king: 
          but not concerning mines and metals which are in the places of private persons. 
          For these can be by common law founded in natural reason in the places of private persons, 
          as is the express text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e534">l. 3, in fi. ff. de rebus eorum</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e536">ff. soluto matrinonio l. diuortio, § si vir</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e541">ff. de censibus l. forma</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e544">ff. de vsufructu per legatum, l. generaliter § uxori</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e549">ff. de usufructu l. item si fundi</ref>.
          And in these mines and metals which are in the places of private persons, 
          the aforementioned 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Nd1e556">Andreas de Isernia</name>
          says that custom is observed where they are, by the text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e560">d. l. venditor § si constat</ref>.
          But when custom is lacking concerning metals found in the soil of a private person, 
          the royal treasury has the tenth part according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e597">d. l. vnicam</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e604">d. l. cuncti preallegatam</ref>.
          And concerning this revenue of metals speaks 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e609">
            the text in l. inter publica in fi. ff. de verborum significatione
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e613">the gloss there</ref>
          declares: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e577">
            Where the text says: we must understand public revenues 
            from which the treasury receives: such is the revenue of the port 
            or of things for sale. Likewise of salt works and of metals
          </quote>,
          the gloss says: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e587">
            <mentioned>Of metals</mentioned>
            concerning which a tenth is given to the treasury from metals, as in 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e629">l. cuncti</ref>
          </quote>,
          etc. This is the gloss. 
          From which it appears that those things which are said to be regalia 
          by that title in the uses of feuds are not totally and simply of the kings. 
          Since some are public and common, not fiscal or patrimonial, 
          which are in the ownership of the prince, 
          but are public in the use of all of the kingdom or principality, 
          according to what is said in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e607">ff. de acquirendo rerum dominio l. quod in littore</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e6Z9">instit. de rerum diuisione § 1</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e614">§ littora</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e617">ff. eo titulo. l. 2 in fine</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e619">l. sequen</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e622">
          ¶ Therefore regalia are shores and public roads and navigable rivers 
          as to defense and protection, so that the king may prohibit anything to be done there 
          if the use of the shore and public road would be impeded, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e641">d. l. littora</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e643">l. sequen</ref>.
          For they are not in the patrimony of the king, because these public things differ 
          from those which are in the ownership of the treasury or Caesar: 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e647">d. l. 2. § 1</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e650">
          ¶ Whence in these roads and shores the prince ought not to grant 
          things which are contrary to common and public law, 
          because by sacred oracles or pragmatic sanctions 
          granted against the utility of the world, rights are to be annulled, etc., 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e666">
            C. de aqueducto l. diligenter circa finem lib. 11o
          </ref>.
          Nor is there commerce of them, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e671">ff. de contrahenda Emptione l. sed et celsus</ref>.
          Nor will the prince donate these things, nor can he donate them, 
          because they are not his, just as fiscal and patrimonial things, as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e726">ff. ne quid in loco publico l. 2 § hoc interdictum</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e731">§ sequen</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e682">
          ¶ But certain regalia are those in which the king has only a quota 
          or the fifth or the tenth part, or that which the peoples at the beginning 
          established for kings for the maintenance of their honorable status, 
          such as ports, that is, revenues or tribute which come from those things 
          which are carried in the port or from the port. 
          These are regalia because they are public in the strict mode, 
          that is, in the patrimony of the king. 
          River rights in the same way, proceeds and revenues coming from these. 
          For banks and their use is public, just as the sea and navigable rivers, 
          which are also called regalia as to the protection of the prince 
          and are inalienable, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e713">l. riparum ff. de rerum diuisione</ref>.
          And then they are called regalia as to the protection of the prince 
          because they are not alienated, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e720">d. l. sed celsus</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e723">
          ¶ The same is said concerning metals or veins of metals and salt works, 
          which are regalia, namely as to the quota part which should reasonably be imposed, 
          if at the beginning of the election of the king by the people it was not imposed. 
          Thus it is in Spain, and the same common laws or their reasons are observed. 
          For it is said in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e795">l. 6 titulo 28 partine 3e</ref>
          that the revenues of ports, salt works and fisheries and iron works 
          and other metals and taxes are of the prince, and also of tolls, 
          which were granted for the honorable sustenance of kings 
          and the defense of the kingdom against the aggression of infidels 
          and for the cutting off of importunate exactions. 
          And these are commonly said properly to belong to the royal crown. 
          For thus that law says in the Spanish vernacular: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e757">
            The revenues of the ports and of the tolls which merchants give 
            for reason of the things which they take from the sea or from the land, 
            and the revenues of the fisheries and of the iron works and of the other metals, 
            and the taxes and tributes which men give, belong to the emperors and to the kings. 
            And all these things were granted to them so that they might have 
            with which to maintain themselves honorably in their expenses, 
            with which they could protect their lands and their kingdoms 
            and wage war against the enemies of the faith, 
            and because they could excuse their peoples from imposing many taxes 
            and from doing other burdens to them
          </quote>.
          This is that law in form.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e780">
          ¶ And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e843">the laws of ordinances lib. 6 titulo 1o l. 8</ref>
          it is declared that minerals, namely veins of gold mines and of other metals, 
          and salt works as well as springs or salty wells from which salt is made, 
          are regalia, nor is it lawful for anyone without license or privilege 
          to dig or usurp anything of them for himself. 
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e854">titulo 12 of the same book l. 8</ref>
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e798">
            license is granted to all indifferently for seeking, digging, 
            and taking gold, quicksilver and marble stones in their own fields or properties. 
            Likewise in others' properties, but without prejudice to the owners 
            and with their consent. But from all that anyone will have obtained from there, 
            after all expenses which he made for himself have been deducted, 
            let him retain the third part, and let him pay two parts to the treasury or king
          </quote>.
          This is there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e818">
          ¶ From which it can be gathered that the patrimony of the king is twofold: 
          the entire kingdom itself, just as the subjects or natural inhabitants of the kingdom, 
          the cities and all things which are in it and annexed to the kingdom and treasury. 
          For the kingdom or republic, the treasury, and the prince are supposed 
          as if for the same thing, as notes 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e835">C. de seruis fugitinis l. penultima</ref>.
          And Baldus on the feuds of marquisates, duchies and counties, 
          where he says that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e839">
            the kingdom or republic is like the liveliness of the senses, 
            the treasury is the stomach of the republic, the sack and firmness, 
            the prince the head. Whence the prince or emperor would be as a tyrant 
            if he did not conduct himself as the republic, 
            and many other kings who would deal for their own private utility, 
            because he is a robber who does not attend to the utility of the master 
            but to his own, 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e923">ff. de negotiis gestis l. si pupilli § 2</ref>.
            And this Innocent notes 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e865">extra. de religiosis domibus c. cum venerabilis</ref>.
            And 
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Nd1e871">Joannes Andreas</name>
            also does what is noted in 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e939">
              C. de sacrosantis ecclesiis. l. neminem per glossam
            </ref>
            and Cinus
          </quote>.
          This Baldus says.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e877">
          ¶ This patrimony the prince cannot alienate, 
          nor do any harm to it without the will of the kingdom. 
          The reason is that he is not the owner but the administrator, 
          nor did he receive it for alienating and making it worse, 
          but for governing, improving and preserving it in its liberty. 
          Nor is it properly his but of the inhabitants of the kingdom, 
          according to what Baldus says in the above place: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e898">
            Whose is the city of Bologna? Of the Church. Rather of the Bolognese, 
            because the Church has nothing of authority there except as the republic, 
            whose image and name of the republic it bears. 
            Likewise it is asked: whose is the city of Siena? 
            It is answered: of Caesar. Rather more of the Sienese
          </quote>.
          This from Baldus.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e910">
          ¶ Nor also can the king alienate those things which are annexed to the treasury, 
          namely the royal revenues concerning which above, 
          because by this the royal status is weakened and would be rendered more impotent 
          both for governing and for defending the kingdom against enemies 
          who would more easily rise up knowing the king's poverty. 
          Whence he would have necessity to burden and oppress the people anew 
          with importunate exactions beyond what they can bear, 
          against the reason and end of the aforementioned law.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e932">
          ¶ The king or prince has another patrimony which the common laws call 
          the private goods of the king, such as the patrimonial goods proper to the prince himself 
          which he possesses as a private person or can have 
          and which can newly come to him from diverse causes, 
          such as those things which on account of the crime of treason, proscription, vacancy, 
          or on account of another cause, goods will have been devolved to his private treasury, 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e955">ff. de iure fisci l. 1</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e957">2 C. <sic>poenis bonorum subl.</sic> l. 1 lib. 10</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e1035">C. de bonis uacantibus. l. 3</ref>
          and through
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e1037">the whole lib 10</ref>,
          as if from moneys which came from the revenues of the kingdom 
          he should buy some possessions or castles or places from private persons, 
          or also those which by his industry he acquired by just war against infidels, 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e1045">
            c. abbate sanc. § pro parte in fine de re iudicata. lib. 6
          </ref>,
          speaking of the king of Aragon acquiring by just war against infidels 
          certain places which were counted among his own and private treasury or patrimony, 
          where it is said that since 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e980">
            the king himself by his worth and effort conquered the above-mentioned places 
            from infidels
          </quote>
          and below 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e985">
            since they became his own property and seemed to be separated from other hereditary goods
          </quote>,
          etc. This is there. 
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e1067">l. 2 de aqueductu in fine lib. 11o</ref>
          it is said: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e989">
            Let him know that the same property, marked by the prescription of fiscal title, 
            is to be aggregated to our private goods
          </quote>.
          This is there. 
          Therefore concerning this patrimony of the king, the king can make donations and grants, 
          always however moderately, lest the patrimony being exhausted from frequent donations, 
          he be forced to extend his hand to the goods of subjects 
          (with justice trampled as sometimes happens) 
          and easily from king be turned into a tyrant according to Tully in book 2 de officiis. 
          But concerning this we will speak more diffusely elsewhere, God helping. 
          Mention is made of each patrimony of princes in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e1091">
            Authent. vt omnes obediant iudicibus prouinciarum § si vero col.
          </ref>,
          there: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e1013">
            either to the sacred patrimony, that is, to imperial things or the empire, 
            or to sacred private things, that is, to the private goods of the prince
          </quote>,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e1101">
            l. bene a Zenone C. de quadriennii prescriptione § sancimus
          </ref>,
          there: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e1020">
            Concerning those things which proceed from the most sacred emperors, 
            not from fiscal goods, but from their private substance
          </quote>,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-d1e1024">
          ¶ Behold therefore what are the regalia of princes, 
          and it seems it must be said thus concerning other kingdoms, 
          that these are regalia and patrimonial or fiscal in any kingdom, 
          unless the contrary appears from the institution of the people or the reigning one, 
          or from the approved custom of that kingdom. 
          And we ought to follow this provided it is reasonable. 
          On account of this Baldus used to say in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e1048">l. 3 C. ad rebellianam</ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Rd1e1050">rubrica ff. de rerum diuisione</ref>
          that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e637-Qd1e1053">
            the whole world observes that kings have regalia, that is, 
            revenues of certain things which cannot be alienated, 
            and other things which they can moderately donate
          </quote>,
          as appears from what has been discussed above. 
          Therefore as it touches those Indian nations, 
          always as we have said, custom or laws are to be awaited, 
          and thus judgment is to be made concerning the present matter.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>