<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 30</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 30</title>
          <date when="2025-10-08">October 08, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-10-08" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="78-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Hd1e97">Section 30</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e99">
          § 30
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Our Catholic Kings of Spain have the supreme principate of that Indian world,
          the dominion and supreme jurisdiction,
          and all those things which by right pertain to supreme princes:
          in potency,
          although not fully in purified potency.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e119">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The corollary is proved because someone is said to have dominion or jurisdiction 
          or power in potency when something is known to be lacking to him,
          by the absence of which he is impeded from the actual exercise of power,
          dominion or jurisdiction.
          Which can happen in many ways.
          Either in a delegate when by a general clause placed in a rescript 
          without expression of things and persons,
          jurisdiction is committed in potency and not in act.
          But after expression 
          <pb ed="#B" n="79-r"/>
          of persons and things he has it in act as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e143" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t3-d1e316@79-80">
            c. pastoralis § quoniam autem de rescriptis
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e150">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Or in any elected person before confirmation.
          For by election the title of prelacy and the habit of power to be administered 
          is conferred on the elected,
          but by confirmation only the exercise is conferred 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e166" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d63-Dd1e244">
            chapter Quanto and what is noted there 63 dist.
          </ref> 
          The gloss notes at the end and by the doctors in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e171">c. si per confirmationem de electione libro 6</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e178">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise the prelate of a collegiate church who does not presently have a college,
          has in potency and potentiality jurisdiction,
          so that if today some were assumed into the college:
          the first prelate could exercise it:
          which previously he did not have in act because the subject was lacking to him 
          concerning which jurisdiction would be exercised.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e199">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And similarly it is evident in a parochial presbyter having a distinct parish 
          in which no one dwells,
          for such a rector has care in potency and not in act,
          concerning which see what 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e210">Panormitanus notes in d. § quoniam autem</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e216">c. de multa de prebendis</ref> 
          whom you should also see in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e222">clement. 1 de priuilegiis</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e221">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          It is also clear through jurisdiction in a potentate or judge before he enters 
          the territory deputed to him as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e230" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e226-Dd1e138">
            l. obseruare ff. de officio proconsulis
          </ref>.
          Whence jurisdiction in potency is by potentiality,
          but in act by exercise,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e238">
            Baldus notes de allodiis libro feudorum et C. de summa trinitate l. 1. 2 columna, in fin.
          </ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e247">Baldus and ff. de officio prefecti urb. l. 1, 1 § 1.</ref> 
          and by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e252">Bartholus ff. de iurisdictione omnium iudicum</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e249">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But someone is said to have jurisdiction not fully in potency whenever it does not belong 
          to someone purely in potency presently:
          but comes to be purified from a future act:
          just as is seen in an archbishop to whom jurisdiction does not yet belong even in potency 
          before an appeal is interposed.
          Whence the archbishop cannot depute an official in the decision 
          <pb ed="#B" n="79-v"/>
          of his suffragan concerning appeals to be interposed to him,
          whose reason is that before the appeal is interposed he does not yet have jurisdiction 
          even in potency:
          but after it has been appealed.
          Then immediately it is purified and jurisdiction presently and fully in potency belongs to him,
          as is the notable text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e280">c. Romana de officio ordinarii lib. 6</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e282">c. Romana de appellationibus</ref> 
          in that book with what is noted by Hostiensis in both places.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e291">
          And each jurisdiction in potency in the aforesaid modes:
          thus is related to exercise and commission.
          For the first which purely belongs to someone in potency presently,
          having it can commit as much namely as to that which he has,
          that is the habit of jurisdiction:
          as because a potentate existing outside the territory of his jurisdiction 
          can delegate a cause to a subject existing in the territory as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e308" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e226-Dd1e138">
            l. observare, ff. de officio proconsulis
          </ref> 
          and what is noted by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e324">gloss and doctors in c. nouit de officio legati</ref> 
          but the exercise of a jurisdictional act:
          he is able neither to exercise nor to commit as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e331">d. l. observare et § quoniam autem</ref> 
          and the gloss and doctors there and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e336">gloss at the end in c. ex tenore</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e341">gloss in c. ex suscepto de foro competenti</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e326" target="http://scta.info/resource/nyf6td-d1e178-Dd1e17247">
            John Monachus in c. si confirmationem de electione lib. 6
          </ref> 
          and in d. c. Romana § 1 de officio ordinarii libro 6
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e338">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But the second belonging to someone not purely in potency presently,
          but to be purified from a future act,
          cannot be committed or delegated as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e37x">d. c. romana</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e349">Panormitanus notes in d. § quoniam autem</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e354">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Nd1e355">Antonius de Butrio</name> 
            in. d. § quoniam autem
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e384">beautifully by the lords of the Rota in decision 846</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e389">decision 156 in the old ones</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e362">
          And the reason is that what does not exist cannot be committed as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e366" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c1q7-Dd1e476">
            1, q. 7, c. Daibertum
          </ref> 
          and d. quoniam,
          and of what does not exist judgment cannot be received 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e371" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e662-Dd1e382">
            ff. de iudiciis l. non potest
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e376" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t3-Dd1e244">
            de rescriptis c. ad hec.
          </ref> 
          And what I cannot do myself,
          I am not able to exercise through others 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e388" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1612-d1e574">
            de regulis iuris quod alicui libro. 6
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e393" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e5058-Dd1e114">
            ff. de administratione rerum ad ciuitatem pertinentium, l. 2.
          </ref> 
          He can however exercise some act concerning preparatory matters of jurisdiction,
          as is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e407" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e226-Dd1e138">
            d. l. 
            <pb ed="#B" n="80-r"/>
            observare
          </ref>, 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e414">d. c. Romana</ref> 
          and by the gloss and Panormitanus in d. § quoniam autem and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-Rd1e418">d. c. nouit</ref> 
          and other places.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e421">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And such is the jurisdiction which the Supreme Pontiff,
          the Vicar of Christ,
          has as regards infidels who have not yet received the faith.
          In order that he may fully have it in potency:
          it is necessary that through the reception of faith or through some offense 
          which they make to the Church,
          and thus from a future act,
          it be purified.
          For it is manifest that the Supreme Pontiff does not involve himself in temporal matters 
          except among Christians and with cause,
          and only within the Church does he have jurisdiction fully in potency:
          and thus nearest to exercise or so that it may be reduced to act.
          But as regards infidels,
          since their conversion or special fault is future,
          which is the act by which jurisdiction is to be purified,
          that is perfected:
          therefore presently,
          until they are Christians:
          it is more remote from being in act,
          and consequently not fully in potency.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e462">
          Since therefore the universal dominion,
          power and jurisdiction of that world does not depend on papal concession 
          or institution alone (as appears from many things proved above),
          but principally from the free consent and voluntary acceptance of those peoples 
          and princes and nations together:
          which consent however our kings have not yet had up to now 
          (as will immediately be proved),
          and consequently they come to be purified from future acts (namely) 
          the conversion and consent of those peoples with their kings,
          it follows that the said dominion,
          power,
          jurisdiction of that supreme principate belongs to our kings in potency only 
          from the part of the title of the aforesaid institution or papal concession:
          and thus in potency not yet presently purified but to be purified:
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e510">
          Therefore only can they occupy themselves concerning preparatory matters,
          namely as to this,
          that they may lawfully go or send their messengers and legates,
          and exercise all preparatory acts which concerning the inhabitants 
          <pb ed="#B" n="80-v"/>
          and dwellers of those regions and lands are to be done or exercised from the beginning.
          Namely those which in the 2nd conclusion we have placed under the order of law 
          to be necessarily observed and to be observed.
          Which it is not lawful for any other Christian prince to exercise because of the express 
          and just prohibition of the Supreme Vicar of Christ under incursion of most grave anathema:
          indeed not even for any cause whatever to approach those parts or to send,
          as appears in the apostolic decree concerning this.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e453-d1e563">
          Whence it appears that our kings can delegate no cause in those lands,
          since the subject is lacking to them (that is) 
          subjects concerning whom they may exercise habitual power:
          nor do they have by right any subject there to whom they may delegate a cause,
          as in the example of the archbishop before the interposition of an appeal.
          And this until those peoples of their own accord submit themselves to their authority:
          as is sufficiently proved by many things adduced above,
          to which see immediately what I say below § 33,
          and thus the corollary is evident.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>