<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 21</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
            <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
            <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 21</title>
          <date when="2025-11-15">November 11, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-15" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="54-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Hd1e97">Section 21</head>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e100">
          § 21
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e105">
          But if the aforesaid means (which God forbid) should be omitted,
          and immediately when Spaniards shall have arrived at those lands and kingdoms 
          and shall have entered them,
          they should notify the same peoples of such new,
          so unusual and for ages unheard of by them,
          indeed not even dreamed of (as we have said) things,
          namely that they are bound to render obedience,
          servitude and subjection to a foreign king,
          and to receive him as universal lord over their own and natural kings and lords,
          and this as regards all inhabitants,
          but as regards their kings and princes,
          <pb ed="#B" n="55-r"/>
          if we speak,
          if they should hear that they ought to submit their necks to another king's authority 
          and recognize a superior,
          when they exist as free kings and superior lords and great Lords,
          ruling magnificently and pompously in their own manner over many other lords:
          will they not all equally be able to be most fiercely disturbed on hearing these things:
          terrified and implacably scandalized?
          Did not King Herod,
          hearing from the Magi that the King of the Jews was born:
          become troubled,
          and all Jerusalem with him?
          And that they could indeed be disturbed is evident because someone is said to disturb another 
          by simple entry into his possession against his will 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e150">l. iniuriarum § fine ff de iniuriis</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e155">1 dist c. 1.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e153">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise someone disturbs another by taking away fruits 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e165">
            Baldus in l. post sententiam ultima columna C. de sententiis.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e163">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise by plowing and gathering of fruits,
          Baldus in consilium quidam acusatus at the end,
          and such a disturber is called malicious 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e180">
            Baldus in l. in cunctis, 1 columna C. finium regundo.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e174">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise it is called a delict 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e189">l. si quis § si tutoris. C. si vi aut clam.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e182">
          Likewise someone is said to disturb by resistance. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e198">Baldus in l. 1, C. de testibus.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e187">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          By selling another's property and handing over possession to the buyer 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e208">gloss and Bartholus in l. si duo 2 columna ff. uti possidetis.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e197">
          Likewise by asserting to have a servitude in another's property 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e218">
            gloss and Bartholus in d. l. si duo in princ. 1. q. ff. uti possidetis
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e223">l. 2 § fine ad finem ff de acqui emptio</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e228">l. menius § fundo ult. colu. ff. de legatis 2.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e206">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          By disturbing in a servitude of an estate:
          he is said to disturb in the estate,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e237">Bartholus in l. sicut § aristo.</ref> 
          verse turbatur 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e242">§ si seruus where the gloss.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e215">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise someone disturbs by any annoyance and impediment 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e252">instit de interdictis § retinendum.</ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e254">Cynus in l. 1, C. uti possidetis</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e225">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise by denying that the adversary does not possess 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e264">
            Bartholus in l. si prius ff. de operis noui nunciatione.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e234">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Likewise when someone asserts himself to possess or to have some right. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e277">Baldus in l. ordinari 5 columna C. de rei vendicatione</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e282">l. non ab re. C. vnde vi.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e244">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But let us pass over in silence many other examples of disturbance:
          there is no one who patiently and without greatest disturbance of his spirit 
          <pb ed="#B" n="55-v"/>
          can hear that he should lose his freedom:
          which thing is known to be inestimable and lovable as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e301">was proved above</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e303">l. libertas ff. de regulis iuris.</ref> 
          And especially that he ought to be subjected to an unknown king,
          of another unknown race.
          Since such kings are wont to be little affectionate toward the people 
          over whom they are placed:
          and consequently do not care much about them.
          And again to afflict them with exactions,
          unbearable forced services and to burden them with other unusual burdens.
          And this was the reason why the Lord prohibited his peculiar people 
          from making themselves a king of another race,
          as is evident 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e320">Deuteronomy 17</ref> 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e322">St. Thomas 1 2 q. 105 article 1 2.</ref> 
          Which also 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e327">
            Bartholus mentions in tractatu de regimine ciuitatis 4 and penultimate columns.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e280">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But what I ask will they do and how will they be disturbed,
          or have been disturbed,
          those who have suffered so many insults,
          calamities,
          and slaughters from our people.
          And those to whom the Spaniards have not yet come,
          and nevertheless have heard how many evils we have inflicted on neighboring provinces:
          when the messengers of our King seek from them their consent and will 
          to receive him as supreme prince.
          If they probably presume and fear with a fear falling upon the most steadfast men,
          that they will be despoiled of their goods,
          dignities and dominions will be taken from them,
          their wives ravished,
          they will be orphaned of their children and reduced into complete 
          and most bitter servitude?
          Truly with the greatest disturbance of their spirits full,
          with terrible horror and immense pain of the viscera and indignation,
          they will by no means be able to endure even hearing it.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e315">
          For who of sound mind will ever dare to doubt that those peoples immediately 
          when they first hear this,
          will rightly rush to the natural,
          just and common refuge of all nations.
          Namely to arms,
          and will repel force by force with all their might:
          so that either they expose their life to the dangers of death and finish it in war:
          or they free their own republics from such invaders whom they judge not undeservedly 
          to be impious and wicked,
          for they are,
          and they see themselves most unjustly about to be subjected?
          What cause is more just for waging war than the repulsion of servitude.
          According to 
          <pb ed="#B" n="56-r"/>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e394">Cicero in the Philippics l. 7.</ref> 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e396">Vegetius de re militari lib. 3</ref> 
          Who doubts that the art of war is more powerful than all things,
          through which freedom is retained and the dignity of the province is propagated 
          and the empire is preserved.
          And again,
          there is no secure possession of riches unless it is preserved by the defense of arms.
          But concerning these things more fully elsewhere.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e351">
          Therefore to avoid such grave and unjust disturbance in those peoples:
          to prevent so many evils which must necessarily intervene in wars,
          so many deaths,
          slaughters,
          devastations of lands (and what is more miserable and lamentable) 
          so many damnations of souls,
          and consequently so many injustices and most wicked works of tyrants,
          and so that there may be a just and God-approved entry,
          principate and universal dominion of our kings into that world:
          it is necessarily required that most modestly,
          most gently,
          most discreetly and most sweetly,
          with sweet and supplicating words,
          with good reasons and inducements,
          they be moved,
          induced,
          persuaded to freely give their own consent.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-d1e394">
          And thus 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e334-Rd1e466">
            part 11 of the conclusion concerning which we began to treat in § 16
          </ref> 
          is evident.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>