<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 8</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 8</title>
          <date when="2025-08-05">August 05, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, 
            Brown University, 
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-08-05" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="21-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e150-Hd1e97">Section 8</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e100">
          § 8
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e105">
           
          From these arises another,
          and let it be the fourth consideration,
          namely that the Supreme Pontiff,
          through the oft-mentioned institution concerning our kings to the superiority of said world,
          did not intend to deprive the kings or natural lords of the aforesaid world of their domains 
          and royal dignities and jurisdictions;
          or to concede anything else to our kings or to give license to do or omit anything 
          by which the preaching of the faith might be impeded,
          or the conversion of the aforesaid peoples might be wholly frustrated or even delayed.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e127">
           
          The first is proven in many ways:
          first because the Roman Pontiff knows better that without a true,
          examined,
          and necessary cause he cannot remove those things which are of natural and common law,
          especially confirmed by divine law of the Old and New Testament,
          as these are,
          as appears from what has been said. 
          But the cause of preaching the faith and the conversion of souls is not a sufficient,
          truly examined,
          or necessary cause,
          since without such deprivation the faith can be preached 
          and the conversion of souls can be had;
          rather on the contrary,
          it is a most effective cause for disturbing the entire world 
          and stirring up the minds of infidels against us,
          <pb ed="#B" n="22-r"/>
          to whom we would give material and just cause for attacking us in war 
          out of just fear of the loss of their goods,
          dignities,
          honors,
          domains,
          and jurisdictions;
          also for blaspheming and hating the doctrine of Christ and the Christian religion,
          and the bearer of the evangelical law,
          that is,
          an immaculate law converting souls (namely) Jesus Christ,
          as if he were iniquitous and unjust,
          and his law iniquitous and unjust;
          and consequently they would withdraw themselves in every way 
          from receiving that law and religion,
          or if they were already prostrated and conquered by us through violence 
          (which would be easy for us,
          at least as regards the Indian nations),
          they would show themselves willing to receive the faith or the sacrament of faith,
          but without doubt they would receive such a thing falsely or derisively,
          despising it.
          That these things would necessarily come to pass 
          if infidels knew that they were to be deprived,
          by right or in fact,
          of their goods and dignities and domains,
          anyone who does not confess this is not prudent but inexperienced.
          But this would be to frustrate and destroy the aforesaid end which God intends 
          and which the vicar of God himself testifies he intends in his apostolic letters;
          and consequently,
          without a just,
          examined,
          and necessary cause,
          it would be contrary to the natural order which the eternal law forbids to be disturbed;
          and finally contrary to those things which are of natural and divine law 
          (which is far removed from the vicar of Christ),
          since he did not receive power for destruction but for the building up of the Church.
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Qd1e212">
            I will act,
            says the Apostle,
            according to the power which the Lord gave us for building up and not for destruction,
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e217">
            2 Corinthians 10.
          </ref>
          Where Saint Thomas explains: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Qd1e219">
            The Lord gave me this special power for converting the gentiles for the building up,
            namely,
            of the Church,
            and not for destruction,
            as the false ones do,
            abusing the power given to them for the opposite of that for which it was given.
          </quote>
          Thus Saint Thomas.
          And in the last chapter of the same epistle: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Qd1e230">
            We can do nothing against the truth,
            but for the truth.
          </quote>
          Where also Saint Thomas says: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Qd1e235">
            But God gave me this power,
            namely of binding and loosing,
            for building up,
            not for destruction,
            namely that you may be built up and not destroyed.
          </quote>
          Thus Saint Thomas.
          Therefore the Supreme Pontiff,
          through the oft-mentioned institution concerning our kings,
          did not intend to deprive the kings and natural lords of that world of the Indies 
          of their domains,
          states,
          royal honors,
          dignities,
          or jurisdictions.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e250">
           
          Second,
          because if he were understood to have deprived those kings of their domains,
          etc.,
          through said institution,
          since no legitimate cause would be present,
          <pb ed="#B" n="22-v"/>
          he would truly be abusing the power which he received for building up,
          to the destruction of the Church,
          and he would be said to act against the truth,
          since by this the faith would be defamed and the conversion of infidels would be hindered,
          which is wicked,
          as we have already said.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e274">
           
          Third,
          because the Apostolic See through its laws or constitutions or donations 
          is not accustomed to remove,
          without legitimate cause,
          those things which are of natural or common or divine law;
          rather it protests that it will preserve them inviolably even unto life and blood,
          as has been proven.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e288">
           
          Fourth,
          through those things which all the canonists commonly determine in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e298">
            c. Que in ecclesiarum de constitutionibus
          </ref>
          namely that the pope cannot deprive infidels of their domains and jurisdictions,
          just as he cannot deprive Christians.
          And particularly 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e305">
            Innocent in c. quod super his de uoto
          </ref>
          which opinion the theologians more studious of natural law also hold,
          and we have written most extensively elsewhere.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e305">
           
          Fifth,
          through what Dominicus de Sancto Geminiano says in consilium 11,
          namely that whenever the pope concedes some new right,
          he is not understood to wish to remove the right which a third party had before,
          because he is always understood to concede without prejudice to another's right,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e327">
            c. super eo de officio delegati
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e329">
            de rescriptis c. Quamuis
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e334">
            c. si propter tua debita, lib. 6.
          </ref>
          And what is more,
          he says,
          even if he should add words referring to a vice from the past,
          saying that the preceding vice can be objected to,
          because through these general words it is not the pope's intention 
          to take away a right acquired by another in a thing or to a thing,
          unless he should say this specifically:
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e347">
            d. c. quamuis
          </ref>
          , and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e349">
            de consuetudine, c. cum olim.
          </ref>
          Thus Dominicus.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e335">
           
          And therefore the words of the apostolic decree of the aforementioned institution 
          do not stand in the way,
          where it is said absolutely thus:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Qd1e342">
            With all the domains of those islands and mainland,
            namely,
            cities,
            castles,
            places,
            and towns and rights and jurisdictions and all pertinences,
            to you and your heirs and successors,
            the kings of Castile and Leon,
            in perpetuity by the tenor of the present documents we give and concede
          </quote>
          etc.,
          from which it seems he deprived the aforesaid kings or lords, 
          etc. 
          But it is not true through the above said and to be said.
          Because the said institution or donation or concession,
          or however it may be considered or named,
          if it must be preserved so as not to be unjust,
          is understood as regards the superiority or supreme and universal dominion 
          and jurisdiction over that whole world,
          <pb ed="#B" n="23-r"/>
          like imperial dignity,
          just as in antiquity the emperor over many kings;
          and yet the kings freely enjoyed and possessed their own dignities and domains 
          and jurisdictions,
          who had justly acquired them.
          Otherwise,
          the emperor indeed had dominion and universal or supreme jurisdiction in the whole empire,
          and as it were mediate,
          with some restriction of jurisdiction,
          as it is to be believed,
          either obedience or service or tribute as a sign of universal dominion,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e415">
            argument in c. tua nobis extra de decimis
          </ref>
          But the trace of this appears in the Herodian kings 
          who in the time of Christ were in Jerusalem subject to the Roman emperor 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e421">
            Luke 1 and 3
          </ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e423">
            Matthew 2
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e425">
            Mark 6
          </ref>
          and in other places.
          Likewise it is clear in secular histories.
          It is also read in the legend of the ten thousand martyrs 
          that the emperors Hadrian and Antoninus,
          having heard that they were Christians,
          wrote to five kings,
          namely Sapor,
          Hadrian,
          Maximus,
          Tiberianus,
          and another Maximus,
          that they should come to them and consult about what should be done with such men.
          They indeed,
          having gathered an army,
          came to the emperors,
          etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-d1e418">
           
          For these jurisdictions and domains are indeed compatible,
          supreme or universal,
          namely,
          and the immediate ones of inferiors,
          from the fact that they are of different species or that they differ in species.
          And thus it is not incompatible that two persons concur simultaneously 
          and at once in the dominion or jurisdiction of one thing,
          one indeed in the universality of the whole,
          the other truly in singular things.
          The text according to the jurists is in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e463">
            l. 1, § per hanc el. 2o ff. de rei uendi
          </ref>
          , where a flock in its universality can be in the direct dominion of someone,
          and yet the singular heads of that flock are in the direct dominion of another.
          And through that text Bartolus determines that the emperor was said to be lord of the world 
          when there were kings subject to him,
          and thus he understands 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e477">
            l. de precatio ff. ad l. hoc Rhot. de iactu
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e482">
            l. bene a zenone C. de quadriennii prescriptione
          </ref>
          . Nevertheless the domains and jurisdictions of individual kings and other things of individuals
          remained with their proper lords which they had justly acquired.
          The same holds 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e491">
            Bartolus in extravagan. ad reprimendum
          </ref>
          in the word <mentioned>totius orbis</mentioned>:
          and at the beginning of the feuds,
          and Angelus and John of Imola,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e498">
            l. si heredes seruus ff. de legationibus 1
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e501">
            Alexander in l. 1, C. unde legitimi
          </ref>
          and thus is limited 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e503">
            l. possideri § ex contrario ff. de acquirenda possessione
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e509">
            l. si ut certo, § si duobus uehiculum, ff.
          </ref>
          <pb ed="#B" n="23-v"/>
          commodati,
          which say that two persons cannot be lords of one thing in solidum.
          Which hold true if both were in the particular simultaneously,
          or in the universal simultaneously,
          that is,
          in one and the same species of dominion.
          Nevertheless if one is universal lord or in the universal,
          the other truly particular or in the particular,
          and thus in diverse species,
          it is well compatible,
          just as is clear in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e163-Rd1e526">
            l. 1, § per hanc, ff. de rei vend.
          </ref>
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

