<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 28</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</n>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 28</title>
          <date when="2025-10-05">October 05, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-10-05" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="72-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Hd1e97">Section 28</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e99">
          § 28
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e104">
          The last part of the second principal conclusion contains that,
          with the free consent of kings and peoples obtained,
          and such papal institution concerning our kings voluntarily held as valid and accepted:
          treaties should be made with them and pacts concerning the manner of ruling:
          concerning the tributes to be paid to our kings,
          with the rendering of oath by both parties concerning preserving the agreement and pacts,
          and similar matters.
          This therefore remains to be proved.
          Which we prove thus.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e127">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Natural reason dictates that a free people wishing to subject itself to someone's direction or government,
          and to make itself subject from being free,
          obligating their persons to keeping fidelity to another,
          and thus to make their own condition worse as regards the diminution of their own freedom 
          (because according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e142">
            Baldus in l. si aquam C. de seruitute et aqua pluuia
          </ref>) 
          although fidelity and subjection is not full servitude:
          it is nevertheless a certain species of servitude,
          as is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e155" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e1711-d1e110">
            de usu fructo l. si cuius
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e159" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e3438-Dd1e173">
            l. cum seruum ad fi. C. de seruis fugitiuis
          </ref>) 
          can reasonably seek some conditions from him:
          because anyone in the handing over of his property can impose the pact,
          law or condition which he wishes,
          because in his own property anyone is the moderator,
          disposer and arbiter 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e172" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e2231-Dd1e312">
            l. in re mandata C. mandati
          </ref>.
          Much more in handing over himself can someone impose law and condition,
          provided it be reasonable.
          And someone can justly submit himself to one person or community in those things 
          which are not contrary to God and which in themselves have no repugnance to natural justice,
          in which he can better be directed by him to whom he submits than by himself,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e197">St. Thomas says 2 2 q. 57 article 2</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e197">
          Hence it was the custom among all peoples and nations in the institutions or elections of kings 
          from the beginning when they wished to create and establish 
          <pb ed="#B" n="73-r"/>
          magistrates or kings over themselves:
          or in their coronations:
          or when successors are admitted to kingdoms,
          to make some treaty,
          pact,
          law or agreement or composition,
          or to renew one already made with predecessors between both,
          namely king and people,
          spontaneously and in good faith:
          preceding the administration or exercise of royal power and jurisdiction,
          treating and making pacts:
          The King indeed promising in words under oath and in writing,
          and swearing tacitly or expressly that he will have due care of the people,
          and will introduce good government,
          and granting liberties,
          exemptions,
          good customs handed down from antiquity:
          or if they do not exist or the old ones do not please the people:
          other new ones and other things which the people demands for its preservation 
          in good state of the whole republic,
          profitable privileges,
          among which there always enters or is understood,
          even if not expressly stated,
          that he will find or exercise no new burden to the prejudice of the people.
          But that he will preserve all equally in peace and tranquility:
          and as father of the whole republic will defend the fatherland.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e272">
          For if any free man in the handing over of his property can place the law and condition 
          which he wishes,
          provided it be reasonable,
          another is bound by natural law to preserve it as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e284" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l4t5-Dd1e153">
            extra de conditionibus appositis c. verum
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e288" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c18q2-Dd1e574">
            18. q. 2, c. Eleutherius
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e293" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e455-Dd1e104">
            ff. de pactis l. 1.
          </ref> 
          Nor is there deceit to one knowing or willing. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e298" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e734-Dd1e460">
            C. de transactionibus l. cum donationibus
          </ref> 
          And pacts must be preserved 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e303" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t35-d1e119">
            extra de pactis c. Antigonus
          </ref> 
          far more strongly can a free people in the handing over of itself to a King or ruler 
          to whom it voluntarily commits itself to be governed for its own good,
          and for this reason obligates itself to revere him:
          to obey and serve him:
          and to keep fidelity perpetually,
          <pb ed="#B" n="73-v"/>
          to pay tributes and other burdens and royal rights.
          It could justly and reasonably place the law and condition which pleased it,
          and the king or ruler thus elected by the people was and now is bound to observe it 
          by natural law,
          as appears in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e334">c. 1 de probationibus</ref> 
          with what is noted there by the canonist and legist doctors in the laws cited above.
          But the people promised necessary honor,
          subjection,
          fidelity and due service with the other things which I just said:
          decreeing to render certain tributes and annual revenues:
          both in recognition of universal dominion and sign of subjection,
          concerning which there is argument in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e347" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t39-Dd1e123">
            c. omnis anima extra de censibus
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e350" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t12-Dd1e214">
            de causa possessionis et proprietatis. c. fi.
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e355" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c10q3-Dd1e249">
            10, q. 3, c. illud
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e359" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e81-Dd1e444">
            C. de episcopis et clericis, l. nulli
          </ref>.
          Both for maintaining the honorable state of the king etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e369">
          Behold a contract on both sides,
          or obligation on each part arising from the will of the parties.
          Therefore we say that by making pacts we draw diverse wills into one.
          Whence the King or ruler or magistrate remains thereby obligated to the kingdom and republic:
          and the kingdom and republic to the king or magistrate.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e382">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And these compositions concerning exacting,
          diminishing or augmenting tributes and services,
          or sometimes exchanging them,
          made between lords and subjects,
          must be preserved,
          nor can they be revoked by the lords:
          because they have the force of law as to them as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e400" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e3206-Dd1e355">
            l. cesar. ff. de publicanis
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e405">
            l. donatione. in fine. Codex de donationibus ante nuptias
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e412" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e6363-Dd1e216">
            l. illud ab vna. et what is noted there C. de annonis et tributis lib. 10
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e420">
          The aforesaid is evident through what Samuel did and ordained,
          or rather God through him.
          For after he placed Saul in the midst of the people,
          already shown as king by lot,
          and the people voluntarily accepted him saying: Long live the king:
          immediately he placed the law of the kingdom there:
          But Samuel spoke to the people the law of the kingdom (that is) 
          according to the interlinear gloss,
          how the people ought to conduct themselves toward the king and the King toward the people,
          and what the king should exact from the people:
          and what the people ought to give to the king.
          Behold the contract and pacts and obligation on both sides.
          1 Kings 10.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e447">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The same appears in David,
          the second King of that Israelite people.
          2 Kings 5.
          Where it is said that David struck a covenant with the people:
          because they made among themselves a composition as regards the law of the kingdom,
          concerning the manner of ruling,
          namely how much power was entrusted to kings:
          and what burdens and services he could impose on subjects:
          because David swore to observe these things to the people:
          but the people swore to observe what they promised to the king.
          And these sworn chapters were called a covenant:
          or the law of the kingdom from the constitution of Saul as king with Samuel 
          by the authority of God:
          which Samuel wrote in a book and recited before all the people as was said.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e474">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For a covenant was a certain manner of very strong contract in which there was a promise 
          from one or from each part to do something and as a sign of friendship.
          And that promise was confirmed by oath:
          and so that it might be still firmer,
          certain ceremonies were done (namely) 
          that animals were killed and divided into two parts,
          and those making the pact passed between those divisions,
          signifying by this:
          that whoever should violate the covenant:
          would be divided into two parts like that animal.
          This from Genesis 18 concerning the covenant which God made with Abraham.
          And the people with the Lord in the time of King Hezekiah.
          Jeremiah 34.
          And between God and the people in the giving of the law.
          Exodus 24.
          And Nicholas in both places.
          And the gloss on Nehemiah 5.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e517">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          It is therefore evident how in the first establishment of a king,
          a certain contract or covenant,
          pacts and agreements were made,
          to which men,
          since they are rational,
          <pb ed="#B" n="74-v"/>
          were induced by natural reason and prudence.
          It was similar when successors of kings were admitted to the royal height 
          in place of the deceased by the peoples,
          namely that the pacts and compositions made with predecessors 
          were either confirmed or reformed,
          especially if they were unjust or just but violated nevertheless.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e545">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          This is evident in 3 Kings 12 where it is found that with Solomon dead,
          who had too greatly burdened the people with tyrannical exactions 
          and unbearable annual tributes,
          when all the people of Israel were gathered at Shechem to establish his son Rehoboam 
          as their king:
          first they wished to settle with him concerning the diminution or relaxation of the tributes 
          by which they were most heavily oppressed and by the harshest servitude,
          from which while Solomon lived they could not be freed.
          But now because a new king was being instituted,
          and it was likely he would seek all the rights (if they deserved to be called true rights) 
          which his father had extorted:
          since it is the custom of rulers to invent new exactions,
          but never to diminish the old ones;
          they had the opportunity of freeing themselves from such a yoke and servitude 
          by settling with their king that he not oppress them as his father had.
          Whence thus it is said there:
          But Rehoboam came to Shechem.
          For there all the people of Israel had gathered to make him king.
          And they spoke to Rehoboam saying:
          Your father imposed a most harsh yoke upon us:
          you therefore diminish a little from the most harsh rule of your father,
          and from the most heavy yoke which he imposed upon us,
          and we will serve you etc.
          And natural reason itself demands that what the predecessor did badly and tyrannically 
          in the kingdom,
          burdening the people,
          the successor should settle and amend at the people's petition,
          and should swear henceforth to preserve it.
          Just as if from the beginning,
          electing or instituting a king over themselves anew,
          they should make pacts for the same condition.
          For subjects are no less 
          <pb ed="#B" n="75-r"/>
          free under the 2nd or 3rd or certainly under the thousandth king than under the first,
          when the kings are just.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e624">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          If indeed the King should reign perpetually,
          obligated by contract or covenant to procure the good and utility of the whole kingdom,
          his own being postponed,
          by that very fact that he consented to the election or institution made concerning himself,
          or succeeds in the kingdom and wishes to reign,
          he assumes the office of ruling,
          tacitly even if nothing is said,
          like a tutor or curator or manager of business who are obligated only from acceptance of the office,
          because they quasi-contract,
          although the express will of both did not intervene.
          For although a ward having a tutor,
          or a madman having a curator,
          or he whose business someone ignorantly manages,
          did not expressly contract:
          nevertheless the tutor,
          curator and manager of business are obligated as if they had contracted.
          Because what is inherent,
          even if not expressly stated:
          nevertheless is understood to be added,
          nor does it change or add. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e666">
            C. de fideiussoribus et demonstra. l. conditiones extrinsecus
          </ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e671">ff. de legatis. l. 1 and 3.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e676">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And so kings are obligated to the kingdom and the republic.
          For the republic is accustomed to use the right of minors 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e689">l. res publica C. quibus ex causis maiores</ref> 
          where the gloss says: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Qd1e685">
            Just as minors are under curators:
            so the republic under administrators
          </quote> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e701">C. de iure respublice: l. rempublicam</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e704">C. de officio eius qui vicem alicuius l. 1.</ref> 
          And this comes from the nature of the tacit contract through the tacit assertion of industry 
          of one accepting the office for which he is elected 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e715">C. mandati l. a procuratore</ref> 
          with what is noted there and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e719">l. pro officio.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e722">l. sequens. C. de administratione tutorum</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e724">instit. where above § tutoris quoque.</ref> 
          Hence it is that the prince is obligated by the contract entered into with the subject as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e731">d. c. 1 de probationibus</ref> 
          and it is a good argument in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e735">c. nisi cum pridem § verum</ref> 
          with what is noted there by the gloss and doctors extra de renuntiatione.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e740">the Cardinal in consilium 142</ref> 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e744">
            Felinus in c. que in ecclesiarum column 14 de constitutionibus.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e715">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          From 
          <pb ed="#B" n="75-v"/>
          which it appears that the consent of the king to reign or wishing to reign is not sufficient alone:
          but it is necessary that the consent of the people intervene so that the contract may be valid,
          and consequently so that the king can reign by right.
          For a contract is defined as the consent of two or more in the same thing,
          and obligation on each part.
          But if one part were lacking,
          it will not be a contract:
          but a violent and tyrannical entry as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e767">1. q. 1. c. principatus</ref> 
          Also 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e772">C. de sacrosanctis ecclesiis l. decernimus</ref> 
          where 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e778">Baldus</ref> 
          says that 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Qd1e744">
            provinces which have been accustomed to be ruled by their kings and princes:
            are said to be under their natural dominion,
            that is by the law of nations as 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e750">l. ex hoc iure ff. de iustitia et iure</ref>.
            And if another takes dominion there contrary to the will of the king 
            (you add: and of the people according to what was proved 
            <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-Rd1e799">above § 16</ref>).
            That one is a tyrant because,
            he says,
            usurped dominions are called tyrannies
          </quote>.
          These his words.
          Where he also said that to those invading camps pertaining to just lords:
          those camps cannot be conceded by the prince etc.
          As we related above.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e770">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And thus the last part of the 2nd conclusion is evident,
          namely that it is necessary,
          with the voluntary consent of the peoples and their kings obtained,
          by which the said papal promotion or institution concerning our kings 
          is pleasing to them and held as valid or accepted:
          that a treaty or contract be made between those peoples and kings 
          and the messengers of our kings:
          concerning the manner of ruling:
          and agreement concerning exhibiting obedience and tributes,
          and observing reasonable laws and customs for them:
          all of which things are to be confirmed by oath etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e427-d1e794">
          And consequently the entire conclusion is left clear with all its parts:
          which contains the order of law and the necessary circumstances which must be observed 
          so that rightly and correctly our kings of Castile and Leon may be able to obtain 
          the supreme principate of that Indian world.
          With all these things omitted,
          it will in no way be possible to justify their entry and 
          <pb ed="#B" n="76-r"/>
          progress into those kingdoms nor their possession of them,
          as will be proved.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>