<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 29</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 29</title>
          <date when="2025-10-07">October 07, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-10-07" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="76-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Hd1e97">Section 29</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e99">
          § 29
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Our illustrious Kings of Spain,
          as long as the peoples and inhabitants of that Indian world with their kings and princes 
          have not freely consented to the aforesaid institution made concerning them by the Pope,
          and hold it as valid and hand over possession,
          have only the title,
          that is the cause of acquiring the supreme principate of the aforesaid world,
          and right to the thing or to the kingdoms and superiority or universal dominion over them,
          which arises from the title:
          but they do not have right in the thing or in the kingdoms.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e130">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For title is every cause of acquiring dominion,
          as title as buyer,
          as donee,
          as heir,
          as one's own etc.
          According to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e141">the gloss, in c. fi. de officio archipresbiteri</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e143" target="http://scta.info/resource/bplext-d1e116-d1e107">
            c. dudum El. 2 de electione in the word "intitulatam"
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e150">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But someone is said to have right to a thing and not in the thing whenever some right 
          remains to be had or obtained by him so that the right to that thing may be acquired by him,
          and thus right to the thing is not yet to have right fully acquired by someone:
          as in one elected to some benefice or dignity.
          For through election only right to the thing is acquired,
          not in the thing.
          But through confirmation or collation right in the thing is acquired according to what is noted 
          in c. penultimo de prebendis lib. et 6 and in c. fi. de concessione preben. eo lib. 
          and c. super his de acusationibus and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e178">clemen. unica de secresta possessionum.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e182">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          So it is concerning our kings.
          <pb ed="#B" n="76-v"/>
          For they have the papal election or institution,
          and thus title and right to those kingdoms,
          which no king of Christians in the world has.
          But there still remains for them another more powerful and more principal right to be obtained,
          namely the consent of the peoples and their kings,
          so that they may hold the said papal institution as valid:
          by receiving them as universal lords and supreme princes:
          by freely handing over to them possession of those kingdoms:
          so that our kings may acquire right in the thing (that is) 
          may obtain full power of exercising supreme jurisdiction and those things which are reserved 
          to the supreme prince and by royal and imperial authority.
          As manifestly appears from what has been said.
          Therefore as long as the aforesaid peoples and inhabitants with their kings have not freely consented etc.
          Our kings will have only the title and right to those kingdoms,
          but not in those kingdoms (that is) 
          they have no faculty of exercising jurisdiction or conducting themselves as supreme princes.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e233">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The consequence is proved first because the natural foundation and efficient cause 
          of all faculty or power and jurisdiction to be exercised and of obtaining the principate itself 
          is lacking to our kings,
          namely the consent of the peoples and their kings.
          For 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e247">
            Baldus says in c. quia propter 3 columna. de electione
          </ref> 
          that consent is required as the natural foundation,
          namely so that someone may enter rightly and correctly into a dignity or magistracy.
          And it ought to be simple,
          that is without fold of force or fear,
          so much so that if violence constrains the electors or the clamor of a raging people,
          the election is said to be null by the very law:
          because that is not called free which is constrained in any way. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e269">
            ff. de conditionibus et demonstrationibus l. titio centum § 1. argument
          </ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e274">ff. qui et quibus l. si optio.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e266">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          He also says there that the efficient cause of election is consent,
          actively in the one electing,
          passively in the one elected.
          Where therefore the consent of those electing is lacking:
          the natural 
          <pb ed="#B" n="77-r"/>
          foundation and complete efficient cause are lacking.
          Therefore such a one can neither rightly nor correctly enter into a dignity or magistracy,
          nor possess it.
          So it is concerning our Catholic kings,
          because until the aforesaid peoples and their kings shall have given consent 
          without fold of force or fear:
          they will not have rightly or correctly right in those kingdoms,
          that is the exercise of royal power (except right to the thing and only title).
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e306">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But that the aforesaid consent is a more powerful and more principal right (I say) 
          namely with respect to the papal institution insofar as such,
          is proved.
          For if those peoples with their kings had voluntarily subjected themselves to our kings 
          or to any other Christian prince before the said institution,
          as they could by the law of nations and natural law since they are free peoples,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e343">§ it is touched upon l. ex hoc iure ff. de iustitia et iure</ref> 
          and all there and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e348">Baldus in c. de quo vult deo extra. de iudiciis</ref>,
          it is manifest that the Supreme Pontiff would not impede such subjection.
          This is proved first because then the final cause of exercising temporal jurisdiction over them 
          would cease.
          For the final cause on account of which the Vicar of Christ can involve himself 
          in temporal matters,
          especially concerning those nations:
          is the preaching of the faith and their conversion,
          to which all things which are to be done in such business ought to be ordered and directed,
          as we have proved in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e367">the 3rd consideration § 7</ref>.
          And this presupposing that provision had been made equally well for those same peoples 
          concerning their conversion to the faith with another Christian prince:
          but otherwise if provision had not been made equally well.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e359">
          Which being granted,
          the Supreme Pontiff could well impede that subjection by reason of the existence of the cause 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e387">
            excellent argument C. Venerabilem with what is noted extra de electione.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e370">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly it is proved because where someone disposes of his own right,
          the consent of a stranger is not required,
          as in § moribus si de feu fue. contio in. do. et agna. vas.
          Which according to Baldus there is true if he disposes of his own right or in a time 
          when he was free,
          but otherwise if to another's prejudice as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e411">ff. de aqua pluuie arcenda l. in concedendo</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e419">l. in diem.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e421">l. receptum ff. communia prediorum</ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e426">
            l. si per fundum ff. de seruitutibus rusticorum prediorum
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e395" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e2264-Dd1e241">
            C. de contrahenda 
            <pb ed="#B" n="77-v"/>
            emptione l. dudum.
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e404">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But those peoples by subjecting themselves to any Christian prince:
          would have disposed of their own right,
          and consequently without anyone's prejudice.
          Therefore the Supreme Pontiff would not have impeded such subjection.
          Therefore with the cause of exercising such jurisdiction ceasing,
          the jurisdiction itself should have ceased.
          The consequence is evident:
          because when cause is required as the foundation of jurisdiction:
          the cause must be present and true and examined:
          otherwise the judgment is null by the very law,
          as we said in § 9:
          For with the foundation of truth removed,
          and consequently of power,
          the edifice which consists principally from this stone of foundation is turned into ruin.
          It is noted by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e470">
            Baldus on rubrica C. si quis aliquem probibuerit 5 columna it applies c. cessante de appellationibus
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e440">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore without the knowledge and license of the Pope,
          before the aforementioned institution concerning our kings as universal princes of that world,
          it was lawful for those peoples with their princes to subject themselves to whichever 
          of the Christian princes they wished,
          whence the said papal institution by itself alone would not suffice without their consent,
          as has been proved:
          therefore for obtaining rightly and correctly full dominion and jurisdiction over them,
          their consent is a more powerful and more principal right.
          Therefore our kings having only the papal institution:
          and lacking the consent and voluntary acceptance of that same institution by those peoples:
          the right which is more principal is lacking to them.
          The first consequence is evident:
          because when two things are so related to some act to be carried out that with one existing 
          without the other:
          that act can be carried out,
          and not conversely:
          that one is more powerful and more principal.
          Or thus according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e512">the Philosopher in Topics 3</ref>.
          Where one can be without the other:
          that one is more principal simply,
          indeed also better in that way.
          This rule is evident.
          In royal authority which can be without the authority of a proconsul:
          that is more principal which cannot stand without the royal:
          <pb ed="#B" n="78-r"/>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e484" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d8-Dd1e141">
            c. Que contra 8 dist.
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e487" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c11q3-Dd1e1554">
            11 q. 3, c. Iulianus
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e493">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Thirdly it is proved that the consent of the peoples and their kings themselves is more powerful 
          and more principal than the papal institution concerning our kings insofar as such.
          And this by a sufficiently fitting text in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-Rd1e504">
            l. et si non sint § veniamus ff. de auro argentoque legatis
          </ref> 
          where the text says that always when we seek what gives way to what,
          we await that which is applied as the cause of what thing arises:
          so that acceptance gives way to the principal.
          Where at the end he adds:
          because we await which thing is applied as the cause from which thing arises:
          not which is more precious.
          These words there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e528">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But since the conversion of those peoples and nations and also their temporal utility 
          were the final cause so that the institution or promotion or donation or concession 
          or by whatever other name it is considered arose,
          as was proved in § 7:
          and without their consent the more principal right and efficient cause of the principate 
          of our kings.
          And since such right has hitherto been lacking to the aforesaid papal institution.
          Therefore our kings have hitherto had only the title and right to those kingdoms:
          but not in those kingdoms,
          that is no juridical authority or power of exercising jurisdiction or conducting themselves 
          as supreme princes of that world.
          Nor will they be able to have it hereafter:
          as long as the peoples and inhabitants with their kings of the aforesaid world 
          do not give free consent.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e440-d1e567">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly,
          the conclusion is proved principally by the example of Saul and David,
          the first kings of the kingdom of Israel,
          who were directed by natural reason and divine motion and inspiration in their works and acts:
          and nevertheless did not dare,
          as long as they did not have the consent of the people,
          although they had the institution or election of God:
          and were certain they were instituted or elected by God as kings of that people,
          <pb ed="#B" n="78-v"/>
          to involve themselves in exercising jurisdiction in that people or to conduct themselves as kings,
          understanding that they had only right to the kingdom:
          but not right in the kingdom,
          as was evidently shown above § 18 and § 19.
          Therefore the 3rd principal conclusion is evident,
          namely that our illustrious and Catholic kings,
          as long as the peoples of that Indian world with their kings have not freely consented 
          to the aforesaid papal institution made concerning them,
          and have held it as valid and have handed over possession to them:
          have only the title,
          that is the cause of acquiring the supreme principate of the aforesaid world,
          and right to the kingdoms and superiority or universal dominion over them which arises from title:
          but they do not have right in them.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>