<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 24</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
            <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
            <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 24</title>
          <date when="2025-11-19">November 19, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-19" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="62-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-Hd1e97">Section 24</head>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e99">
          § 24
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e104">
          But the third proof is through instruments or privileges,
          or even through papal letters.
          By this also those peoples will by no means be able to be convinced 
          so that they are bound to stand by whatever letters that may happen to be shown to them.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e115">
          This is proved thus:
          By that which someone probably ignores and to which by not giving faith 
          he is excused by probable ignorance:
          he cannot be convinced:
          nor will anything be able to be necessarily concluded to him.
          Therefore by whatever instruments,
          privileges,
          or even by papal letters,
          those peoples cannot be convinced,
          nor can anything be necessarily concluded to them,
          even after they have received the faith,
          that the aforesaid institution emanated from the Pope,
          or that the Pope had power to make it.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e133">
          The antecedent is evident concerning him who is ignorant:
          because he has not learned the knowledge of some art.
          For such a one probably ignores that knowledge since he has not learned it:
          nor does he profess that art,
          or 
          <pb ed="#B" n="62-v"/>
          is bound to learn it,
          who also by not giving faith to the principles of that art is excused by probable ignorance:
          because he is ignorant without any fault,
          and consequently could not be convinced:
          nor will anything of that art be able to be necessarily concluded to him:
          as is evident in itself.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e160">
          And it is proved by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-Rd1e163">l. regula, § sed facti</ref> 
          with what is noted there:
          and in regula ignorantia de regulis iuris where fully by Dynus and by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-Rd1e171">gloss 38 distinctione in suma</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-Rd1e174">1, q. 3, § notandum in text and gloss.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e169">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But ignorance is probable when someone is ignorant of what commonly all 
          or the greater part of citizens or those who are of his state or quality are ignorant of 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-Rd1e188">
            Baldus in l. iuris ignorantia in the word Iudicis C. qui admitti.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e183">
          The consequence is proved:
          because such peoples,
          even after they have received the faith,
          at least for a long time,
          will probably,
          indeed invincibly,
          be ignorant of the force or authority of any instruments or privileges or papal letters:
          and therefore if they do not give faith to such letters,
          they will be excused by probable ignorance.
          Since the art of letters is not at all among them.
          And such instruments are by no means held among them:
          nor have they ever been accustomed to give faith to such things:
          or to bear witness in such a way.
          But rather that art seems to them to be a certain sleight of hand 
          or divinatory superstition or incantation,
          or something similar coming from the work of demons:
          when they perceive that what is done far away,
          the Spaniards know completely.
          And therefore blamelessly and without any fault they have not learned the art of letters 
          and all nations of their quality universally are ignorant of it,
          whence no one of them is bound to it,
          and consequently no one of them is bound to have faith in whatever letters or instruments 
          which the Spaniards will show them,
          at least for a long time:
          probable ignorance,
          indeed invincible,
          excusing them.
          For those peoples have sufficient impediment:
          on account of which they could not know the force and 
          <pb ed="#B" n="63-r"/>
          authority of instruments or letters.
          Nor are they compelled to believe the Spaniards asserting this:
          since in such a difficult and grave business they are entirely suspect:
          as has been proved:
          Argument for all that has been said in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-Rd1e251">c. inter dilectos de fide instrumentorum</ref>.
          Where certain privileges of the Church are not believed.
          See what is noted there in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-Rd1e258">c. ad audientiam de prescriptionibus</ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e245">
          From which you will see that even among us,
          so that faith be had in some writing:
          it is necessary that it was commonly accustomed to have been believed among us by our ancients:
          or that it be found in a place concerning which no suspicion of falsity is had.
          From which it is evident that if among us some writing is believed and makes faith:
          this is:
          because it is indubitably reputed to be authentic and faithful and without any suspicion of falsity.
          Therefore where the reason of such certitude and indubitable truth shall have ceased:
          the giving of faith and belief itself will have to cease.
          But among those peoples such reason of certitude and indubitable truth ceases:
          since commonly all without any fault are ignorant of letters and books and their force:
          nor do they know them to be of any moment of estimation or authority:
          indeed they have very many motives for conceiving vehement and violent suspicion of falsity:
          since the letters or instruments made concerning this,
          and which can be shown to them,
          contain things which are expressly contrary to natural law and the law of nations,
          and contrary to their public utility according to their estimation at least.
          Therefore it will not be a wonder if there is lacking in them belief 
          and the exhibition of faith to any letters,
          even papal:
          especially in a matter so difficult and of such great prejudice.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e289">
          By the third species of proof also,
          namely through writing or any letters,
          even papal,
          those peoples cannot be convinced,
          nor will it be able to be necessarily concluded to them that the aforesaid institution 
          was made by the Pope,
          or that the Pope could make it to the prejudice of so many kings and lords 
          and peoples likewise.
          But if anyone should try to prove the aforesaid to such peoples through any letters or instruments:
          <pb ed="#B" n="63-v"/>
          it would be just as if to one not knowing or ignorant of the knowledge of some art:
          he wishes to prove something pertaining to it through the principles of that same art:
          which would be ridiculous and quite unreasonable.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e318">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Concerning the 4th species of proof,
          see below the 4th principal conclusion § 31 where you have the resolution 
          with excellent reasons.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e333">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Concerning the 5th,
          what we said concerning the third suffices:
          and add that before the year of the Lord 1492 it was not yet known whether that world 
          and its inhabitants were in the nature of things.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e347">
          The 6th is nothing to the purpose.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e356">
          And similarly the 7th.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e363">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But the 8th,
          namely through oath:
          by this also nothing can be concluded to them,
          even if all the Spaniards should swear,
          for the reasons alleged above for the 2nd.
          Therefore they are not bound to stand by such oath,
          nor to give it any faith.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e381">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore by the often-made proofs of our law such peoples and nations cannot be convinced,
          even after they have received the faith,
          nor can it be fully or sufficiently concluded to them or certainly proved 
          that the said institution or promotion concerning our kings was made by the Pope,
          or that the Pope had power to decree it:
          and consequently they are not bound to stand by the said proofs:
          because they can rightly presume that the letters shown to them concerning these matters are false:
          and that those testifying to it can and ought to be accused of lying and falsity:
          and since it also contains in itself something which by the judgment of men 
          and according to truth is contrary to natural law and the law of nations,
          and can seem to them to be for the destruction of their republics,
          and consequently deviant from all honesty and justice:
          and thus will be estimated by the judgment of all men,
          at least to be to their maximum prejudice:
          because it places over them a foreign and unknown lord:
          indeed any prudent and capable man would not hesitate to resist with all his might 
          such an institution.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e374-d1e429">
          Therefore those peoples have just and reasonable cause not to accept,
          or at least to defer,
          even after they have received the faith,
          <pb ed="#B" n="64-r"/>
          such a papal institution or promotion concerning our kings,
          because reasonable cause is rendered:
          and they will do this by the authority of law.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>