<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 27</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 27</title>
          <date when="2025-10-04">October 04, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-10-04" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="67-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Hd1e97">Section 27</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e99">
          § 27
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly the same is proved thus.
          No one acts against the faith if he does not believe or doubts concerning that 
          on which Catholic doctors hold contrary opinions,
          until it is determined by the Church that this is against the faith:
          or that from it something contrary to the faith follows.
          But concerning the power of the Pope,
          especially in temporal matters,
          namely when he can exercise temporal jurisdiction or in what cases:
          Catholic doctors disagree and hold contrary opinions,
          as is evident in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e123" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t1-Dd1e290">
            c. Nouit de iudicis
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e128" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t2-Dd1e244">
            c. licet de foro competenti
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e131">c. uenerabilem de electione</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e136" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t6-Dd1e603">
            c. per uenerabilem extra qui filii sint legitimi.
          </ref> 
          And in many other places of law and treatises which they have written concerning this.
          <pb ed="#B" n="70-r"/>
          And especially in the very matter which we treat,
          namely whether among infidels there are justly legitimate dominions and jurisdictions etc.
          Therefore those peoples and nations will not act against the faith 
          if they do not believe or doubt,
          even after they have received the faith,
          that the Pope could have instituted the kings of Spain as superiors of that world.
          The Major is 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e161">St. Thomas 1. p. q. 32 last article and quodlibet.</ref> 
          The consequence is clear and is specially proved as is evident through 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Nd1e162">Innocent</name> 
          and 
          <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Nd1e167">Hostiensis</name>.
          For the former says that among infidels there are legitimately dominions and jurisdictions,
          nor can the Church despoil them of the same goods without fault,
          whom a multitude of doctors,
          both canonists and legists,
          follow.
          The latter indeed frankly asserts,
          rather absurdly,
          that at the advent of Christ all infidels were by that very law despoiled of such things,
          and thus he makes them incapable of dominions.
          Some follow him,
          as it seems,
          since they understand little of the necessary difference or distinction of infidels.
          But from the school of Theologians there is first 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e186">St. Thomas 2 2 q. 10 article 10</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e190">q. 66 article 8 ad 2</ref> 
          who subtly proves that among infidels there are justly dominions and jurisdictions.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e196">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The same 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e201">
            <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Nd1e202">Augustine of Ancona</name> 
            in tractatu de potestate pape. q. 23
          </ref>.
          Most recently however 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e209">Lord Cardinal Cajetan in 2 2. q. 66</ref> 
          where above more clearly and more intimately,
          although in few words,
          he pursues this doubt:
          and renders it most open truth where he says thus: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Qd1e221" source="http://scta.info/resource/TAcCaj-d1e1613-d1e1747@16-215">
            If there should be found pagans who have never been subject to the Roman empire:
            inhabiting lands in which the Christian name has never been,
            for the lords of these,
            although infidels,
            are legitimate,
            whether they are governed by royal or political rule.
            Concerning these I know no law as regards temporal matters.
            Against these no king,
            no emperor,
            nor the Roman Church can wage war to occupy their lands or subject them temporally:
            because no cause of just war underlies.
            Whence we would sin most gravely if we should strive to extend the faith of Christ 
            by this way:
            nor would we be legitimate lords of those lands:
            but we would commit great robberies and we would be bound to restitution 
            as unjust warriors or occupiers
          </quote> 
          etc.
          These his words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e255">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Since therefore there is controversy concerning such matters among illustrious doctors:
          indeed as for the most part all follow the truth which we defend,
          namely that the Pope cannot 
          <pb ed="#B" n="70-v"/>
          occupy or take away the lands or dominions of infidels,
          therefore neither can he place another lord over them against their will.
          Therefore not to believe or to doubt after they have received the faith:
          that the Pope cannot make the aforementioned institution concerning our kings,
          those peoples will not incur the fault of heresy.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e279">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For they are induced not to believe by an efficacious motive,
          namely by natural reason elicited from natural law itself.
          Because namely they have their own Kings and natural lords who govern them in justice 
          and peace and all good political rule in their own way,
          as without faith they can with moral virtues,
          and therefore rightly led by natural consideration,
          they will estimate all other rule of another foreign prince:
          not necessary to them:
          but superfluous,
          because nature does not abound in superfluous things:
          just as it does not fail in necessary things according to the Philosopher.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e309">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Nor also if they are unwilling to consent to papal letters of the said institution:
          or to obey immediately apostolic commands concerning this:
          will they be rebels or contumacious:
          First because they do this by the authority of law § 23 in the first reason 
          for proving the minor.
          Second because they have just cause not to obey nor to give consent,
          as is widely evident above § 23 24 25.
          Third because those peoples,
          both kings and common people,
          feel themselves most gravely and most enormously burdened by such promotion or institution,
          and suffering maximum prejudice.
          And therefore they are to be heard and not thus abruptly judged,
          as will be shown below in the 4th principal conclusion.
          Finally fourth because all those nations,
          even after they have received the faith,
          labor under probable,
          indeed invincible ignorance,
          as is evident § 23 and 24 and 25.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e350">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But those ignorant probably or invincibly,
          when they do this or omit it without guile and affection for erring,
          cannot be called contumacious or rebels.
          Whence if by impossibility any spiritual sentences or of the Church 
          should be fulminated against them in this case:
          they would by no means bind them in conscience as regards God nor as regards the Church.
          This is proved because for someone to fall into excommunication,
          true or presumed guile is especially required:
          of which kind is broad fault: 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e372" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e1463-d1e625">
            l. quod nerua ff. de po
          </ref> 
          John Andreas holds this in cap. quanto de sententia excommunicationis where he says 
          that no one falls into any canon:
          unless he is in guile:
          and 
          <pb ed="#B" n="71-r"/>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e385">
            the same Innocent in c. cum medicinalis eo titulo lib. 6
          </ref> 
          it applies that 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e390">
            Bartholus notes in l. quicunque C. de servis fugitiuis
          </ref> 
          where he says that wherever it speaks of capital or corporal penalty,
          guile is understood.
          Therefore by stronger reason in this penalty which kills the soul,
          mutilating it from the living body (that is) the holy Church.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e400">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore those peoples by not believing that the Pope could make the said institution:
          or by not admitting it nor giving consent,
          will not contract any heresy:
          nor commit contumacy.
          But it stands well that they do not believe this or doubt it,
          and do not admit that,
          nor wish to receive our kings as universal superiors:
          and are Catholic and obedient children to apostolic commands.
          Thence it follows consequently:
          that neither by ecclesiastical penalties or censures:
          as by temporal ones ought they to be punished or molested.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e421">
          And thus the truth of the conclusion situated at the beginning of § 22 is evident.
          Moreover it is manifestly evident how necessary it is for our kings 
          that most gently and most sweetly,
          by good reasons and persuasions,
          those peoples be induced to receive them by free consent:
          if they wish to rule rightly and correctly that world and its vast kingdoms:
          and thus this eleventh part,
          as contained under the order of divine and natural law,
          is not superfluous,
          but necessary,
          without which nothing juridical will be done.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e439">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And according to the aforesaid we wish to be understood and corrected 
          what we said in our 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e447">
            confirmatory treatise concerning royal law in the proof of the first conclusion 
            in the 2nd principal reason
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Qd1e453">
            namely that as soon as those peoples have received the sacred sacrament of baptism,
            our kings have complete power in act and can exercise contentious jurisdiction over them
          </quote> 
          etc.
          But it should be added there: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Qd1e466">
            and after they have given free consent just as has been prescribed
          </quote> 
          and what I said in the 19th proposition to the royal council of the Indies,
          namely that all the kings and natural lords,
          communities,
          cities and peoples of that world,
          after they have voluntarily received the faith,
          are bound to recognize our kings as emperors and universal lords,
          nevertheless preserving the rights and dominions of the natural kings and lords 
          and peoples and other individual persons,
          as was contained in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e484">the 18th proposition</ref>.
          But if before 
          <pb ed="#B" n="71-v"/>
          baptism they are unwilling,
          they can be punished by right by no judge in the world on this account.
          Where it seemed to be supposed that after baptism was received,
          if they did not recognize,
          they could be compelled and punished.
          Nevertheless we wish this passage to be understood thus (namely) 
          that both after baptism and before,
          if they are unwilling to receive our kings as supreme princes,
          there is no judge in the world who has power to punish them for this cause.
          As is left determined in the conclusion posited above and its proof.
          Since in their natural faculty they have the right of consenting or dissenting 
          to the often-said papal institution in both their states (namely) 
          either before or after their conversion,
          as from very many things already proved this truth has been made evident,
          and they have many other exceptions if this cause should be brought 
          into contradictory judgment.
          Nevertheless they would have been obligated to receive our kings as princes 
          if they had not suffered evils,
          cruelties and irreparable damages and tyrannies from our Spaniards;
          if the faith had been preached to them peacefully and according to Christian form,
          by an obligation which is called to the antidote.
          Which obligation arises from that natural equity that we should do good 
          to one doing good to us 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e536">l. sed si lege. § consuluit. ff. de peti. here.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e542" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t26-d1e210">
            c. cum in officiis, De testamentis
          </ref> 
          Nor however is such an obligation like that natural one which has its origin from a pact.
          For on account of this no action is competent 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e549" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e1452-Dd1e155">
            l. etiam ff. de compensationibus
          </ref> 
          where such obligation to the antidote cannot be brought into compensation 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e557">l. ex hoc iure § penultim ff. de donationibus</ref> 
          concerning this see what is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-Rd1e563" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t19-Dd1e275">
            c. ad nostram de probationibus
          </ref> 
          We understand therefore in our said proposition 19 that natural kings are obligated 
          to our kings,
          and therefore let these things be supplied there.
          And let what has been said concerning the second state of those peoples,
          namely after they will be Christians and baptized,
          suffice.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e581">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But concerning their third state,
          namely after receiving unheard-of evils through our cruel tyranny,
          so many slaughters,
          so many devastations and destructions of peoples,
          towns and cities:
          indeed of kingdoms:
          which are now turned into deserts and made into solitude,
          a habitation of wild beasts:
          when they had been most full of mortals and other innumerable species of torments 
          (I am silent about the plunderings,
          captivities,
          stolen treasures,
          usurped dominions and dignities) 
          and infinite calamities of every kind,
          neither seen nor heard nor dreamed of anywhere on earth:
          which they have suffered from us without cause.
          If we speak I say concerning this state:
          the response is manifest which any person will give you,
          however much he may be reared in forests and barbarous by nature.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e621">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For he will say not only that they are not bound to receive our kings 
          over kingdoms not their own,
          as they are:
          but if they had been their own and patrimonial,
          brought down by legitimate succession:
          rightly and by law they are to be despoiled of them,
          and as public enemies to be pursued in war and tortured with most cruel death.
          For such an opinion those peoples have rightly conceived concerning our illustrious kings 
          of Spain:
          namely that they are strong kings,
          robust,
          impious,
          unmerciful:
          implacable and crueler and more unjust than all in the world,
          always thirsting for human blood:
          thinking that all the evils which they endure proceed from the very will 
          of those kings themselves.
          Which however is not true,
          as will be explained below.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e413-d1e657">
          And to finish these things:
          our kings can well abandon all hope:
          that they will ever hold the principate of that world safely without scruple of conscience:
          even if those peoples give consent:
          since the laws will always presume that they give it compelled by most just fear:
          but what is prior is very dangerous in the matter:
          that neither will it be sought from them,
          burdened as they are,
          on account of the insensibility of the counselors:
          nor will they themselves ever truly or interpretively give it.
          And now let anyone,
          even a barbarian,
          see and judge whether this part is not 
          (that by gentle and flattering words and reasons those peoples must be induced 
          to give consent) 
          so that our kings may rightly enter into the principate of that world:
          superfluous or necessary.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>