<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 4</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 4</title>
          <date when="2025-11-10">November 10, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library,
            Brown University,
            ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
                 url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-10" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Hd1e97">Section 4</head>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e99">
          § 4 With these things presupposed,
          the following Catholic conclusion is put forward: 
          General conclusion
        </p>
        <!-- possibly beginning of proposition 4; not clear -->
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e108">
          No one without mortal sin of theft or plunder 
          and obligation to restitution 
          can take with the intention of keeping for himself 
          any treasure improperly so called,
          whether it consists in money and coinage,
          or in vessels of gold or silver,
          or in furnishings and any other precious things 
          which owners have placed in whatever place,
          either in a shrine or in a temple or in a tomb or under the earth,
          however much it may have aged with antiquity,
          if the owner still survives 
          or any to whom it pertains to succeed by right.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e132">
          This conclusion is so Catholic 
          and manifest that it needs no proof;
          rather whoever would dare to deny it 
          will either be foolish or will not escape heresy. 
          And the reason for this conclusion is 
          that those treasures or riches or precious things 
          are another's property having proper owners,
          either those who placed them in the aforesaid places 
          or ordered them to be placed there 
          or their heirs. 
          But whoever takes or seizes another's property 
          against the owner's will 
          commits theft or indeed plunder 
          if violence is applied. 
          And the owner is said to be unwilling 
          even if he does not object out of fear or shame,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e157">
            ff. de furtis l. penultima
          </ref>. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e163">
          Therefore it is mortal sin,
          first because it is against justice. 
          But everything that is against justice 
          is mortal sin according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e169">
            Saint Thomas 2 2ae question 59
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e175">
          And also 
          because it is against the divine precept 
          where not only theft properly so called is prohibited 
          but also every illicit usurpation of another's property, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e181">
            Exodus 20
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e185">
            14, quaestione 5, c. penali
          </ref>,
          and specifically 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e190">
            c. si quid inuenisti
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e194">
            c. Multi
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e197">
            quaestione 6, c. 1
          </ref>,
          where it is said: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e202">
            If another's property 
            on account of which there is sin 
            can be returned and is not returned,
            penance is not done but feigned;
            but if it is truly done 
            the sin is not remitted 
            unless what was taken is restored
          </quote>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e213">
            regula peccatum de regulis iuris lib 6
          </ref>. 
          On these things 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e216">
            Raymundus in summa titulo de furtis §. 9
          </ref>,
          where likewise 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e221">
            quid si aliquis
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e224">
            panormitanus in capitulo finali de furtis
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e233">
          Therefore as regards our proposition 
          and the question proposed in the beginning,
          this responsive conclusion is put forward:
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e242">
          To no man in the world,
          not even to the king of Spain 
          (which we wish to be said 
          with all reverence 
          that we owe to the royal highness),
          without the license and free 
          and indeed gracious will of King Inca 
          or his descendants 
          to whom it pertained to succeed in their goods
          by right according to their laws or custom,
          is it permitted to inquire or search,
          to dig or to take treasures or riches or precious things 
          with the intention of keeping them 
          which they buried in tombs 
          and the so-called Guacas with their deceased. 
          If they have done the contrary 
          they will commit mortal sin of theft or plunder,
          and unless they restore them and do penance for their sin,
          it will be impossible to be saved. 
          And not only must they repent of the sin of theft or plunder 
          but also of the injury 
          which they inflict especially 
          upon the aforesaid successors or living descendants of theirs 
          whose tombs they violate,
          derogating from the honor and praise of both 
          (namely) the living and the dead 
          and causing their memory to cease 
          For this also they are bound to make satisfaction to them.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e299">
          Inca was the appellative name of the kings 
          or rather emperors of the kingdoms of Peru,
          just as the kings of Egypt were 
          formerly accustomed to be called Pharaohs,
          then <name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Nd1e308">Ptolemies</name>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e311">
          The first part of this conclusion is sufficiently clear 
          from what has already been said,
          namely that the treasures and precious things 
          found in tombs are another's property 
          and thus have owners,
          namely King Inca 
          who is the legitimate successor and heir of Huayna Capac,
          and indeed of a great and most prudent king 
          as all Spaniards dwelling in that region confess,
          who had succeeded many illustrious kings 
          who reigned happily in those kingdoms 
          for nearly nine hundred years. 
          There had also succeeded 
          the aforesaid Huayna Capac another of his sons,
          namely Atahualpa,
          in the kingdom which was called Quito,
          and of this one sons and daughters exist today. 
          Similarly, 
          there survive successors of the petty kings 
          who were subject to the rule of the kings Inca and Atahualpa 
          and had their tombs full of treasures 
          and diverse most precious furnishings. 
          Therefore, 
          without the license of Inca and Atahualpa 
          and the other petty kings having their tombs,
          it was licit to no one 
          to inquire, search, and take 
          with the intention of keeping 
          for themselves those precious things.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e354">
          The second part,
          namely that, 
          if they did the contrary,
          they would sin mortally with the sin of theft or plunder, 
          is clear.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e363">
          First because they act against justice.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e372">
          Second because they inflict injury upon them,
          taking from the dead and living 
          insofar as it is in them honor and fame 
          which consist in this,
          that the memory of their dead not be destroyed 
          but live perpetually in the opinions of men. 
          And this is a great interest of both 
          as has been proved through the first and second propositions.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e388">
          Third because they transgress the divine precept.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e393">
          Fourth because human laws also prohibit and punish it sharply,
          namely with the ultimate punishment,
          as appears in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e399">
            l. 2 § Diuus Adrianus ff. de sepulchro uiolato
          </ref>,
          where it is said thus: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e404">
            Against those who despoil corpses 
            governors are accustomed to intervene more severely,
            especially if they attack with armed force. 
            So that if they did it armed like bandits 
            they are even punished capitally.
          </quote> 
          Thus there,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e418">
            Codex eo titulo, l. pergit audacia
          </ref>,
          where also he 
          who takes away the clothing of the dead or ornaments of the tomb 
          is punished with the same penalty as a sacrilegist: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e425">
            if with arms capitally,
            if without arms he is condemned to the mines.
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e430">
          According to the laws of the kingdom of Castile, 
          the same is prohibited and punished by death,
          as is clear in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e440">
            l. 1a titulo 18, libro 11o
          </ref>,
          where these words are placed: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e439">
            <foreign xml:lang="es">
              He who breaks open the tomb of a dead person 
              and takes anything from there shall die for it;
              and if he takes nothing he shall pay one hundred gold sueldos,
              half to the King and the other half to the relatives of the deceased.
            </foreign>
          </quote> 
          Now each sueldo was worth one hundred and three gold pieces or ducats,
          as is had through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e459">
            the gloss on l. 1am titulo 5 lib. 2o fori
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e455">
          And because, 
          from the gravity of the penalty 
          which is inflicted in prohibition of some act, 
          the gravity of the fault is argued,
          therefore whenever human laws prohibit 
          some act under penalty of death or mutilation 
          or condemnation to the mines,
          always doing the contrary is mortal sin 
          according to the doctors and Saint Thomas,
          since human laws justly bind in the forum of conscience,
          because such a penalty is not inflicted 
          except for what would be very harmful to justice 
          and the good of the republic. 
          It applies to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e487">
            the aforesaid l. qui sepulchra Codex eo titulo
          </ref>,
          although there was little care,
          indeed none,
          by our magistrates in parts of the Indies 
          to order the execution of such laws,
          where it is said: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e497">
            Those who violate tombs,
            the houses (so to speak) of the dead,
            are seen to perpetrate a twofold crime. 
            For they both despoil the buried by destroying 
            and pollute the living by fabricating
          </quote>.
          They pollute,
          namely,
          by inflicting injury, etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e508">
          The third part of the conclusion,
          namely that unless 
          they restore the treasures 
          and other precious things 
          and all goods taken from the tombs 
          to their proper owners or heirs 
          and do penance for their sin,
          they cannot be saved,
          is clear from 
          the preceding general conclusion with its proof. 
          Nevertheless we wish to prove it again. 
          <!-- para break ? -->
          And it is argued first thus: 
          No one can be saved without penance after mortal sin. 
          But one detaining another's property 
          and not restoring it does not do penance 
          but feigns it,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e532">
            Augustine said to Macedonius
          </ref> 
          and is had in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e537">
            d. c. si res
          </ref>. 
          Therefore those who have taken or will take the aforesaid treasures 
          from tombs without the license of the owners,
          unless they restore them to those to whom they pertain,
          will die impenitent and consequently it will be impossible to be saved.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e548">
          Second it is argued thus: 
          without observance of justice 
          it is impossible for anyone to be saved. 
          But those taking the aforesaid treasures and riches 
          from another's tombs act against justice. 
          Therefore, 
          unless they restore them,
          which is an act of justice,
          it is impossible that they can be saved.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e565">
          Third it is argued: 
          it is impossible for anyone to be saved 
          unless mortal sin is forgiven him. 
          But to detain another's property 
          even for a moment against the owner's will 
          is a mortal sin just as to steal or seize,
          on account of which it is said in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e576">
            Ecclesiasticus 21
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e579">
            Flee from sin as from the face of a serpent.
          </quote> 
          But those not restoring the aforesaid things 
          which they steal or seize from tombs 
          are always in mortal sin. 
          Therefore, 
          it is impossible for them to be saved.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e589">
          Fourth: 
          it is impossible for anyone 
          who owes a debt of money to be saved 
          if he does not return or pay it,
          just as through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e596">
            the Apostle to the Romans 13
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e601">
            Render to all what is due,
            to whom tribute is due tribute,
            to whom tax tax,
            to whom honor honor,
            and owe nothing to anyone except to love one another
          </quote>.
          Whence having premised that debts should be rendered to all 
          lest perhaps he seem to have said too little 
          since this sounds like an affirmative precept,
          he added a negative: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e624">
            owe nothing to anyone
          </quote>, 
          as if to say: 
          <mentioned>
            You sin against God if you detain 
            against his will what you owe to anyone
          </mentioned>.
          But those who despoil tombs and take treasures from there 
          with the intention of keeping them for themselves 
          against the owners' will 
          are their debtors 
          and are obliged to render them 
          by divine precept. 
          Therefore, 
          if they do not render them, 
          it is impossible for them to be saved.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e639">
          Fifth it is argued: 
          None of those who inflict any notable harm on a neighbor 
          can be saved unless he repairs and removes it,
          since every harm inflicted on another 
          is of itself repugnant to or contrary to charity,
          which is the life of the soul 
          and moves to willing and doing the good of another. 
          But all those who take the aforesaid treasures 
          against the owners' will 
          inflict notable harm,
          namely impeding them from enjoying and rejoicing 
          in their goods and riches 
          which were placed in those tombs 
          for the honor, praise, and glory of themselves and their ancestors. 
          Likewise they inflict on them another greater harm,
          which is that the memory of their parents and themselves perish.
          Similarly honor and praise and glory and name and fame 
          in which they placed especially their whole interest and happiness 
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          are extinguished. 
          They are the cause, 
          whence they injure them greatly. 
          Therefore, 
          unless through restitution of so many treasures 
          taken against the owners' will 
          they remove and repair such harms,
          it is impossible for them to be saved. 
          For they lack charity and therefore have dead souls.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e689">
          The fourth part of the conclusion is also proved,
          namely that for the injury 
          which they inflict on the living and dead 
          they are bound to repent and to make satisfaction 
          as they are able. 
          As regards repenting it is clear,
          since from their mortal sin of theft or plunder 
          there follows in their neighbors that evil of injury,
          and this even if they did not have the intention of injuring 
          but only of stealing or seizing treasures,
          because he who gives occasion for damage 
          is seen to have given the damage itself, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e717">
            c. si culpa de iniuriis et damno dato
          </ref>. 
          But if they intended to inflict injury 
          for the sake of diminishing honor or opinion,
          <!-- TODO: trans triage -->
          beyond the sin,
          because it is against charity for neighbor 
          whom we are bound to love as ourselves, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e728">
            Matthew 22
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e731">
            8, questione 1, c. in scripturis
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e736">
            de penitentia, dist. 2, c. charitas el. 2o
          </ref>, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e744">
            Codex, de iniuriis, l. si non es nunciator
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e749">
          Indeed as regards making satisfaction 
          as one is able,
          by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e756">
            d. c. si culpa
          </ref>,
          where it is said thus: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e762">
            If by your fault damage was given or injury inflicted,
            or perhaps you gave aid to others inflicting them,
            or these things happened through your inexperience or negligence,
            by right it is necessary to make satisfaction for these things,
            nor does ignorance excuse you if you ought to have known 
            that from your deed injury could most likely happen or loss.
          </quote> 
          Thus there. 
          The reason for which is according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e776">
            Saint Thomas
          </ref>,
          who will be alleged below: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e778">
            because restitution and satisfaction are distinct. 
            For restitution is not part of satisfaction. 
            And therefore a man harming a neighbor 
            is not reconciled to him for an offense or injury through this,
            that he restores his things to him,
            but through this,
            that above this he shows him something of humility.
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e790">
          That moreover the aforesaid thieves 
          or rather robbers or plunderers 
          have committed injury and such loss is proved,
          because they take from the deceased 
          their whole perpetual being,
          namely to live in the memory and opinions of men,
          and consequently they totally take away from the living honor,
          praise and glory. 
          And this is a most atrocious injury to both, 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e808">
            instit. de iniuriis, § atrox
          </ref>. 
          And this injury is so much graver 
          as it redounds to more people. 
          Just as that which is inflicted on a prince 
          is graver than that on some private person,
          because it redounds to the injury of the whole multitude.
          Since therefore this injury redounds to the whole house,
          progeny or royal kinship of those kings and petty kings,
          indeed to the universal communities of their kingdoms,
          as appears from what has been said,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e830">
            argumentum de legatis 3, l. nutu, in fine
          </ref>;
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e836">
            argumentum 32, q. 7, capitulo offerebat
          </ref>,
          and disgrace is done to the whole kinship's splendor, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e840">
            l. 1, Codex, de senatus consultis
          </ref>,
          closing by taking away. 
          Therefore other things being equal,
          from this very fact such injury is greatly aggravated, 
          on this 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e849">
            S. Thomas 2 2e q. 65 a. 4
          </ref> 
          and elsewhere. 
          Whence for this injury inflicted 
          not only all descendants and the whole royal kinship 
          but also the universal communities of those kingdoms 
          can act in their own name for injury against them, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e862">
            ff. quando appellandum sit l. 2, § pen.
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e865">
            § fine
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e870">
            De appellationibus, l. non tantum
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e873">
            de iniuriis, l. cum possit
          </ref>. 
          For injury is done to the house,
          and there are three laws 1 and 2 and 3 
          most excellent for the proposition, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e881">
            ff. de liberali causa
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e887">
            ff. Qui et aduersus quos, l. in fine
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e896">
          Would it not be injurious among us 
          to take away the standards, shields, insignia 
          of nobles and magnates of Spain,
          and far more of kings,
          which they are accustomed to store in chapels of churches,
          and moreover tombs or monuments 
          especially when they are covered with gold-woven or silk cloths 
          or adorned with other precious furnishings 
          or with golden or silver vessels? 
          Certainly no one of the nobles of Spain 
          at least (whatever it may be among other nations) would not bear it very ill 
          and would not try as he is able to avenge this injury most fiercely,
          considering that 
          his proper honor and the glory 
          and praise and fame of his predecessors 
          are greatly harmed. 
          For that pertains (as has often been said) 
          to the diminution or rather deletion of 
          the honor and glory or fame of the living and dead. 
          And this is a great interest of both. 
          Therefore, 
          it is necessary for those thus harming 
          to make satisfaction for the injury beyond the necessary restitution.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e936">
          And if it is acted upon juridically also civilly,
          it will stand by the oath of the living 
          as regards estimation as legitimate proof, 
          as is clear in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e951">
            c. olim de iniuriis et damno dato
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e954">
            C. Unde vi, l. si quando
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e957">
            2, q. 1, c. in primis
          </ref>;
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e959">
            de his que ui met. cau. fi, c. ultimo
          </ref>. 
          And the oath ought to be of this form: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e964">
            We so-and-so swear that we would prefer 
            to lose so many thousands of our own 
            rather than to have suffered such an injury.
          </quote> 
          Moreover the estimation of injury increases or decreases 
          according to the degree of dignity of the person suffering injury, 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e975">
            d. § attrox et § pena insti. de iniuriis
          </ref>. 
          For it is manifest in our case 
          that reasonably and probably anyone will judge 
          that since those to whom the injury was inflicted 
          were kings and great and most powerful and most wealthy lords,
          and they valued their tombs so highly on account of honor, praise, and glory,
          as things to be preferred to all wealth and preeminence even when dead,
          as is clear from what has been said,
          the estimation which they would make of the injuries 
          which they have suffered in such matters 
          from our people would not be just anything 
          but thousands of thousands and hundreds of hundreds of thousands. 
          Since truly such estimation among them 
          and also among Philosophers and any wise men of this world 
          has no comparison. 
          Therefore there remains for such plunderers 
          beyond the restitution of so many stolen treasures 
          great satisfaction,
          and thus the way of being saved.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e1014">
          But if it is dealt with in the forum of conscience concerning such injuries,
          since they are not estimable with a price,
          they are bound to placate those thus harmed 
          as much as would be possible for them,
          settling with them about the injuries done to them 
          by themselves and humbly seeking pardon. 
          And we ought to use this mode of satisfying 
          especially whenever damage or injury 
          inflicted on neighbors cannot be fully recompensed. 
          These things are proved by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1040">
            d. C. olim de iniuriis
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1044" >
            S. Thomam 2 2e q. 62 articulo 2 ad 1m
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1048" >
            ad 3m
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1051" >
            4 sententiarum dist. 18 q. 1 articulo 5 quaesticula 1a in corpore
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1056" >
            ad 1m
          </ref>. 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1059" >
            hostiensis in summa titulo de iniuriis § contra quos detur
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1064" >
            § inquantum detur
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1068">
            Raymundus and his gloss
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1078">
            Ulricus in summa confessorum, lib. 2 titul. 5 q. 65
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1080">
            The Holy Archbishop of Florence also in 2a parte titulo 2, c. 2, § 3
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1085">
            Astesanus similarly prima parte sue summe libro 2o titulo 14
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1090">
            Adrian finally in 4o speaking about restitution of reputation
          </ref>. 
          And thus the fourth part of the conclusion is clear,
          and since the whole responsive conclusion to the question is sufficiently clear.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e1102">
          Likewise the law is in all respects 
          the same concerning treasures and precious things 
          if any are found in temples of idols 
          which they venerated as their gods in their infidelity or idolatry,
          as concerning those which were placed in the tombs of their ancestors, 
          namely that they did not hold them as abandoned things 
          nor did they renounce ownership of them,
          nor now after their conversion are they vacant,
          but they have owners,
          namely either those who offered them to the idols in person 
          if they survive or their heirs 
          to whom it pertains to succeed by hereditary right 
          according to their laws or customs.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e1130">
          This is proved because 
          if they offered them to their false gods,
          this without doubt was understood 
          to be offered under a tacit condition,
          namely if that or those to whom they sacrificed such things were the true god,
          and thus esteeming him the true god,
          since the intention of the gentiles 
          especially tends principally and finally 
          to worshipping the true God whom they know,
          although confusedly,
          naturally. 
          Thus Jerome says on Psalm 95: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e1145">
            Thus both we and the whole human race naturally understand God. 
            For there are no nations which do not naturally understand their creator. 
            For although they venerate stones and wood,
            nevertheless they understand that something is greater than they are,
            and in their error they judge themselves to have wisdom,
            that is,
            there is no nation which does not naturally understand God. 
            Finally the gentiles worship idols,
            that is they venerate stones and wood,
            and if perhaps they make a quarrel and if any oath comes among them,
            they do not say "these stones see," "the wood sees," but "God sees and God hears."
          </quote> 
          Thus Jerome in form.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e1181">
          A certain Roman idolater,
          a grammarian named Maximus,
          writing to Augustine,
          strove to show this same thing: 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Qd1e1192">
            Indeed (he says) who so demented,
            so captive in mind,
            would deny it to be most certain 
            that there is one God without beginning,
            without offspring of nature,
            or a great and magnificent father? 
            We invoke his powers 
            diffused through the work of the world with many names,
            since we all are ignorant of his proper name. 
            For God is a name common to all religions. 
            Thus it happens that 
            while we pursue as it were certain members of him piecemeal 
            with various supplications,
            we are seen to worship the whole
          </quote> 
          etc. 
          Thus he in the epistle which is numbered among 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1216">
            Augustine's epistles as 43
          </ref>. 
          Since therefore they offered 
          to others who were not gods,
          esteeming that they were offering to the true God 
          so that they might worship and venerate him,
          after now by God's grace 
          they have received the faith 
          and know that they were deceived in doing this,
          it is manifest that they can recover and reclaim those things,
          since they did not place them there with that mind,
          thinking through error that they were gods,
          with a tacit or implicit condition 
          that if they were not true gods or god,
          in no way would they otherwise have offered them,
          and consequently they did not lose ownership of those things. 
          This is clear in one who gives what is not owed by all right 
          to one through ignorance or error,
          thinking to give to another,
          since error excludes his free will. 
          For every error induces repetition,
          and thus it is understood indistinctly, 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1242" >
            l. cuius per errorem, ff, de regulis iuris
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1247" >
            Codex, De conditione indebiti, l. 1
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1250" >
            l. cum et soluta
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1255">
            through that whole title
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1261">
            ff.
          </ref> 
          and through the whole and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1266">
            Codex de iure et facti ignorantia, L. cum quis
          </ref>,
          where 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-Rd1e1268">
            a great gloss is noted in cap. finali de solutione
          </ref>. 
          Since therefore with a tacit condition,
          although not excusing,
          every idolater is seen to worship idols,
          thinking through error 
          that he venerates the true God and offers to him 
          his immolations or sacrifices,
          to which sacrifices in common natural reason 
          they see themselves to be obliged 
          — which if they knew they erred,
          natural reason itself would draw them back from idolatry — 
          it follows manifestly that through error 
          they placed those precious things 
          unowed in temples to the honor of false gods,
          certainly not going to place them 
          if they knew the error,
          and therefore there is no doubt that,
          as we said,
          they can reclaim them. 
          Since just as knowing the error 
          they would not offer them,
          so without doubt 
          they would not cast away their ownership of them. 
          Therefore they are still their owners,
          and they can reclaim them as their own things. 
          This will also able to be confirmed through an example of this kind: 
          Let a case be given within our Christian religion 
          that some Christian was in such error 
          that he thought that those things
          which he offered in church to the honor of God 
          and for celebrating divine worship 
          — chalices and other vessels 
          either golden or silver 
          or gold-woven or silken — 
          did not please God and would profit him nothing after this life,
          it seems manifest 
          that he would surely not have 
          cast away ownership of those things from himself 
          in his intention nor held them as abandoned things. 
          Since even if he offered them in church 
          so that divine worship would be celebrated honorably,
          this however presupposing a tacit and implicit condition 
          if they pleased God and so that he might receive a reward in the other life,
          otherwise certainly he would not have offered them in vain,
          reason itself compels us to understand. 
          But if, 
          by the impossible, 
          that error were confirmed by someone 
          to whose authority and faith deference should deservedly be given,
          there would be no one of the gentile philosophers having judgment of prudence,
          if he were constituted judge of this controversy,
          who judging justly would not decree those offered goods 
          to be restored to him as proper and having ownership of them.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e111-d1e1350">
          It appears therefore no less,
          or by equal and perhaps stronger reason,
          that treasures and other riches and precious furnishings 
          which are found and have been found or will be found in future time 
          in the temples formerly of idols and were offered in honor of the gods 
          in the time of their infidelity 
          pertain to those who offered them or their heirs,
          just as those which are or will be found or discovered in tombs.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
