<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 13</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 13</title>
          <date when="2026-01-02">January 02, 2026</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2026-01-02" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="35-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Hd1e97">Section 13</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e99">
          § 13
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e104">
          Part 5
          Humble and gracious greeting and address etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e116">
          Namely,
          that by showing just and due honor and reverence to princes and lords,
          or to magistrates of places or peoples,
          they may attract and win over their minds,
          and thus be considered peaceful and humane men.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e127">
          For men are accustomed in the beginnings of their words,
          especially to strangers,
          to use greeting out of courtesy:
          so that the invocation of good things which is made through greeting may be the beginning of their speech.
          Moreover,
          one who does not use a benevolent greeting is judged to be rude and uncouth.
          Hence,
          greeting is now almost necessary among men by custom in the beginnings of speeches:
          and therefore Christ instructed the Apostles that they should precede others in greeting,
          because it is a virtue to bestow honor before receiving it;
          on account of which 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e148">at Romans 12 the apostle said</ref>
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e153" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom12_10@5-7">Let each of you outdo one another in showing honor</quote>
          that is,
          let each one strive to honor the other before being honored by him.
          Thus said 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e160">Chrysostom in homily 31 on Matthew</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e162">Do not think that because you are teachers it is therefore necessary for you to wait until a greeting is brought to you by them:
          but rather you should precede them in honor and greet them first</quote>
          these are his words
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e181">
          And that honor and reverence is owed even by the faithful to the kings of unbelievers was shown at length above in the first consideration.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e189">
          Part 6
          Exemplary,
          gentle and Christian conduct,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e201">
          ¶ Since the norm of living well and right works is necessary,
          so that we may gain the nations which do not know God:
          and thus our kings,
          to whom this pertains,
          may enjoy the attainment of the intended end.
          For the works of Christians,
          even if few,
          are more efficacious for the conversion of unbelievers,
          than words however persuasive they may be and however numerous.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e222">
          Indeed,
          there would be no need for words if our life shone with the light of holiness,
          whence Chrysostom,
          on the first chapter of Genesis,
          homily 8,
          says thus:
          for God does not wish that a Christian should be content with himself alone,
          but that he should edify others not through teaching alone but also through life and conduct.
          Nor does he lead us into the way of truth so much as into care for life.
          For what we do is not considered as much as what we say.
          And so that you may know that this is the case,
          though we may philosophize infinitely with words and discourse on patience,
          and when the time comes we do not demonstrate it with works,
          words will not profit as much as works will harm.
          But if after words we exhibit a specimen of works,
          we shall be deemed worthy to admonish others of those things which we fulfill through works;
          because Christ called those blessed,
          saying,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e260">Blessed is he who does and teaches</quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e262">Matthew 5.</ref>
          See that he placed work first:
          and then teaching.
          And so,
          with work preceding,
          even if teaching does not follow:
          the works themselves suffice more clearly than light to teach those who look upon us.
          Therefore let us consider this in all ways,
          that we teach first by works and then by words:
          so that we may not also hear from 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e279">blessed Paul</ref>,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e275">You who teach another,
          do you not teach yourself?</quote>
          And when we wish to admonish another to do something necessary in an honest manner:
          let us first strive to do this same thing ourselves,
          whereby we may have greater confidence in speaking:
          and let all our care be in the salvation of souls.
          And in whatever way we can,
          let us restrain the lusts of the flesh,
          etc.
          these are Chrysostom's words
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e284">
          ¶ Indeed,
          the norm which the first messengers of our kings ought to maintain when entering those parts of the Indies,
          so that the necessary order of entering them may be observed,
          is set forth fully by the 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e303">apostle at 2 Thessalonians chapter</ref>
          among other things saying:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e299">You are witnesses,
          and God,
          how holily and blamelessly and justly and without complaint we were among you who believed</quote>:
          thus before as after your conversion,
          as the 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e318">interlinear gloss</ref>
          says,
          etc.
          How holily (that is) toward God according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e322">the same gloss</ref>
          and according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e324">Athanasius</ref>
          (that is) observing all things necessary to be done in piety and worship toward God;
          but according to Anselm,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e314">how holily:
          with regard to the purity of our most clean conduct we were to you;
          how justly (namely) toward our neighbor,
          doing what is due and not doing what is undue</quote>.
          According to the interlinear gloss or according to Athanasius:
          that is,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e326">inflicting injury on no one by demanding money.
          And without complaint,
          without offense of any kind</quote>.
          Or according to Anselm,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e338">how justly,
          with regard to maintaining equity toward neighbors,
          doing what is due;
          and how without complaint (that is) how innocently and irreproachably we were to you,
          because we did nothing to you on account of which you could complain about us:
          or we were without complaint to you because we never complained about you when we bore your weakness;
          in such a manner we conducted ourselves toward you (that is) for your benefit,
          as you yourselves know</quote>
          etc.
          And in the 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e356">later epistle to the Thessalonians chapter 3</ref>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e378">Anselm</ref>
          says on that passage,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e360">you yourselves know</quote>
          etc.
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e363">It is not necessary that I explain to you that tradition,
          because you know it.
          You know,
          namely,
          how those who wish to walk rightly ought to walk through the way by which we walk,
          that is,
          follow our examples</quote>
          these are his words.
          But Polycarp,
          the disciple of blessed John the Evangelist,
          in his 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e394">epistle to the Philippians</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e374">Considering your conduct irreproachable among the nations,
          so that from your good works you yourselves may receive praise and the Lord may not be blasphemed in you.
          But woe to that man through whom the name of the Lord is blasphemed</quote>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e384">
          ¶ Therefore the preliminary form of drawing unbelievers to Christ is clear:
          namely,
          holy life and exemplary conduct shining with virtuous works and without offense,
          whose piety and in every way from every part is irreproachable.
          For he who intends to teach others ought to put forth exemplary works of his words,
          so that he may teach more by work than by speech:
          just as the apostles who taught first by examples of life,
          then by words.
          Indeed,
          there was no need even for words when the works cried out.
          And so much did their works testify to living a most holy life,
          that no one would indeed criticize their life,
          but they detracted from their preaching,
          according to Chrysostom:
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e412">
          Finally,
          for the sake of preaching,
          they bore calumnies as if they were seducers.
          But hardly anyone ever presumed to vituperate their life.
          Wherefore,
          no one ever charged the apostles with the crime of fornication or shamelessness or avarice:
          but they called them only seducers,
          which only refers to doctrine.
          For whoever is conspicuous by the brilliance of life and venerable to them,
          it is necessary that truth itself also stop the mouths of enemies.
          Indeed,
          that it is not right to assail with curses and reproaches those who live irreproachably,
          you may hear Christ say,
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e437" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt5_16@2-19">Let your light shine before men,
          that they may see your good works and glorify your Father who is in heaven</quote>.
          Therefore,
          just as no one would call the sun dark,
          not even if he were blind:
          for he will be ashamed to oppose the opinions of men.
          So also no one presumes to blame him who is very conspicuous by beauty and illustrious by honesty of character.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e451">
          ¶ Therefore,
          let us so live that the name of God may not be blasphemed by the nations:
          nor indeed let us seek human glory,
          nor again let us lack the worst opinion;
          let us do what is good and right:
          but let us honor God in both ways.
          Shine among whom (he says 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e485">at Philippians 2</ref>)
          as lights in the world.
          For this reason indeed he chose us,
          that we should be as lights and become as leaven,
          and be made teachers of the rest:
          that we may live as angels among men on earth:
          as men with infants and children:
          as spiritual men with fleshly men:
          that they may acquire great profits from our company;
          that we may be seeds,
          so that we may bring forth the widest fruit.
          There would be no need for words if in this way our life shone with the light of holiness.
          There would be no need for teachers if we displayed honest acts of virtue.
          Indeed,
          no one would be a pagan,
          if we ourselves took care to be Christians as we ought;
          if we obeyed the commands and decrees of God;
          if,
          having suffered injuries,
          we did not repay in kind;
          if,
          provoked by curses,
          we blessed;
          if we repaid good things for evil.
          No one would be such a wild beast that he would not immediately run to the worship of true religion,
          if he saw these things being done by men.
          And so that you may learn that it is so,
          Paul was indeed one man,
          and he drew so many to the teaching of God.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e498">
          If we were all of this kind,
          how many worlds of lands could we ourselves attract.
          For disciples always look upon the life of their teachers;
          but if indeed they see us also desiring the same things with them,
          coveting the same things:
          seeking honors and primacy:
          how will they be able to admire the Christian religion?
          Behold,
          they see the reprehensible life of Christians,
          earthly minds and cast down to the ground;
          they admire money no differently than themselves.
          Indeed,
          even much more;
          they similarly dread death;
          they equally fear poverty;
          they bear diseases with the same impatience;
          they love glory and power no less than themselves;
          they destroy themselves for the sake of avarice;
          they serve themselves:
          whence will they be able to believe?
          Perhaps from signs?
          But these are not now done.
          Or truly for the sake of holiness of life?
          But that has plainly perished.
          Or for the sake of charity?
          But nowhere is any trace of it seen.
          Wherefore,
          we shall give an account not only of our sins but also of another's disadvantage,
          of which we ourselves are the cause.
          Let us come to our senses at last,
          let us be vigilant,
          I pray:
          let us display a heavenly manner of life on earth.
          Let us say with the apostle:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e544">Because our conversation is in heaven</quote>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e546">at Philippians 3</ref>.
          Let us undergo struggle and battle on earth.
          But perhaps you will say there were great men among us.
          But the pagan will respond and say:
          How shall I believe that?
          For I do not see you doing the same things which you proclaim those illustrious men did with words.
          For if it is right to believe such narrations everywhere,
          we ourselves could also bring forward great and admirable philosophers into the midst,
          for the sake of life and character.
          But show me Paul and another John.
          For now you are each prepared to kill for the sake of a penny.
          You stir up innumerable quarrels for the sake of an earthly clod,
          etc.
          All these things are from 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e595">Chrysostom on chapter 3 of the first to Timothy,
          homily 10.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e571">
          And on the first to Corinthians,
          homily 4,
          the same Chrysostom reasons thus:
          therefore in this way let us overthrow if we fight:
          and far more than by words,
          we shall strike their souls by the rectitude of life.
          This is the greatest struggle;
          this is the most certain syllogism which is accomplished through works.
          For even if we frequently philosophize with words,
          we would not therefore exhibit a better life;
          no profit would accrue to us.
          For men do not attend to words but scrutinize works and say:
          You first obey your words,
          then admonish others.
          And if you say that there are innumerable good things in the future age,
          and yet you seem to be attached to present things as if they were not,
          your works will persuade me more than words.
          For when I notice a plunderer of others' property grieving excessively for lost things,
          liable to many other crimes,
          for what reason shall I believe you about the resurrection?
          And although they do not say this,
          they nevertheless turn it over in thought and mind.
          And this is what prevents unbelievers from becoming Christians.
          Therefore,
          let us call them back by the example of our life.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e616">
          For many uneducated men in this way struck the minds of philosophers,
          as if they were showing philosophy by the thing itself:
          emitting a voice clearer than a trumpet by goodness of life and philosophy.
          For this very thing is more powerful than the tongue.
          When,
          therefore,
          I say that it is not permitted to be angry with anyone,
          and then I afflict the pagan with innumerable evils:
          in what way will I be able to attract him with words when I drive him away with works?
          Wherefore,
          let us attract them by integrity of life,
          and let us build the church through their souls,
          and let us acquire such riches.
          For nothing can be compared to the soul:
          not even the entire world,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e644">
          ¶ And in homily 9 on superstition to the people of Antioch:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e651">Meanwhile,
          it is necessary to say this to your charity:
          just as God glorified us through so great a creature,
          so also we glorify him through pure conduct.
          The heavens declare the glory of God:
          not so much speaking as being silent and bringing all things into admiration by the brightness of life.
          For let your light shine before men,
          that they may see your good works and glorify your Father who is in heaven.
          For when an unbeliever sees you,
          a believer,
          composed,
          modest,
          adorned,
          he will marvel and say:
          Truly great is the God of the Christians,
          what kind of men he has established,
          what he is like,
          what kind of men he has made.
          He has made angels out of men.
          If anyone makes an insult,
          they do not revile.
          If anyone strikes,
          they do not retaliate;
          they pray for those who have harmed them.
          They have no enemy.
          They do not know how to harbor anger;
          they have not learned to lie</quote>
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e688">
          And on Matthew 5 in the imperfect work:
          So let your light shine,
          etc.
          He who teaches (he says) and does what he teaches,
          truly teaches.
          But he who does not do what he teaches does not teach another but condemns himself.
          And it is better to do and not teach than to teach and not do.
          Because he who does,
          even if he is silent,
          corrects some people by example.
          But he who teaches and does not do not only corrects no one but still scandalizes many.
          For who would not be moved to sin if he sees the very teachers of piety sinning?
          Therefore,
          through those teachers who teach and do not do,
          God is blasphemed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e712">
          For example,
          if priests teach well and live better,
          seeing this,
          the pagans say:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e716">Blessed be God who has such servants.
          Truly their God is the true God</quote>.
          For unless he were just,
          he would never hold his people thus concerning justice.
          For the discipline of the lord is demonstrated by the character of the family.
          But if they teach well and conduct themselves badly,
          seeing this,
          they say:
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Qd1e731">What kind of God is theirs,
          who do such things?
          Would he tolerate them doing such things unless he consented to their works?</quote>
          You see how God is blasphemed through evil Christians.
          Nor can the lord have a good reputation who has a bad family.
          Whence it was said to the people of God:
          For the name of God is blasphemed among the nations through you,
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e779">Isaiah 52,</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e781">Ezekiel 36,</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-Rd1e783">Romans 2</ref>.
          These are from Chrysostom.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e752">
          We could cite many other testimonies both from Chrysostom himself and from Jerome,
          Cyprian and Augustine,
          and the teachings of other holy doctors in confirmation of the present conclusion of the part,
          namely that exemplary,
          gentle and Christian conduct is necessary,
          etc.,
          so that the entry of the Spaniards,
          especially the first entry,
          into those parts and kingdoms of the Indies may be ordered and not lack justice.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e229-d1e771">
          ¶ We have added in this part that there ought to be made an offering of some small gifts on the part of our king,
          so that their arrival may be more pleasing and acceptable to those kings and peoples,
          because by these things which are alluring,
          namely,
          they will begin to be affected toward our kings,
          and thus disposed to more easily give consent when it will be negotiated with them about receiving them as universal lords.
          Moreover,
          this offering of small gifts will be useful for more willingly hearing the preaching and receiving the faith:
          just as it is read of blessed Sylvester that he called Jews and other unbelievers to come to the faith by gifts and presents.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>