<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 25</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 25</title>
          <date when="2025-11-20">November 20, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">
            John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-11-20" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="62-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Hd1e97">Section 25</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e99">
          § 25
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Secondly,
          the minor of the principal reason posited above § 23 is principally proved,
          namely that those peoples,
          by not accepting the said papal institution concerning our kings,
          are moved by just and legitimate cause and by the authority of law.
          And it is proved thus.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e122">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          He has just and legitimate cause not to accept or at least to defer the command 
          of a prince or even the Pope,
          or any other ordinance:
          who by it thinks himself unjustly burdened:
          especially if that burden is upon the whole people or kingdom,
          and from it is feared that some great scandal will arise:
          or dangerous disturbance of the whole people or kingdom,
          or another similar evil to come.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e149">
          But those peoples and kingdoms,
          especially their princes and kings,
          even after they have received the faith,
          can reasonably consider themselves and theirs much unjustly burdened 
          by the often-said papal institution concerning the universal dominion 
          and jurisdiction of that entire world to our kings,
          and rightly fear great scandal and burden and most dangerous disturbances in the whole people,
          indeed in peoples and kingdoms,
          by accepting the said institution when they see themselves all to be subjected 
          to a foreign and unknown lord,
          which naturally instills fear in all men,
          and thus they can wonder about the mind and goodness and justice of the Pope:
          be disturbed and exasperated in their spirits.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e174">
          Therefore such peoples,
          nations and their kings have legitimate and reasonable cause not to admit 
          such papal institution,
          or at least to defer its acceptance etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e186">
          The consequence is noted with the Major and the proof of the Major 
          of the preceding reason.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e191">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The Minor is proved as regards the first part,
          <pb ed="#B" n="64-v"/>
          namely that they can reasonably consider themselves and theirs unjustly burdened etc.
          Because as was proved in the first reason,
          by no species of proofs,
          and thus neither by divine or natural law,
          nor even by civil and canon law,
          can it be proved to them:
          because in neither is it found to be provided:
          that for having care of their conversion and spiritual salvation they are obligated 
          to receive our kings,
          even foreigners,
          as universal lords:
          but rather on the contrary divine and natural law itself they have in their favor,
          as anyone moderately learned can understand for himself,
          and as we have explained in the said confirmatory treatise and more extensively in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e226">
            our book on the one way of calling all peoples to the true religion
          </ref>.
          It follows:
          that for their defense they can by right oppose the exception of unjust burden 
          and especially of injury:
          and truly feel and think themselves most gravely and very enormously injured.
          Since they are free kingdoms and peoples and subject to no one except their own lords:
          and their princes themselves not recognizing a superior,
          judging and reasonably feeling that the industry,
          care and expenses of our kings which they will undergo or have already undergone 
          for their conversion and reduction to Christ,
          they have offered to Christ himself freely according to the custom of Christians:
          just as they themselves received freely.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e258">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          For great burden and injury,
          indeed maximum,
          is judged by all men:
          to change lord or to recognize and have another superior and multiple lords,
          or that their lord be not free.
          As in c. fi. de dilationibus.
          And what the doctors note there and in c. suborta de re iudicata and in l. imperialem § preterea ducatus 
          de prohibita feudi alienatione per federicum and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e289">Innocent notes in c. auditis de prescriptionibus</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e295">
            Hostiensis and Panormitanus and Felinus,
            and others,
            in c. dilecti de maioritate et obedientia,
            and in c. fi. eo titulo
          </ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e300">
            the same Panormitanus in c. fin. de causa possessionis et proprietatis
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e306">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But if any people or city or province:
          or kingdom,
          even among ancient Christian peoples,
          should feel such burdens and injuries 
          <pb ed="#B" n="65-r"/>
          from the letters or rescript or any ordinance of the Pope,
          since it deviates at first sight from natural reason and is contrary to public utility,
          and which would prepare perpetual prejudice,
          to such letters,
          command or any ordinance they would justly and reasonably not obey,
          nor hold it as valid,
          even if they should have a second command.
          Therefore far more reasonably and justly those peoples and nations,
          even after they have received the faith,
          since then they will be tender and recent and neophytes,
          that is newly converted to the faith,
          can not hold the aforesaid institution as valid,
          nor accept it:
          or at least defer consent,
          indeed even resist it:
          by argument from the lesser which is valid in law as in c. quemadmodum § nam si potest 
          de iure iurando and in c. cum in cunctis de electione.
          The statement of John of Andrea applies that if by a privilege of the prince conceded 
          by his own motion some university happens to be gravely injured,
          the remedy of that same prince is to be implored concerning this,
          as is noted in c. suggestum de decimis and Panormitanus in c. 2, 
          de immunitate ecclesiarum column 5.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e359">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          To this purpose the notable opinion of Innocent in c. inquisitioni de sententia excomunicationis applies.
          Where he says that if the Pope commands a layman not subject to him temporally 
          that he should give his thing to someone,
          he is not bound to obey him if legitimate cause of obeying does not appear,
          since he is not subject to him temporally.
          Which statement applies to many things according to Panormitanus in c. que in ecclesiarum 
          de constitutionibus.
          To the same Clement. Pastoralis de re iudicata where it is weighed that the King of Sicily 
          was not subject to the emperor:
          you should add that even if he is subject to him,
          he can not obey:
          when there is not or does not appear legitimate cause,
          or at least await a second command according to what was predetermined.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e385">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The second part of the minor,
          namely that their princes and greater men rightly have cause to fear grave scandal 
          and dangerous disturbance,
          was proved in § 21 and will also be seen in § 30,
          in which several reasons were mentioned why rightly all the inhabitants of those 
          <pb ed="#B" n="65-v"/>
          regions can:
          be most fiercely disturbed:
          and implacably scandalized:
          Therefore they have just and reasonable cause not to accept the mentioned papal institution,
          or at least to defer such consent or acceptance.
          And thus the same as before.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e426">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Thirdly the same is principally proved thus.
          He has legitimate and reasonable cause not to obey,
          accept,
          or defer the command,
          letters or any ordinance of a prince or Pope:
          who is induced to not obeying,
          accepting or at least deferring by probable and just fear.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e448">
          But those peoples and nations with their princes and superiors are induced to not obeying,
          accepting and deferring consent to the aforesaid papal institution by probable and just fear.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e457">
          Therefore they have just and reasonable cause not to obey,
          accept,
          or at least defer,
          even after they have received the faith,
          the aforesaid institution,
          command or any ordinance.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e473">
          The Major is proved,
          because just fear,
          even probable,
          which otherwise according to the laws is called falling upon a steadfast man,
          which is the cause of present or future danger and trepidation of mind 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e481" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e567-d1e108">
            ff. quod metus causa, l. 1
          </ref> 
          namely when grave evil is feared gravely,
          that is from probable cause,
          excuses in all things which a man does because of just fear or fright,
          except sin,
          whence it excuses,
          annuls,
          rescinds and removes an act requiring free consent,
          as is evident through 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e504" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e567">
            the entire title ff. quod metus causa
          </ref>, 
          and by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e507" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t40-Dd1e123">
            cap. abbas
          </ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e510" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t40-Dd1e184">
            cap. dilectus extra que vi aut metus causa fiunt
          </ref>.
          So much so that a contract celebrated through fear in those things which require free consent:
          is null by the law itself,
          as is read and noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e524">l. similiter § fine ff. eo</ref> 
          and see 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e532">
            Panormitanus and others in c. veniens. El. 2 de sponsalibus
          </ref> 
          where it is evident that those things which are done through such fear regularly do not hold:
          provided someone falls into fear without his fault,
          and rescission of those things which have been done can be sought by the action 
          which fear caused,
          <pb ed="#B" n="66-r"/>
          as in the said laws.
          And those things which induce just fear or fright according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e551" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d29q1-d1e166">
            St. Thomas,
            in 4. distinction 29. question 1. article 2. argument 2.
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e557" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d29q1-d1e185">
            the body
          </ref>:
          are death,
          beatings and tortures as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e560">d. c. cum dilectus</ref> 
          dishonor through rape and servitude as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e566" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e567-Dd1e181">
            isti quidem ff. eodem
          </ref> 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e571">isti. eodem. § 1. 2. et 3.</ref> 
          and chains which lead back to servitude.
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e576" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e567-d1e172">
            l. neque timorem. ff. eodem
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e581">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Just fear is also inflicted by the loss of all or the greater part of temporal goods as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e596" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t40-Dd1e123">
            d. c. Abbas
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e600" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e607-d1e120">
            c. frequens. de restitatione spoliatorum. lib. 6
          </ref> 
          if someone cannot be sustained without the goods which he fears to lose.
          As is noted by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e607">Panormitanus and others in d. c. abbas.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e610">
            gloss in l. aduocati. C. de aduocatione diuersorum iudiciorum
          </ref> 
          notes that money is the life of man:
          and that temporal goods are nothing other than bodily life:
          whence just as fear of death excuses as was said,
          so fear of losing temporal goods or the greater part of them.
          And the reason is because if in odious matter all goods and the greater part of goods 
          are equated as in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e627" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e607-d1e120">
            d. c. frequens
          </ref>:
          the same seems true in a favorable case as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e635">Panormitanus notes in d. c. abbas.</ref> 
          Hence:
          that temporal goods as necessary always follow the condition of the person as in c. 1, 
          de iure patronatus and in authent. ingressi. C. De sacrosanctis ecclesiis.
          For our bodily life cannot be sustained without the help of temporal things.
          And on the contrary 1. q. 1 si quis obiecerit. and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e649">gloss in d. c. abbas</ref>.
          And from this not only when someone cannot live without those things:
          but also when he suffers grave loss.
          And for this 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e659" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d50-Dd1e597">
            c. presbyteros 50 distinctione
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e664">l. penultima. C. eodem</ref> 
          apply.
          And the aforesaid have such an effect of excusing:
          even if they are only in threat and not inflicted,
          when it is probably estimated that it will be so.
          Argument of those things which are noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e679" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t40-Dd1e184">
            d. cap. cum dilectus de his que vi metuve fiunt
          </ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e684">
          Whence threatening words or mere requests of a tyrant induce just fear,
          who was accustomed to treat badly men not acquiescing to his prayers.
          For then prayers alone instill just fear.
          It is noted by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e699">the gloss and doctors in d. c. cum dilectus.</ref> 
          Therefore the judge ought to consider the person threatening.
          For there are some men who 
          <pb ed="#B" n="66-v"/>
          threaten and immediately execute,
          and others threaten much and do nothing,
          as Bartholus notes in tractatu de tyrano and Innocent.
          And Hostiensis and others in d. c. cum dilectus.
          The threats and terrors of the powerful also inflict just fear:
          and this if such powerful people are wont to rage after threats:
          otherwise threats would not excuse.
          Bartholus in d. l. metum. 
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          The same is understood of threats and terrors of a husband or prelate.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e726">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And the aforesaid are understood if they or any of the aforesaid threaten one's own person:
          or of children,
          or wife and such according to St. Thomas where above article 2 and in d. l. isti quidem, 
          ff. eodem
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e738">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          But the minor,
          namely that those peoples are induced to not accepting the said institution by just fear etc.
          Is proved because as was said above and will be said:
          the first step by which the Spaniards entered those regions was that unexpectedly 
          they invaded those peoples existing peacefully in their homes,
          with unheard-of slaughters,
          fires,
          swords,
          massacres,
          robberies,
          sparing no sex or age or dignity,
          killing them,
          also cruelly devastating everything:
          and they filled that entire world with scandals and disturbances,
          cries,
          mournings,
          lamentations and fears:
          principally displaying nothing other than to strike fear and horror of themselves 
          into the spirits of the innocent:
          so that afterward they might safely hold them in most bitter servitude at will.
          Surely if they had not yet experienced the unjust,
          cruel and execrable customs of the Spaniards,
          most justly and most deservedly they could still fear and very much dread 
          that the aforesaid evils inducing just fear threaten themselves and theirs:
          seeing a barbarous,
          unknown and robust race:
          and terrible to them in appearance,
          surrounded by such efficacious arms:
          and most distant from them in customs:
          and suspecting that they must whether they wish it or not enter into association with them,
          and must receive them in their own lands and homes to dwell perpetually.
          For it can be doubtful to no one of sound mind that it persuades itself that such peoples 
          must necessarily be moved by probable and just fear 
          <pb ed="#B" n="67-r"/>
          and horribly shaken:
          lest from such a fierce race of Spaniards:
          their goods:
          dominions:
          dignities:
          and jurisdictions be snatched away:
          beatings:
          and tortures:
          chains,
          dishonorations through rapes and adulteries:
          servitude moreover be inflicted on their own persons and of their children and wives:
          and death,
          as most fully and most woefully has been done,
          alas.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e833">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          And if you add that greater and more probable fear will be made to all peoples,
          great and small,
          namely the uncertainty of the integrity,
          rectitude and affection toward them of the future prince or lord:
          then there will be fuller proof of the minor proposition.
          For it was said above. 
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          25 that Kings of another foreign and unknown race are wont to be little affectionate 
          toward the people to whom they are newly placed over.
          And thus not to care much about them:
          but to unjustly burden them with undue burdens and oppressive extortions,
          and sometimes to afflict them unmercifully even to the exhaling of the souls of subjects.
          And from this they could and can rightly much fear.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e867">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Because therefore not only is what is considered:
          but what can be:
          because outcomes are in the consideration of men 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e875" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e2305-Dd1e919">
            l. pater filio: ff. de heredibus instituendis
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e878" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e4700-d1e427">
            l. aut facta § euentus ff. de poenis
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e887">
            § posteriore instit quibus modis testamenta infirmantur
          </ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-Rd1e894" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e3291-d1e462">
            l. generaliter § si libero homini ff. de fideicommissaris libertatibus
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e900">
          Therefore it must be concluded that the minor is sufficiently proved,
          namely that those peoples and nations with their kings or princes and superiors,
          even after they have received the faith,
          are induced to not obeying or accepting,
          or at least deferring consent to the papal institution concerning our kings:
          by probable and just fear.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e387-d1e914">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> 
          Therefore the truth of our principal minor proposition remains clear and unshaken,
          namely that the peoples of those regions have most just and very reasonable cause:
          not to accept the mentioned papal institution even after they have received the faith:
          or at least to defer and suspend consent:
          and consequently they do not deserve penalties,
          neither temporal nor ecclesiastical.
          Therefore it is lawful to no one to inflict them,
          no more after they have received the faith:
          <pb ed="#B" n="67-v"/>
          than while they were infidels.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>