<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Section 34</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Section 34</title>
          <date when="2025-12-13">December 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="cod-hgy7ss">John Carter Brown Library, Brown University, ms Codex Sp 5</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="92-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506">
        <head xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Hd1e97">Section 34</head>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e99">
          § 34
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> The conclusion is proven because nothing legally valid was done after the 
          promulgation of the aforesaid institution carried out in Rome,
          up to the present day regarding the entry and progress of the Spaniards throughout that 
          entire world:
          but all things were and remain legally null
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e117">
          therefore our Kings now stand in that condition just as if the papal institution were now 
          being promulgated in Rome etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e124">
          The consequence is clear. 
          <pb ed="#B" n="92-v"/>
          The antecedent is proven in many ways. First,
          because the Spanish messengers of our kings,
          contrary to the law of nations and natural and divine law,
          without cause or reason in the manner of brigands,
          made their first work from which they began their mission to invade those kingdoms 
          living peacefully in a hostile and impious manner:
          fields dripping with human blood on their hands. Where there was no count of those 
          slaughtered of either sex and age and dignity nor of those who were led captive to cruel 
          servitude as to a slaughterhouse
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e156">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> As has long been known throughout the entire world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e164">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Second,
          because the order of law and those things which must necessarily be observed under it,
          namely those twelve things which are enumerated in conclusion 2,
          were never observed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e179">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Third,
          because since all things which these men perpetrated in their entry and progress 
          throughout that entire world were the works of cruel tyrants:
          it is manifest that all things are null,
          about which no one who is of sound mind doubts.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e191">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Fourth,
          because those peoples never consented to the aforesaid institution concerning our kings,
          nor did they give consent to any matter which would grant some right to the Spaniards or 
          the kings of Spain.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e203">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Fifth,
          because no king or people of that entire world recognized the kings of Spain as lords or 
          supreme princes.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e214">
          Sixth,
          because they never voluntarily handed over possessions either of that world or of any part 
          of it,
          although they were the true lords and proprietors. But they were violently and contrary to 
          the order of natural and divine law despoiled of these things.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e226">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Seventh,
          because they occupied and the Spaniards usurped the kingdoms and provinces which were 
          accustomed to be ruled by their natural kings and princes and were under their natural 
          lordship,
          that is by the law of nations:
          against the will of their kings and natural lords,
          which is properly characteristic of tyrants,
          because usurped dominions are called tyrannies 
          <pb ed="#B" n="93-r"/>
          therefore all things remained legally null. As is clear from what is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e248">l. decernimus C. de sacrosanctis ecclesiis</ref>
          and above all things exist broadly proven
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e254">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Eighth and finally:
          because everything that the Spaniards perpetrated in that world from the beginning of its 
          discovery until now:
          and those peoples suffered from them,
          was always instilling terrible fear in the most steadfast men,
          as appears from very many things said and is most well known,
          therefore all things were of no validity.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e274">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> The reason for the nullity of all the aforesaid is because they lack 
          the foundation of power and jurisdiction,
          even if kings and powerful men of the world they may be in their kingdoms,
          having all manner of power:
          because in evil and unjust acts they are reduced to the status of private persons as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e290">l. 3 de officio presidis</ref>
          and in regula ea que Cum ibi notatis 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e294">de regulis iuris lib. 6</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e297">
          For jurisdiction is the substance and foundation of all things which a King or ruler or any 
          judge does in the entire republic,
          which ought to precede the office of the one declaring law. For it is born before it is 
          exercised into act as is clear 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e307">C. qui pro sua iurisdictione l. 1</ref>
          and note in 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e310">l. instar C. de iure fisci lib. 10</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e313">
          therefore where there is no jurisdiction or whose jurisdiction on account of the injustice 
          which he commits,
          abusing his jurisdiction,
          is suspended,
          things done do not stand by force:
          because he is private 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e322">D. l. 3 ff. de officio presidis</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e328">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Therefore,
          since the messengers of our kings had no jurisdiction,
          which if they had had would have been suspended on account of their horrible works:
          but they were private persons and truly tyrants existed and most true bandits,
          who would dare to doubt that all things done by them,
          whatever they may be,
          are null and of no strength or validity
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e349">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> For nullity,
          if taken in the concrete,
          is a vice or defect of the thing done arising from transgression of law. But if it is taken 
          as in the abstract and in the faculty of acting and legal remedy and subject:
          thus it is described 
          <pb ed="#B" n="93-v"/>
          (according to 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e368">Sebastianus Vantius in his treatise de nullitatibus</ref>) 
          it is a right and common remedy for voiding or declaring void the act which is in question,
          pertaining to the matter
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e380">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> After the establishment of law arose the cognition and remedy of 
          nullity. For the law would have been established in vain if against its transgressors and in 
          favor of public law and the oppressed some salutary remedy had not arrived. For anyone 
          could have been deprived and despoiled of their property and proper patrimony unheard,
          with no preceding cause and cognition,
          even by a non-judge,
          contrary to natural justice and the proper substance of law according to what 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e404" target="http://scta.info/resource/inleiv-d1e71-Dd1e781">Innocentius</ref>
          placed in c. que in ecclesiarum de constitutionibus. And thus deprived and despoiled,
          as if naked and unarmed without help and the support of law,
          they would have remained. Therefore,
          through this remedy those not summoned shall be summoned,
          those not heard shall be heard,
          those not defended shall be defended,
          the merits of causes shall be examined,
          and all deceit,
          fraud and machination shall be excluded:
          and innocence shall remain safe among the wicked. And therefore not undeservedly the law 
          calls this remedy a common help and holds it to be a mere defense according to the 
          doctors.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e438">
          Therefore nullity is a remedy of law,
          the protection of laws,
          the punishment of the rash,
          a common help and true defense of the oppressed,
          and introduced on account of a public cause. And since God has given no power to men,
          even to kings or princes,
          however much they shine with dignity,
          of doing injustice and iniquity to the ruin or damage or prejudice of men. Therefore 
          against the evils which,
          abusing the power handed over to them by God,
          especially princes and great men work:
          no other remedy can be imagined except that whatever unjust thing they have done contrary 
          to natural or divine law does not stand by law:
          as 
          <pb ed="#B" n="94-r"/>
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e478"><name xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Nd1e479">Prepositus</name>
          in c. si dominus 11 q. 3</ref>
          notably says,
          where he says That if the iniquity and injustice which the supreme prince commits depends 
          on such a law by which the prince is bound,
          such as the law of nations or natural or divine law:
          and then because the pope,
          emperor or any other prince:
          cannot remove that:
          then if such a sin is notorious or clear and evident,
          and especially if it is grave:
          he is not to be obeyed as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e506">d. c. si Dominus</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e508">c. non, el. 2 ea causa</ref>
          and questione and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e515">c. iulianus</ref>
          and note by 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e517">hostiensis in c. proposuit de concessione prebendarum</ref>. 
          and the reason is because the sentence cannot remove that law because in this he has no 
          power,
          in this respect he is private:
          And therefore one ought not obey him thus commanding outside his jurisdiction:
          especially in a case in which this is notorious or evident as 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e543">ff. de officio presidis. l. 3</ref>
          and Codex de iurisdictione omnium iudicum and it is an excellent argument 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e540">de privilegiis c. cum olim</ref>
          And especially because that case is supposed which is such:
          that it cannot be repaired through a superior in the manner of an appeal or restitution or 
          simple matter,
          for the reason that he who carried out such an act has no one to whom recourse can be had.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e553">
          And the reason for this is because while the support of positive law ceases:
          recourse must be had to the support of the law of nations or natural law as is clear in 
          the declaration of wars and reprisals as is clear 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e577">ff. de iustitia et iure l. ex hoc iure</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e566">23. q. 2. c. dominus noster</ref>
          But the equity of natural law demands and requires that one not be enriched with another's 
          loss 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e573">l. nam hoc natura ff. de conditione indebiti</ref>
          and an inferior not be evidently unduly burdened or oppressed by a superior 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e580">ff. de his qui sunt sui vel alieni iuris l. 2 § dominorum</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e585">C. unde vi, l. 1.</ref>
          But the remedy of the law of nations or natural law is this,
          that if there is no superior who can retract an unjust act:
          that it be null 
          <pb ed="#B" n="94-v"/>
          and held as not done. Because another remedy cannot be imagined. And through this 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e602">ff. quibus ad libertatem proclamare non licet l. 2</ref>
          works excellently. For in these matters,
          since no other remedy remains,
          it is permitted by one's own authority to act against:
          and not to obey a superior:
          indeed to declare law for oneself. all these things prepositus in form.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e614">
          The sentence of 
          <ref xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Rd1e616">baldus in de pace constantie, c. in nomine Christi</ref>
          which we placed above § 9 works well. 
          <quote xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-Qd1e623">
          But nullity is expressed in these terms namely:
          null:
          void:
          vain:
          useless:
          of no strength or validity to exist:
          not to be valid:
          not to hold:
          to have no force:
          and not to subsist by force:
          and not by law:
          not rightly or correctly or badly or wrongly and ineffectively done:
          to be weak:
          not to have firmness:
          and to be held as not judged,
          undone,
          annulled,
          void,
          null and not ratified and similar things
          </quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e642">
          <pc type="pilcrow">¶</pc> Therefore,
          since those western peoples living in their own kingdoms and lands without injury to any 
          other people or nation were not summoned nor heard:
          Indeed without a preceding cause and cognition by the Spaniards who were not judges,
          they were deprived and despoiled not only of their property and proper patrimony but also 
          of royal dignities,
          principalities,
          liberty,
          wives,
          children with all other goods,
          even life itself with the greatest torments,
          and there is no superior today in the world,
          at least in fact,
          to whom recourse can be had:
          and thus the wretched and pitiable ones remain naked,
          deprived,
          despoiled,
          unarmed,
          without help and in every way undefended,
          therefore no remedy remains for them nor can another be devised:
          except (which in truth it is) all things done concerning and against them are to be held as 
          undone.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e694">
          Not indeed that such a remedy will profit them anything:
          both for those already killed and damned in hell,
          <pb ed="#B" n="95-r"/>
          since thousands of thousands have died without faith and sacraments:
          and for the living and oppressed destitute of all hope of redemption on account of the 
          insatiable gullet of avarice to be filled. I seem to think this remedy and consolation 
          alone could at some time be had for them:
          namely by seeing on the day of judgment when all will be summoned and heard and the 
          merits of their cause will be examined just like all the others,
          and all deceit and machination of the tyrants and the nullity of their works will be 
          revealed,
          and they will be destined for eternal punishments by the sentence of the just judge. But 
          the innocence of those who suffered evils here from them (unless other sins from elsewhere 
          impede) will remain manifest,
          defended and safe.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="cy8th8-d1e506-d1e727">
          Therefore all things which were done by the Spaniards from the beginning of the discovery 
          of that world until now are null by law,
          and consequently our Catholic Kings are in that state in which they were when the 
          apostolic letters were being drawn up in Rome.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>